Welcome to Projects,
where you truly
get to put into practice what
you've learned at Code School
by writing code on your
local computer. Then having
Code School check your work.
To get started, we'll show
you how to fork and clone
a repository on GitHub.
And if you've never used Git
or GitHub before — don't worry.
We'll walk you through what you
need to know to get started.
Once you have the
code on your computer,
we'll have some tasks
for you to complete
in your editor of choice.
Then, when you've successfully
completed the tasks
and pushed your
changes to GitHub,
we'll check your code for you.
After completing a
project, you'll not only
know how to work
with that technology.
You also have a
working local project
to continue learning
with and expand upon.
And as an added bonus, you can
even earn badges on Code School
by completing projects.
Head over to the "Hello,
Code School" Project
to give Projects a try.
Or pick out a project
on a technology you want
to learn, and jump right in.