Welcome back.
In this section, we'll learn
how to write functions.
Let's write a new
program that outputs
a different greeting
message depending
on the hour of the day
that we run this program.
When we run the
program in the morning,
before noon, the program
prints "Good Morning."
In the afternoon,
and before 6 p.m.,
it prints "Good Afternoon."
And after 6 p.m., it
prints "Good Evening."
Let's see how we
can implement this.
The first thing
that we need to do
is figure out how we can grab
the current hour of the day.
To do this, we'll
import a new package
from the standard
library called time.
From this package, we'll
call the Now function
and chain it with another
function call to the Hour
function.
We'll assign the
final return value
to a variable called hourOfDay
using type inference.
Next, we'll invoke a
function called getGreeting.
Now we haven't created this
function yet, but when we do,
it will take hourOfDay
as its single argument
and we'll assign the return
value to a new variable called
greeting.
We'll create our new function
with the func keyword followed
by its name, getGreeting.
We know we want to
return a string,
so we'll define the string
data type as its return value.
We also know it takes
a single argument.
We'll call it hour.
But how do we find out which
data type this value is?
Type inference was nice enough
to let us avoid declaring type
when we created
hourOfDay up there,
but now we must find out
the data type in order
to complete this function.
How do we do that?
One way to find out
the data type returned
by a function from the
Go standard library
is by referring to the
official documentation.
If we go to the page
for the time package,
we can find the signature
of the hour function
and see that it returns
a value of type int.
And that's the type
that we need to set
for the argument from
our getGreeting function.
Not hard, right?
Our function is now complete.
And this is what every
function in Go will look like.
It will start with the
func keyword, followed
by the name of the
function, then the data type
and the arguments it expects,
and finally, the data
type that it returns.
Now we can move on to
implementing this function.
We'll return a different
greeting message
based on the hour of the day
represented by the integer
value passed as argument.
We'll create an if
condition, checking
if hour is less than 12.
Then, we'll return the
string "Good Morning."
We'll nest a new if
in the else clause
and check if hour
is less than 18.
If so, we'll return
"Good Afternoon."
Finally, if none of the
if clauses return true,
we'll return the
string "Good Evening."
And we are done
with this function.
Now we go back to
the main function
and call the print
line function,
passing the greeting
message as argument.
That's all we need.
If we run our program now, we'll
see a different output message
depending on the hour
of the day that we
run this program, as expected.
That's it for this section.
Now it's your turn to
exercise what we just
learned about functions
in the challenges.