[SINGING] Put on
your headlamp and get
ready to dig as we tunnel into
Golang, pushing past twigs.
We'll work our way underground,
programming systems
safe and sound.
Go's efficient,
simple, and fast.
Parallel work makes
coding a blast.
Now let's burrow down
and start to play.
It's time to get On
Track With Golang.
You're watching On
I'm Carlos Souza.
And in this section,
we'll learn how
to create variables and
work with data types.
Let's go back to where we
finished in the last section.
Notice here that we
referencing the os.Args already
twice from two different
places-- first,
when we read the
number of arguments,
and then again, when we want
to read the element at index 1.
This is unnecessary repetition
and the start of a code smell.
Let's see how we can fix this.
We'll create a
variable called args
and assign it the value from
os.Args using :=.
This operator tells Go to create
a new variable called args
and automatically find out the
data type for this variable
from the value that's
being assigned to it.
Once we do that, we can
use the new variable args
as the argument for
the len function
and for the print line function.
Letting the compiler
figure out or infer
the data type for a given value
is also called type inference.
Type inference is a quicker way
to assign to variables instead
of manually declaring
them before assigning
a value, also supported in
Go, as we'll see shortly.
We've mentioned static typing
as being a characteristic of Go.
Now let's talk a little
bit more about that
and see how that
relates to data types.
One way data types
can help us write
better programs is by
determining how much space
is needed to store a value.
To illustrate this, let's
look at this example.
Our gopher friends need to
store an acorn they just
found in the forest.
To store this acorn,
they choose a basket.
They pick one with just
enough storage space
and place the
acorn inside there.
The basket they pick can
perfectly accommodate
the acorn, so that's all good.
The acorn here is a
value, like the number 1,
or the string "hello."
The basket is a data type
like an integer or a string.
And placing an acorn
inside a basket
is like assigning a value
to a specific data type.
However, there are different
types of baskets out there
and many different
types of acorn.
For the next one they
find, the gophers
could make the poor decision of
choosing a basket with way
more storage space than
what's needed for that acorn.
While it would
fit in the basket,
they'd end up with a
lot of unused space.
In programming, this means
allocating more memory
than what's necessary.
Or, they could make
another mistake,
picking a box that's
too small for the acorn.
In programming, this means
not allocating enough memory
to store a value.
So for every value,
there's always
a proper data type
that determines
how that value should be
stored and the operations
that can be performed on
values of that data type.
For large acorns,
there's big baskets.
And for small acorns,
there are smaller baskets.
There are two different ways
to declare variables in Go,
using type inference or
manual type declaration.
Type inference is the
one we've just seen,
where the data type for
some value on the right
is inferred during the
assignment operation
to the newly created
variable on the left.
This is where we use the
special := operator,
and it's the most
common and preferred way
to declare variables in Go.
As an example, we can assign
the string "Hello, Gopher"
to the message variable without
having to explicitly tell
its data type.
The Go compiler figures
that out for us.
The other way to
declare variables
is via manual type declaration,
where the variable data
type is declared prior
to the assignment.
When declaring
variables this way,
we use the var keyword
followed by the variable name,
and finally, its data type.
Then, we can assign
values to it using
the regular = operator.
As an example, we declared the
message variable of type string
and then assign it the value
"Hello, Gopher" on the line
below.
Although being more verbose,
we'll see some examples
where using manual
type declaration
can be useful and
sometimes even necessary.
The ability to specify which
data types are expected
to be assigned to variables
combined with the fact
that Go programs go
through a build process
gives us static
typing, which is when
the compiler checks
for type errors
before the program is run.
In this code snippet, if we
declare a variable age of type
string, and then try
to assign the value 42,
we'll see a compiler error
during the build process,
accusing a type
mismatch, like this one--
cannot use 42 as type string.
When we change string
to int, then no errors
are raised because 42
is, in fact, an integer.
Going back to our
previous code, instead of
using type inference, we
could have manually declared
the type for os.Args, which
is a collection of strings,
indicated with his
bracket prefix,
and our code would
work the same.
Most times, type inference
and manual type declaration
can be used interchangeably,
but as we can see,
type inference is less
code to write, to read,
and much simpler to work with.
We'll look at some of these
data types more in depth later
in the course, but
here's a list of some
of the built-in types we've seen
so far in this course, which
can be found in most Go
programs-- int for integers,
used for numbers like
42, string for strings,
like "hello," bool for
booleans, either true or false,
and the collection
type we just saw--
in this example, a collection
of type strings represented
by the square brackets followed
by the string type, which
can store multiple
string values,
like "acorn" and "basket."
And that's it for this section.
Have fun in the challenges.