SINGING] Put on your headlamp,
and get ready to dig,
as we tunnel into Golang,
pushing past twigs.
We'll work our way underground,
programming systems
safe and sound.
Go's efficient, simple, and fast.
Parallel work makes
coding a blast.
Now let's burrow down
and start to play.
It's time to get
On Track With Golang.
You're watching On
Track With Golang.
I'm Carlos Souza, and in the
first section of this course,
we'll take the initial steps
into the world of the Go
programming language
and learn just enough
to write our first program.
But before we jump into code,
let's learn some of the reasons
behind Go and what
it's good for.
Go is an open-source programming
language created by Google
that makes it easy to build
simple and efficient programs.
Here are some of its
main characteristics.
First, Go is a
compiled language,
meaning we must run our source
code through a compiler, which
reads that source code and
generates a single binary,
or executable file, which we
can use to run our program.
Throughout this
course, we'll talk
about data types like integers,
strings, and booleans,
and we'll learn that the
Go compiler validates
operations involving these
types before we run our program.
This leaves less room
for unexpected surprises
when we do run our
program, and places
Go in the category of
statically typed languages.
Programs written in
Go are fast and can
scale really well, thanks to
a concurrency model that's
built into the language
and quite easy to use.
We'll take a closer look at
concurrency in the last level.
Go programs are
also easy to deploy
because the compiler generates
a single executable file.
Sometimes, deploying a
Go program to production
can be as simple as copying the
executable over to the server.
And last but not
least, it's a language
that's just fun to write.
Now, the natural next question
is what types of programs
should we use Go for?
And the answer is
systems programming.
Systems programming is
a type of programming
aimed at servicing other systems
as opposed to servicing users
directly.
These lower-level programs
more often than not
will not expose a
graphical user interface,
like links and
forms and buttons,
but instead they'll run
straight from the terminal
or the command line.
For those with experience
in building web
or mobile applications,
I know this
sounds a little
different than usual,
but here's a quick
comparison-- programs that
provide services
directly to humans
are called application programs.
These allow regular
end users, most times
without any
technical background,
to perform common tasks.
Examples of these
types of programs
include e-commerce, to-do
list apps, text editors,
and music players.
Programs that provide
services to other programs
are called system programs.
Examples include APIs, game
engines, network applications,
and command-line applications,
just to name a few.
These are usually
resource constrained
and must perform really fast.
And that's where
Go really shines.
In this course, we'll look at
the most common features used
when writing programs in Go.
These include how to
build and run programs,
importing and creating
packages, basic constructs
like functions, variables,
loops, conditionals,
how to work with
different data types,
and finally, how to
write concurrent code
using goroutines.
Now, let's start
writing some code.
Our first Go program will
be a simple Hello World.
We'll write our code to
a single source code
file, then compile that
file using the Go compiler,
which generates a single
binary, or executable file.
Running the program, we'll
print a message to the console--
"Hello.
I am Gopher."
Now let's see how
we can write this.
We'll create a new project for
our program and call it hello.
Here on the left is a
typical Go workspace.
The source folder is the
root for all our Go projects,
and we'll create a new folder
for each separate project,
like we're doing
here with hello.
Under the new folder, we
can find a Go source code
file with the .go extension.
Since this Hello World program
will have a single file,
we'll call it main.go.
And this is a naming
convention, not a rule.
Inside our main.go file, the
very first thing we write
is the package
definition, package main.
Then, we define
the main function
using the func keyword.
This function is the entry
point for our Go program.
All Go programs must have a main
package and a main function.
In order to write
to the console,
we'll need to import a package
from the Go standard library,
called fmt, which
stands for format.
Package imports go after
the package definition.
Then, from inside
the main function,
we'll call the print line
function from the fmt package,
giving it the string, "Hello.
I am Gopher."
Notice semicolons are
not necessary in Go,
and this is all the code
that we need for now.
Now let's see how we
can run this program.
Remember we talked about
the compiler, which
read source code and
produces an executable file?
Well, this process of
reading source code,
resolving package
dependencies, and generating
a single, executable file
is called a build process.
In order to build
our Go project,
we use the build
command, shipped with Go.
We run go build from the
project root folder, hello.
The compiler will produce
an executable file
named after the project,
hello, but with no extension.
Using this file, we
can run the program
and see the message printed
to the screen, "Hello.
I am Gopher."
Those with a background
in interpreted languages
like Ruby, Python,
or PHP might be
wondering if
there's a way to run
Go programs without this
intermediate compilation step.
And the answer is yes.
We can use go run, another
command that's shipped with Go
and give it the main
file name, main.go.
With a single command, our
program will be built and run,
and we can see the same message
printed to the console--
"Hello.
I am Gopher."
While we'll rarely see go
run being used in production,
this command is quite
handy for development,
and it's what we'll use for
the remainder of this course.
Another command
that's shipped with Go
and can greatly increase
productivity and development
is called go fmt.
We can use this command
to format Go source code.
Let's take a look
at this example.
Here on the left, we have
the same Hello World code
we wrote before,
except now, it's
formatted a little different.
There's weird line breaks,
random white spaces,
and it's pretty
inconsistent overall.
While this is still valid
syntax and will run just fine,
it's very hard for
humans to understand.
To fix this, we can
run go fmt and give it
the filename, main.go.
We'll also use the -w flag
to tell the go fmt command
to write the results back to
the original source file instead
of its default behavior of
printing out to the console.
Once we do that, we can
see the code is now
a lot easier to understand.
There are many benefits to
following go fmt's formatting
rules instead of coming up with
our own individual standards.
First and foremost, we get to
avoid most debates around code
styles.
We know developers have
preferences of their own,
but with a tool like go fmt
doing most of the work for us,
it's not that hard to adopt
a new style that everybody
can agree on.
Also, by not having to
worry about minor concerns,
it becomes easier to write,
read, and maintain programs.
To make it even easier to
incorporate go fmt into our Go
toolbelt, many plugins are
available for text editors
that will take care of
running that command for us.
For example, we
can have it set up
where go fmt is run
on every file save.
Or, we could create a
pre-commit hook in git
that uses go fmt to check
formatting before each commit.
That's it for this
first section.
Have fun writing your first
Go program in the challenges,
and I'll see you back here.