[SINGING] Put on your headlamp
and get ready to dig
as we tunnel into Golang,
pushing past twigs.
We'll work our
way underground,
programming systems
safe and sound.
Go's efficient,
simple, and fast.
Parallel work makes
coding a blast.
Now let's burrow down
and start to play.
It's time to get
On Track With Golang.
You are watching On
Track With Golang.
I'm Carlos Souza and
in this section,
we'll learn about interfaces.
The program we'll write now will
loop through a list of gophers
and call the jump method
on each one of them.
To write this, we'll
use a combination
of things we've learned
in the course so far
and the code might start
looking a little bit complex,
so we'll take it step by step.
First, we'll create
a getList method
that returns a slice
with pointers to gophers.
This is what the brackets
and the star symbol mean.
When calling this
function from main,
we'll assign the return
value to a new variable
called gopherList.
Then, we'll create a
for loop and use range
to read each element
from gopherList.
Using the underline
character, we
ignore the index
for each iteration
and grab each gopher directly.
Then, from inside
the for loop, we
call the jump method
on each gopher
and print the result
to the console.
Static typing is what allows
the Go compiler to ensure
that every element
returned by getList
responds to the jump
method so we can safely
call this method for each
gopher returned from range.
Now let's see how we can
implement the getList function.
From inside getList, we'll
create two gophers, Phil
and Noodles.
We'll grab their pointers
with the ampersand symbol,
and then create a new slice
with those pointers using
the same bracket and star
symbol combination we
have in the function signature.
Lastly, we'll return the slice.
If we run the code now, we
can see it prints the message,
"Phil can jump HIGH" and
"Noodles can still jump."
Turns out other
types can also jump.
There are other struct
types like horse
with different properties,
name and weight,
but the same method
signature, a jump
method that returns a string.
The implementation of jump for
a horse checks for the weight
and prints a message if it's
greater than 2,500 kilos
and another message if it's not.
Now let's go back to
our getList function
and create a horse struct.
We'll give it the name
Barbaro and weight, 2,000.
Now if we try to add the new
horse to our existing slice,
we'll run into an error.
We cannot combine both a gopher
and a horse under the same
slice of type star gopher.
In fact, a horse
is not a gopher.
But they do share similar
behavior, so there is a way.
We'll do this by
creating an interface.
Interfaces provide a
way to specify behavior.
If something can do this,
then it can be used here.
We'll create a new
interface called jumper
using the type keyword--
the same type keyword
we used to create a struct.
Then, give it the name
of the interface, jumper,
and the primitive type it
inherits from, interface.
Inside the interface, we
declare a method signature
that is expected to be
present in all types that
implement this interface.
Then we go back to the
getList function and change
the return value to be a
collection of jumper types,
not gopher anymore.
Notice the star
symbol is not needed
in the function signature
when returning interfaces.
And we change the type
of slice created
in the function
body to type jumper.
All types belonging
to this slice
must comply with the
jumper interface.
In other words, they must
implement a jump method.
In Go, types implement
interfaces implicitly
simply by implementing
the methods that
were declared on the interface.
Both gopher and horse
have a jump method
with the exact same signature,
so we can add both types
under the slice of type jumper.
Now back to our
main function, we'll
rename our variables to better
reflect the type changes
that we've just made.
We'll assign the
return from getList
to a variable called
jumperList and the return
from range to a
variable called jumper.
The compiler does not
care about naming,
so we could name these something
else like list and element.
But we always want to make
sure that the code we write
is easily readable
by other humans,
so it's always good to
favor meaningful names.
If we run this
code again, we can
see it still prints the
same messages as before.
And now, a message
from horse as well.
I will jump.
[HORSE NEIGHS]
There is a reason, however,
that we use the name
jumper for our interface.
A convention in Go for
naming one method interfaces
is to start with the method name
and then add an "er" suffix.
Because we had a jump method,
we named our interface jumper.
Some examples from the
Go standard library
that use this convention
include the reader interface
with the read method
and the writer interface
with the write method.
That's it for this section.
Now it's your turn to write some
interfaces in the challenges.