Welcome back.
In this section, we'll learn
how to make our code easier
to work with by
creating packages.
Going back to where we stopped
in the last section with our code,
we'll notice that
as we keep adding
more code to the
main file, this file
will grow long and complicated.
Even though it's all split
into structs and methods,
it's somewhat unorganized and
still too much code to look at.
All that really
matters in this file
is the code inside
the main function.
So let's see what we can do
with all this other code.
One way to refactor files
that are growing too long
is to create project
packages and move
some of that extra code
over to these packages.
A new package is a folder within
the project that holds logic
for a specific part of the
program that doesn't belong
inside the main function.
Here's our current
project structure.
Inside the root
folder, hello, we
have the entry point for our
program in the file main.go.
We'll create a new package
called model, represented
by a folder with the same name.
Inside this folder, we'll
create a new main.go file,
a naming convention
in Go for packages
that only have one file.
The first thing we do
inside this new file
is to define our new package
with the package model
statement.
Then, we can start
moving some code over
from the old main.go
file in the hello folder
to this new package file.
In order to be accessed
from outside packages,
identifiers must be
explicitly exported
by adopting an uppercase
naming convention
for the first letter.
So we change the name
for the GetList function
by making the first
letter uppercase.
Back to the main source
code file in the program,
we can import our new package
by using the import statement
followed by the project name,
hello, slash the new package
name, model.
From inside the
main function, we
can call the GetList function,
now part of the model package
namespace, and assign the
result to jumperList, just
like before.
However, if we try calling the
jump method like we were doing
before, we'll see
an error like this--
cannot refer to unexported
field or method jump.
This means the jump method
that we're trying to call
was not properly exported
from the model package.
References to
unexported identifiers
will cause the Go compiler to
raise errors like this one.
Let's see how we can fix this.
Interface methods and their
corresponding implementations
must also be
capitalized in order
to be accessed from
other packages.
Going back to our
model package, we'll
change the jump method
names to uppercase,
both on the method signatures
and on the interface.
Only the method names
need to be exported,
not the structs or the interface.
Now if we try to
run your code again,
we can see it works fine,
and prints the jump message
for each of our jumpers.
And notice how the
source code in this file
is now a lot easier to read.
That's it for this section.
Now it's your turn to create
packages in the challenges,
and I'll see you back
here for the last section.