Welcome back.
In this section, we'll
look at arrays and slices.
One way we can
create arrays in Go
is with manual type declaration.
Let's write a new program
that stores the name of three
programming languages
in an array,
and then prints them
back to the console.
When creating arrays in Go
via manual type declaration,
we must set a specific size.
To create our new array, we
use the var keyword, then
the name of the variable,
langs, and then the array type,
brackets, with the max number
of elements, in this case 3.
Lastly, the type of data that
this array will hold-- string.
This array will hold no
more than 3 string elements.
And if we run this
program right now,
we can see it
prints to the screen
the zero value for our
array, an empty array.
We can add elements to
an array by assigning
to each specific index.
Remember-- index
count starts at zero,
so the first element
Go is assigned
index 0, then Ruby to index 1,
and JavaScript to index 2.
When we run this
program, we can see
the array along
with all its elements
is printed to the console.
Adding more elements to an array
than what was initially stated
will crash our program.
It will raise an
out-of-bounds error.
If we try assigning
an element to index 3,
the compiler generates
the following error--
invalid array index 3.
The compiler is basically
saying, "You said 3.
Now you want to add 4."
Using arrays and setting
a max number of elements
can help the compiler
prevent some errors,
but it also removes
some flexibility.
Let's look at another type that
enhances arrays called slices.
The slice type is
built on top of array
to provide more power
and convenience.
Most array
programming in Go is
done with slices rather
than simple arrays
because slices are more flexible.
Declaring a slice works
similar to declaring an array,
except we leave out the
max number of elements.
This creates a slice
with a zero value of nil.
Is this bad?
No, not at all.
A nil slice behaves the
same as an empty slice.
It can be appended to using
the append function, which
takes two arguments-- a
slice and a variable number
of arguments, could be one or
many, but in this example,
we'll use just one.
We call the append
function multiple times,
passing first the
slice we want to append
to, and then the element that
we want to append to that slice.
If we run this
code, we can see Go,
Ruby, JavaScript, and LOLcode
printed to the console.
That's it for this section.
Now it's your turn to play
with arrays and slices
in the challenges.