[SINGING] Put on your headlamp,
and get ready to dig.
As we tunnel into Golang,
pushing past twigs.
We'll work our way
underground,
programming systems
safe and sound.
Go's efficient,
simple, and fast.
Parallel work makes
coding a blast!
Now let's burrow down
and start to play.
It's time to get On
Track With Golang.
You're watching On
I'm Carlos Souza,
and in this section,
we'll learn about the for loop.
Unlike other languages
that offer multiple options
for building loops, the for
loop is the only looping
construct available, and
the only one we'll ever need
when writing programs in Go.
As we'll see, it
is very flexible
and allows us to build
loops in many different ways.
Here's the canonical or the
complete form of the for loop.
The first thing
we might notice is
that just like the
if statement, there
are no parentheses in for loops.
We use the for keyword, followed
by three components that
control the loop--
the init statement,
executed before the
first iteration;
the condition
expression, evaluated
before every iteration; and
the post statement, executed
at the end of every iteration.
Let's see what this
looks like in practice.
Let's write a
simple program using
a for loop that
iterates five times
and prints numbers from 0 to 4.
We can use the
:= assignment
on the init statement to
create a new variable.
We'll call it i, and
initialize it to 0.
The condition expression will
check that i is less than 5.
If it is, it will run
the loop and at the end
execute the post statement,
which increments i by 1.
This is what the ++ sign does.
Inside the loop, we'll print
the current value for i.
When we run this program,
we can see numbers 0
through 4 printed
to the console.
The for loop components
are actually optional.
We can create loops that use
variables declared previously
in our code and have a single
condition expression like this.
Here, we create both
i and isLessThanFive,
and assign them 0 and
true, respectively.
Then, we'll create a for
loop with only a condition,
and we'll leave out the
init and post components.
For the condition
expression, we'll
simply use the
isLessThanFive variable.
As long as this
variable is true,
this loop will continue to run.
Then, from inside
the loop, we'll
print the i variable
just like before.
And at the end, we'll
increment i using the ++ sign.
In order to break
from this loop,
since it does not
have a post statement,
we'll need to change the
value for the variable used
in the condition expression.
We'll write an if statement
that checks whether i
is greater than or equal to 5.
And if it is, it changes
the isLessThanFive variable
to false, which stops the
loop before the next run.
If we run our code now it
will not only print numbers
from 0 to 4, but also 5.
This is because our if statement
simply changes the flag,
but the condition
expression will not
be evaluated until the next run.
It's also common to write
for loops with no components
at all.
In this example, we're still
creating and initializing
the variable i to 0, but that's
the only variable we'll use.
To break out of this loop, we'll
use the break keyword, which
stops the loop immediately.
When we run this program, we can
see it prints numbers 0 to 4.
It does not get to 5.
Lastly, here's something we'll
find in a lot of networking
programs, an infinite loop.
Infinite loops are
useful for setting up
network listeners that wait
for connections from clients.
Say we have
someListeningFunction,
an example function
that runs and waits
for connections
across the network.
We run this program and it
never finishes executing.
The infinite for loop
holds the process
and runs indefinitely,
either until something
internal to someListeningFunction
breaks out of the loop, or until
we manually kill this process.
That's it for this section.
Now it's your turn to exercise
loops in the challenges.