Welcome back.
In this section, we'll learn
about writing conditionals,
reading user-supplied arguments
from the command line,
and package imports.
Let's write a new program.
And here's how
it's going to work.
It's going to read a
user-supplied argument
from the command line and
print it back to the console.
For example, when run go
run main.go, and give it
the string argument
"Into the tunnel,"
we want to see that argument
printed back to the console.
If we run the program
with no argument,
like we see here
below, then we'll
print the default message
"Hello, I am Gopher."
We'll use the same main.go
source file for this,
with the main package
definition up at the top,
and the package fmt
import right below.
Then, from inside
the main function,
the first thing we'll do
is add an if statement.
Unlike other languages,
if statements in Go
require no parentheses,
but the if and else blocks
must be enclosed
in curly braces.
Next, we'll use the
len function built
into Go, which
takes one argument
and returns its length.
We'll talk about this
argument in just a second.
But for now, we'll check
if the return from len
is greater than 1.
If len is less
than or equal to 1,
then the program flows
into the else block.
Being a built-in
function means that len
can be invoked directly
without us having
to import any specific package.
Now the next step is
to pass an argument
to len, which will be os.Args.
Os.Args is an array containing
all arguments passed
to the running
program, including
the name of the
program itself along
with any user-supplied
arguments from the command line.
Next, the os package
from the standard library
must be added to the
import list in order for us
to access its args property.
Our program is still unfinished.
But let's see what it would look
like if we run this right now.
We'll type go run, give it the
name of the program, name.go,
and the argument
"Into the tunnel."
When running this, the
element at index 0 on Args
is the name of the
temporary executable created
by the go run command.
And the element
at index 1 on Args
would be the string
"Into the tunnel."
But we're not done yet with our
program, so let's finish it.
From inside the if block, we'll
call the print line function
and give it the element on index
1 of the os.Args array, which
is the argument supplied by
the user from the command line.
From the else block, which will
be executed when no argument is
passed from the
command line, we'll
print the default
message, "Hello.
I am Gopher."
Now our program is complete.
Let's run it again and
give it that same argument,
"Into the tunnel."
Again, index 0 will be
the name of the program
and index 1 will
be the argument.
Since we have two elements in
os.Args, the return from len
is 2 and the if statement
evaluates to true.
The if block is run and we
see "Into the tunnel" printed
to the console.
Now when we run the
program with no arguments,
only index 0 on os.Args
is assigned a value
and the call to the
len function returns 1.
The if statement evaluates to
false so the else block is run
and the default message is
printed to the console--
"Hello.
I am Gopher."
Now let's pause
here for a moment
and take a look at what would
happen if we'd forgotten
to import the os package.
If you try to run
your code like this,
then the Go compiler
will raise an error
during the build process,
looking something
like this-- undefined--
os in os.Args.
We'll see this message repeated
for every line in our program
that's referencing
the os package.
The compiler is basically
saying, "I don't
know where os is coming from."
We could just add the os
package to the import list
like we did before,
but let's take a look
at another tool
that's shipped with Go
and can help us with that.
Goimports automatically
detects missing packages
and updates import statements
in the source code.
So on our source code file
with the missing os package,
we can run goimports and give
it that same -w flag, which
means we want to
write the results back
to the original file and give
it the name of the file we
want to fix, main.go.
Goimports will
detect all references
to packages not
imported in this file
and will automatically import
those packages for us--
in this example, the os package.
As a bonus, goimports
also formats code
according to go fmt.
As we can see here with
the parens and line
breaks after each package name.
Our file is now fixed so
we can safely build and run
our program again.
Just like before, running
it with no arguments,
we get the default message.
And running it with an
argument prints that argument
to the console.
And that's it for
this first level.
Have fun in the challenges.