Welcome back.
In this section, we'll
learn the difference
between values and references,
and how to work with pointers.
Let's add a new feature
to our existing program,
the validation of
a gopher's age.
To implement this feature,
we'll add a new property
to our gopher structure,
called isAdult.
This property will determine
whether a gopher is an adult,
and will be of type Boolean.
In other words, it will only
hold the values true or false.
Then, we'll create a new
function that takes a gopher
struct as its argument.
This function will check
if a gopher is of age,
and then set a value on the
isAdult property from the struct
passed as an argument.
If gopher is of age, then
we'll set isAdult to true.
Otherwise, we'll
set it to false.
This pattern of passing an
argument to a function,
and writing to that argument
from inside the function,
can be found in parts of
Go's standard library,
like the scan method from
the database package.
The zero value for the
boolean type is false.
Remember?
This will be the initial
value for isAdult,
when you create a new
gopher without assigning
to this property.
When we run this code, we
can see isAdult is false.
Now let's implement our
validation function.
We'll call it validateAge.
This new function takes one
argument and writes to the
isAdult property
of this argument.
The function does
not return anything.
In this code, we can
see we're passing a type
gopher as an argument to
the validateAge function.
So this function should
accept either a type gopher,
or something that's
compatible with it.
Let's see what happens if
the argument type is gopher.
When we call validateAge, then
a copy of the original struct
will be created and received as
the argument to the function.
When we assign to the
isAdult property,
we assign to the copy
of the gopher, and not
the original gopher.
And this line assigns
true to g.isAdult.
When we print the
gopher to the console,
we'll see that isAdult
property is still false.
This is because the
validateAge function
wrote to a copy of the gopher
that was passed as an argument,
not to the original gopher.
To understand the reason
for this behavior,
we have to understand the
difference between values
and references.
Now this is not an easy
concept in programming.
So to help illustrate this,
we'll use music playlists
as an analogy.
Say we have two
albums, one called
Are You Gonna Go My Way?
and one called Milo
Goes to College.
The first album has
songs A, B, and C.
And the second album,
songs D, E, and F.
Then say we decide to create
a playlist so we can listen
to it while we do some coding.
We'll call this playlist
Music for Programming,
and we'll pick three songs
off these two albums here
on the left that we can
assign to the playlist
here on the right.
Let's see how we can
create this playlist using
two approaches, one with
values and the other one
with references.
With values, we'd create
copies from each one
of the original songs, and
then assign those copies
to the new playlist.
The playlist would contain
individual and independent
copies of the original songs.
Now the second,
and more efficient
way to create this playlist
is by storing references
to the original songs.
The playlist would
work the same,
but instead of creating
multiple copies of each song,
it would have slots pointing
back to the original songs.
This would allow for
the same end result,
but with a much more efficient
usage of storage space.
Now let's look at
another example
of values and references in Go.
We'll start with an example of
passing around data as value.
Here, we assign the string
Go to the variable language.
Behind the scenes, a
primitive string value
is assigned to the new
variable, language,
and this variable is
stored in a memory address.
Say, this one.
Now, if we assign the
value from language
to a new variable,
favoriteLanguage,
then a new memory
address is created
for this new variable
which receives
a copy of the original data.
At the end of the day, we'll
be using two different memory
addresses to store two
versions of the data that
look exactly the same.
This is using memory
unnecessarily.
Now if we pass around data by
reference, here's what happens.
We start by assigning
Go to language, just
like we did before.
And again, a primitive is
assigned to a new variable,
and a new memory
address is created.
Now when assigning this
variable to a new variable,
we'll use the ampersand symbol.
What this will do is
return a reference
to the existing memory address,
taking us to the original data.
In this example, a single
memory address is being used.
This means not creating
copies of the data
and using memory
more efficiently.
Now that we've gone over the
differences between values
and references, let's go back to
the code that started all this.
If you remember,
what we wanted to do
was figure out how to pass the
original gopher as an argument
to the validateAge function, so
that changes made to the gopher
from inside this function
were reflected back
to the original data.
In order to assign a
reference to a new variable,
we've learned we can use
the ampersand operator
to return a pointer.
Let's use that operator
when creating a gopher.
This way, when we pass it as
a reference to validateAge,
we'll be passing a reference
to the original data
and not creating a copy.
Next, we need to
find out which data
type to use on the validateAge
function signature.
We can't simply
use a gopher type.
If we do, check
out what happens.
When we run our program,
we'll see an error message,
like this one, "cannot use
Phil type *gopher as type
gopher."
We're using the wrong type.
To fix this, we must use
the *gopher data type
as the parameter, indicating
a pointer to the struct.
When we do that, we can
properly read values,
and assign to properties
on the original gopher.
Now when we run our
code, we can see
that the original value
from the struct is changed,
and it prints true for
the isAdult property.
You'll also notice the ampersand
on the output in the console,
indicating this is a pointer
to an underlying struct.
So we've learned some pretty
advanced stuff in this section.
Now it's your turn to practice
them in the challenges.