[SINGING] Put on your headlamp
and get ready to dig.
As we tunnel into Golang,
pushing past twigs.
We'll work our way underground,
programming systems
safe and sound.
Go's efficient, simple, and fast.
Parallel work makes
coding a blast.
Now let's burrow down
and start to play.
It's time to get
On Track With Golang.
You are watching On
Track With Golang.
I'm Carlos Souza,
and in this section,
we'll learn how to add
structure to data using structs.
Not many people know this, but
our gopher friends' ability
to jump is based on their age.
Let's use the following
example to describe
the logic for gopher jumps.
We'll start with two variables--
gopher1Name and gopher1Age.
We'll assign them Phil and 30.
Notice we're using the
type inference operator,
so we don't have to worry about
explicitly declaring the type.
If gopher1Age is
less than 65, we'll
call the highJump function.
This function takes
a string and prints
to the console the name
of the gopher followed by
"can jump HIGH."
If we run this code, we can see
it prints "Phil can jump HIGH."
Despite the odds, even the
more experienced gophers
can keep up with the youngsters.
Here's a second set
of instructions.
We create two more variables,
gopher2Name and gopher2Age.
Noodles is 90 years
old, which causes
the conditional to return false
since 90 is not less than 65,
so the else block will run
and lowJump will be called.
The message "Noodles can
still jump" is printed.
The code we've written
so far works fine,
but if we put it all
together under the same file,
we'll notice it's going to
look a little bit confusing.
For each new gopher that
we add, two variables
need to be created and
another if statement.
On top of that, logic rules
for highJump and lowJump
are exposed because they're
part of the same file.
All of this indicates that our
code is leaking logic details.
Let's see if we can fix that.
Even in procedural
languages like Go,
there are ways that we can
hide unnecessary implementation
details from the caller.
Check out this snippet.
You might not know
exactly what it's doing yet,
but I bet you think this
looks cleaner and easier
to understand than
the previous code.
So before, we were
over here on the left
where our code was leaking
implementation details.
And what we want
to do is get here
on the right, where the code
is properly encapsulated.
Let's see how we can do that.
We're going to do
this using a struct.
A struct allows us to
group named properties
under a single
abstraction, a single name.
To declare a struct,
we use the type keyword,
indicating a new type is
to be declared, and give it
the name of the new struct
type we're declaring, gopher.
That's the name of the struct.
Then we specify the underlying
type primitive, a struct.
Inside curly braces, we
define our properties
with the respective types.
We'll create a property
name of type string
and then a property
age of type integer.
To use our newly created struct,
we need to allocate memory.
The simplest way to allocate
memory and assign values
to a struct is using something
called a struct literal,
similar to a slice literal.
To do that, we use
the name of the struct
and pass it the initial
values between curly braces.
Here, we create gopher1 with
the name property set to Phil
and the age property set to 30.
Then gopher2 with the name
property set to Noodles
and the age property set to 90.
Remember-- the
struct creation code
goes inside the main function,
but the struct declaration code
must be placed outside main.
A struct contains behavior
in the form of methods.
And the way that we
define methods on a struct
is similar to how we
define regular functions.
We start with the
func keyword, but then
instead of the function
name, we follow it
with the receiver of the
function in parentheses.
The receiver is the type we'll
use to call this function from.
In this example, the
receiver is the type gopher.
Then, after the
receiver, we have
the name of the function, jump.
And lastly, the data type
for the return value,
which will be a string.
From inside this method,
we can access properties
from gopher via the
explicit receiver
that we declare on the
function signature, which
is the gopher struct that we'll
be calling this method from.
We can read the age property
with g.age and the name
property with g.name.
This is the same
logic we had before,
but now part of this method.
If age is less than
65, we'll return
the name of the gopher followed
by the string "can jump HIGH."
Otherwise, it returns the
name of the gopher followed
by the string, "can still jump."
We can now go back
to the main function
and simply call the jump method
on each one of our gophers.
And our code will still
behave the same as before,
but it looks a lot cleaner.
This is the first step into
hiding implementation details
from the caller
of this function.
One thing that can
help us remember
this type of refactoring is call
the "tell, don't ask" principle.
This principle states that
rather than asking for data
and acting on it,
instead, we should simply
tell the program what to do.
Let's look at this example.
Here on the left, we ask
for gopherAge and check
if it's less than 65.
It's up to us, the caller,
to determine whether or not
to call the highJump function
or the lowJump function.
This is the asking version.
Now the same logic expressed in
a telling way looks like this.
We have the definition of what
a gopher is and how it jumps,
but then when we want
to perform a jump,
we simply call the jump method.
All the logic of how
the jump should behave
is encapsulated
inside this method.
That's it for this section.
Now it's your turn to practice
structs in the challenges.