In this section, we'll learn
what to do when things go south
and how to work
with errors in Go.
Our rodent friends
have a problem.
Turns out some people have
been running this program way
too early and waking up the
gophers from their sleep.
Let's change our program
so that it is not
allowed to be run before 7 a.m.
If that happens, it should exit
immediately with an error code.
The way we communicate
errors in Go
is via a separate return value.
Any function that can
potentially generate an error
should declare an error data
type as part of its signature.
Back to our example, we'll
update the getGreeting function
to return two values
instead of one.
We'll keep our string and add
a second return type of error.
Then, from the
function body, we'll
add an if statement to check
whether hour is less than 7.
In other words,
whether this function
is being invoked before 7 a.m.
Remember when we talked
about the two different ways
to declare variables, one being
manually declaring the data
type before we
assign it a value?
Well, this is what we'll use
for the message variable.
We'll declare the message
variable first thing
in the function
outside the if block.
We use the var keyword followed
by the variable name message
and its data type, string.
Then, from inside
the block, we'll
return the newly
declared message
variable along with the
new error we create,
separated by a comma.
To create an error, we'll need
to import the errors package
from the standard library.
Notice that message has not
been assigned an initial value
and this is totally fine.
When we declare variables
in Go, they're automatically
assigned an initial value.
A zero value is what's assigned
by default to variables
without an explicit
initial value.
Each data type is assigned
a different zero value.
String types are
assigned an empty string.
Integers are assigned zero,
and booleans are assigned false.
We won't be covering all
data types in this course,
but here's a list with
some more data types
and their respective
zero values.
The complete list of zero
values for each data type
can be found in
the official docs.
Now let's update the rest
of the getGreeting function
to reflect the latest changes.
Instead of straight up
returning the greeting message
like we were doing before,
we'll now assign it
to the message variable.
Since we've previously
declared this variable,
we'll use the = to
assign the proper message
depending on what time it is.
Finally, we'll return
the message variable
with whatever value was
assigned to it depending
on the hour of the day
and an explicit nil.
The nil value for
error indicates
that no errors occurred during
the execution of this function.
Now let's go back
to the main function
and see how we can
call getGreeting.
The getGreeting function
now returns two values--
the message and an error.
In Go, we can assign
multiple values at once
by separating the
variables using a comma,
like we're doing here--
getGreeting, comma, error.
Whenever dealing with a
function that returns an error,
it's a common practice to
always check for that error
before proceeding
with the execution.
We do that with an if
statement, checking if the error
variable is different than nil.
If it is, then we know
some error occurred,
and we'll deal with that
inside this if block.
The way we'll deal
with this error for now
is by printing it
to the console.
This is a nice way
to help whoever's
running this program
figure out what caused
the error in the first place.
Then, we'll want to terminate
this program immediately
and inform the caller
that an error occurred.
One way we can
do that is by using
what's called an exit code.
Exit codes are a POSIX standard
that many operating systems
comply to.
An exit code of 1 means
the program has finished,
but errors have occurred.
To exit with an error, we'll use
our old friend, the os package,
in the exit function,
passing it the number 1.
That's it for our program.
Let's go back and see
how it's working now.
If we run the
code now, it still
prints the proper greeting
messages after 7 a.m.,
but if we run it
before 7 a.m., it
prints the error message
"Too early for greetings!"
The exit code 1 is also returned
so that other programs using
our program are informed
that an error occurred
and can act accordingly.
It's the end of this level.
Now it's your turn to work with
some errors in the challenges.