In this section,
we'll learn about one
of the most talked about
features of Go-- goroutines.
But before we talk
about goroutines,
let's take a step back so we can
understand why they even exist.
Consider the following
search engine, "Big Search."
Big Search allows us
to type in a keyword
and it will search the
web for three things--
websites, images, and videos.
Depending on how Big
Search is implemented,
there are a couple different
ways this search can happen.
We could implement Big Search
as a sequential program.
In sequential programs,
before a new task starts,
the previous one must finish.
If Big Search was
coded this way,
here's how it could behave.
It would start with the
first search, say, website.
Only when that
search was finished,
it would move on to the
next search, images.
Then when that was
complete, it would move
on to the last one, videos.
The total time in
sequential programs
is the sum of all the tasks.
So if the search for website
took 2 seconds, the search
for images took 3 seconds,
and the search for videos
took 4 seconds,
then the total time
would be 2 plus 3 plus
for 4-- 9 seconds.
Now in concurrent
programs, multiple tasks
can be executed independently
and may appear simultaneous.
If Big Search was
programmed this way,
we would see results from
websites, images, and videos
showing up in what would
appear to be the same time.
Under the hood,
each search would
be split into small
chunks and those chunks
would alternate execution.
The total time would still be
the sum of all the tasks, 9
seconds, but tasks would
alternate time slices,
giving the impression
they're running together.
Finally, in parallel
programs, multiple tasks
can be executed at the same
time in multi-core machines,
or machines with multiple CPUs.
If Big Search was programmed
and run as a parallel program,
then website, image,
and video searches
would all be performing
at the same time
and the total time
for search would be
the time for the slowest task.
Videos is the slowest task, so
the total time of the search
would be 4 seconds.
I know this might sound
a little bit confusing
if it's the first time
you're hearing about it,
but the important
thing to remember
is that concurrency
is not parallelism.
Concurrency means
independent, which
is a necessary step
towards parallelism,
which means simultaneous.
Go's concurrency
model and goroutines
make it simple to build
parallel programs that
take advantage of machines
with multiple processors, most
machines today.
A goroutine is a
special function in Go
that executes concurrently
with other functions.
We can create them
with the go keyword.
Yes.
Go is also a keyword.
In this first example, we
have functions f and g.
This is a sequential
program, so function g
must wait until f is finished in
order to run, like we see here.
In this other example, we create
a goroutine and run f on it.
Because our main program
also runs in a goroutine
by default, then both f and g
will be executed concurrently
like we see here.
This is the first step into
writing concurrent programs,
but it's worth noting that
on single-core machines,
concurrent code is unlikely
to perform any better
than sequential code.
Now let's write a new
program to demonstrate
concurrency and parallelism.
This new program creates
a slice of strings
using a slice literal
with initial values
Phil, Noodles, and Barbaro.
Then, we'll loop
through each element
and invoke a function,
printName, which
takes a single string argument.
The printName function
takes this string argument
and simply prints
it to the console.
We'll run our
program with go run
and use the Unix
time command to track
the duration of the execution.
As we can see, it takes 321
milliseconds, less than half
a second, to run and
print each name.
Now let's simulate a
time-consuming task
on printName and we'll
do this by adding
a very costly mathematical
operation using the math
package from Go's
standard library.
Inside the printName method,
we'll create a for loop
and execute a time-consuming
computation 100 million times
before printing the name.
This computation will keep
the processor very busy.
When we add heavy
processing to printName,
we can see a big increase
in execution time.
When we run our
code again, we can
see it went from 321
milliseconds to 11.6 seconds.
It's running each call to
printName sequentially,
so before one starts, the
previous one needs to finish
and it completely
blocks the processor
while it's doing
the math operation.
The first step into making
this code concurrent
is to use the go keyword
to create a goroutine
for each call to printName.
However, Go programs
are not automatically
aware of newly
created goroutines.
So if we run this program,
the main function exits
before the goroutines
are finished.
That's why we'll see it takes
less than a second to run
the program, but it does
not print any names.
Don't worry.
There's a built-in
solution in Go for this.
We'll synchronize our code
using the sync package
from Go's standard library.
From that package, we'll use
the WaitGroup data type
to make our program wait for
our newly created goroutines
to finish.
So we import the sync package
and declare a new variable, wg,
from the sync.WaitGroup
data type.
We'll use the Add method to
set the number of goroutines
to wait for.
Instead of hard coding
the number of goroutines,
we'll use the len function
to return that number for us
based on the number of
elements from the names slice.
Then, we'll use the Wait
method to prevent the program
from exiting before
all goroutines being
tracked by our WaitGroup
are finished executing.
Lastly, the Done
method from WaitGroup
must be called at the end
of each function that's
running on a goroutine.
To do that, the printName
method must be given a reference
to the original
WaitGroup so that we
call Done on the original
value and not on a copy.
We use the ampersand symbol
here to pass a reference.
Remember that?
Calling the Done method from
the printName function running
inside a goroutine--
it's kind of like saying
to the WaitGroup-- hey,
there's one less goroutine
you need to wait for.
Just letting you know.
Our code is done.
Let's run the program
now, but let's specify
we want to use
one processor.
We do this by setting the
GOMAXPROCS environment
variable to 1.
The Go runtime reads
this environment variable
and runs our program
on a single CPU.
This will run a concurrent
version of our program,
not parallel.
We can notice that
with a single processor
there is no noticeable
performance improvements.
Still taking around 11 seconds.
Still slow.
The good news is that
the Go runtime defaults
to using all processors
available on the machine,
and most machines today have
more than one processor.
This means that in most
cases, our concurrent Go code
automatically run in
parallel with no changes.
Running the program
without GOMAXPROCS
on a machine with four CPUs
will use all four CPUs.
And we can see that
now, our program
runs much faster, from 11
seconds down to 4.1 seconds.
It's running the goroutines
with the printName functions
in parallel.
Congratulations on reaching
the end of this level
and the end of this course.
There are still some
challenges left,
so head over and practice
writing some goroutines.
And don't forget to check
out the wrap-up page.
[BEEPING]
Op-- bleh.
Zero value is the default
value assigned to variables
without an explicit
initial value.
That's a lot of value.
[BEEPING]
--max number of elements
can help the-- pffft.
Read it.
Ah--