Welcome back.
In this section, we'll
learn about slice literals
and looping with range.
When we know beforehand
which elements
will be part of a slice, then
calling the append function
multiple times like this will
start looking too verbose.
As you can see here, for each
new language you want to add,
you'd have to write
an entire new line.
But here's a better way
using a slice literal.
In a slice literal, we can nest
elements between curly braces
like this.
The element count is
inferred from the number
of initial elements, so we
can use the type inference
operator.
We print that to the
console, and then we
can see the three elements--
Go, Ruby, and JavaScript.
One simple way that we
can read from slices
is by accessing the
elements by their index,
just like we do with arrays.
Here, if we read from
index 0, 1, and 2,
we'll see Go, Ruby,
and JavaScript.
Reading the elements
by index works,
but it doesn't scale
well as our slice grows
or when we don't know the
exact number of elements
until the program is run.
Take this code for example.
Now, instead of creating a
slice in the main function,
we're running a function that
returns a slice of strings.
What we don't know is the
total number of elements,
so we can't access elements
by index knowing for a fact
that an element will be there.
We can't tell if
the index is valid.
The most common way
to read slices in Go
is using a combination of
the for loop and range.
Now we've learned
about the for loop,
but this is the first time
that we're looking at range.
The range clause provides a
way to iterate over slices.
Here's what it looks like.
We're at our for loop
with this assignment.
i receives the range
of langs and the loop
will run once for each
value that's part of langs.
We don't have to know
how many elements there
are because range will
take care of assigning
the index for each one to the i
variable before the block runs.
Now inside our for
loop, we can use
the index that's been
assigned to the i variable
to read the elements
from the original slice.
By navigating slices
with range, we
can be sure that indices
used to read from that slice
will always be valid.
So we print each
element to the console
and we can see Go,
Ruby, and JavaScript.
Calling range on a slice
actually returns two elements.
The first one is
the index, which
we have been assigning to i.
But if we declare
another variable,
we'll call it element,
separated by a comma,
we can also read the
value for that index.
This allows us to
read both the index
and the value stored on
that index at the same time.
However, notice how
in this example,
we're reading the
element and the index i,
but we're not doing anything
with the i variable.
This will produce an error.
The Go compiler
will not allow us
to assign a value to a
variable unless we're actually
using that variable, which
in this case, we're not.
But in order to read the element
directly from the langs slice,
we must assign the
index to something.
Now instead of a
regular variable,
we'll use the
underline character.
The underline character tells
Go that this value will not
be used from anywhere
else in the code,
so the compiler
will just ignore it.
When we run this code now, it
prints the languages just fine.
Just a heads up--
don't forget this--
when given a single identifier,
range assigns the index and not
the element.
This snippet prints 0,
1, and 2-- the indices--
and not the languages.
That's it for this level.
Now it's your turn to
practice in the challenges,
and I'll see you back
here in the next level.