[SINGING] What's that
shooting across the sky?
A rocket, a meteor,
or a data type?
With PHP, we'll make it
through with variables, arrays,
and loops.
As you track meteors
around the world,
your coding knowledge
will unfurl.
Shall we play a game?
Yes, indeed.
Let's join forces and Try PHP.
Welcome to Try PHP.
I'm Hampton and
we're going to learn
the basics of the PHP language.
So what will this course cover?
Well, this is going to be our
core structure for Try PHP.
In level 1, we're
going to look over
syntax and basic variables.
In level 2, we're going
to look over simple arrays
and associative arrays.
In level 3, we're going
to look over conditionals
and operators.
And in level 4, we're going to
look over looping constructs.
What do you need to know to
get started with the Try PHP
course?
You might think that you need
to know a lot of programming
to start with.
Well that's not true.
Really all you need is
some basic HTML and CSS.
For that, you can
take our courses,
which is Front-end Foundations
and Front-end Formations.
Why PHP?
Why now?
PHP is a server-side
scripting language
that's been around since 1997.
And over the years,
it's grown into a very
modern and performant tool.
Here are a few tasks that PHP
helps us achieve very simply.
It allows execution of code
inline with our HTML markup.
It gives a simple reading and
processing of files and images.
It gives us request and
response processing with forms.
It's very high performance
and scales easily.
Let's get started
looking at how PHP works.
At the very
beginning, we're going
to want to add PHP code
directly into our HTML file.
What you see here is a
very simple HTML page
that has a hello world block
inside of a paragraph tack.
The output in our browser
will look something like this.
Hello World.
The first thing we have to
do is to rename our file
so that the server knows we
want to process this file as PHP
and not HTML.
So all we need to do
is rename the file
from dot HTML to dot PHP.
Even though we've changed the
file extension to dot PHP,
the output remains
the same, which
means we can mix HTML and
PHP code in the same file.
Our next step is going to
be add code to the file.
What's different now?
Normally, we send a
URL to request a page
and the server responds to
us with some HTML and CSS.
What's going to be
different since we've
changed our file to dot PHP.
How is this server
going to handle it?
Now that it's a PHP file, when
a user requests from the server,
the server sees that it's a PHP
file, runs through the file,
and validates that it's
properly formed PHP.
The server then runs all the
code inside of the PHP file.
After running all of
that code, the server
sends back the dynamically
generated output back
to your browser.
That output is
usually HTML and CSS.
If we want to add some
PHP code to our file,
we're going to need
to use something
called a code block,
which looks like this.
A code block starts
with a less than symbol,
a question mark, followed
immediately by PHP, a space.
And then to close that code
block you add another question
mark and a greater than symbol.
Anything that falls in
between these two tags
tells the server we want to
execute this as PHP code.
Let's add some code and see what
it looks like when it's output.
The first thing we're going
to do, as you might expect,
is to say hello to the world.
We're going to do this by
using a built in function
from PHP called echo.
First, we're going to type the
function key word echo followed
by a space, and then
a set of single quotes
with the string, or string of
characters, in between them.
To tell the PHP interpreter
that we're done with this line,
we're going to add a semi-colon.
You will do this for the
end of every line in PHP.
Once it's executed, this
will place a hello world
inside of the paragraph
tags on our page.
Next, we should talk
about variables.
Variables, as their name
alludes to, vary in value.
There are many uses
for a variable,
but mostly they're
a placeholder--
a placeholder for your data.
To define a variable,
you're going
to start with a
dollar sign, followed
by a word or words separated
by underscores, not spaces.
Here you can see we have
a variable called name.
To put data into
our variable, we
use an assignment
operator or an equal sign.
Next, we'll assign a
string to the name variable
by placing it inside a
set of single quotes.
You can use double quotes,
but standard practice
is to use double
quotes only when
you're doing string evaluation.
We're going to
get to that later,
but for now, just
use single quotes.
Notice that after
creating our variable,
nothing is automatically
displayed into our output.
In order to do that,
we're going to want
to use the echo function to echo
the content of our variable.
Notice that now there are two
lines inside of our code block.
As far as the PHP
interpreter is concern,
whitespace is irrelevant.
PHP standards do help us choose
the right amount of whitespace
to use in our code, but
it's all for readability.
There are some rules
when creating variables.
They always start
with a dollar sign,
they always use underscores
instead of spaces,
you can't use hyphens, and
you can't start with a number.
Here you can see some valid
and invalid variable names.
Another great feature of
PHP is that your code blocks
can go anywhere in the file.
We're going to move
our definitions
to the top of the
file, as you can see,
and it still works
exactly as it did before.
Now our variable is defined
at the top of the file,
at the first line, but not used
until later on in the file,
but still the output
remains the same.
We can also use the same
variable in multiple locations.
What have we learned so far?
We've gone over syntax
basics, code blocks,
how the server
handles and processes
PHP files, variables
and naming conventions,
and the echo statement.
Now it's time for you
to write your first PHP
code in the challenges.
Have fun.
.