Welcome back.
In this section, we're going
to dig deeper into arrays.
Let's walk through a
simple data problem.
Here, we're creating an array
with five different games.
How could we better organize
these games into groups?
One way is to sort
this into two groups.
One group for tabletop games
and one group for card games.
To do this, we're
going to need to use
an array within an array--
or a multi-dimensional array.
Here we have a
simple associative array
with the key of tabletop and
then a single value of sorry.
This is not really going to help
us very much, because it only
contains one game.
But, arrays can use any
data type as their value.
So we can also use an
array as the value.
So now instead of the
string value of sorry,
we'll use the array function.
Then after opening up
a little bit of space,
we can now add all of
our games that fall
under tabletop comma separated,
just like in a normal array.
Now we have a simple,
multi-dimensional array.
Next we can add another key
of card with a value of array
with our other two
games as its values.
If we do a print r on
our games array variable,
here's what our
output will look like.
We now have an associative
array with two items.
Those two items are indexed
arrays as their values.
How can we access this data?
We can access the data
by calling our games
array using the key for
the type of games we want.
Here, you can see we're
calling the key of tabletop.
So our output is going to
have an array of the three
values of tabletop games.
We can do the same thing to get
the values of all of our card
games.
If we want a single
item in our group,
we simply open the
square brackets
with our first key, then
another set of square brackets
with our second key.
Here, the first item in our
tabletop group, or a key of 0
is the game, sorry.
Notice, if we wanted to output
an array we use print r.
If we wanted to output a
single value, we use echo.
Maybe we don't want to have
poker as an option any longer,
but we want to
replace it with rummy.
All that you need to do is
to use the same addressing
that we use to echo
a single value,
but add a new value on the
right side of an equal sign,
or our assignment operator.
Here you can see the
replacement inside
of our array when
we run a print r.
Single access and modification
of our array items is fine,
but if we need to do more, we
can use some built-in array
functions that PHP
provides to us.
I want to go through
a few of those now.
The first one I want to review
is the array function count.
At first, you can see we have a
new array-- an array of names.
If we want to know how many
items we have in the array,
we can use the count function.
In this case, the count will
result in the output of 4.
We can combine
all of these items
by using a function
called implode.
It joins all the elements in
the array into a single stream.
The first argument of
the implode function
is the joining
character for the array.
And the second argument is
the array variable itself.
Here you can see the result.
What if we want to
randomize the array?
Well, we can use the
shuffle function.
If we do shuffle and
then the array itself,
it modifies it in place.
To output this, we'll just
use the previous function
we learned, implode, and
that way we could combine
an output or randomized string.
PHP also provides us
a way to sort arrays.
In this case, we can sort it
alphabetically by using asort.
Again, we'll follow this up
with another echo and implode
of the array to see the result.
Let's have a quick
review of what we've
learned so far in this section.
We've gone over in detail
multi-dimensional arrays
and gone through a few
simple array functions
that PHP provides for us.
Now it's time for
you to jump in and do
some challenges concerning
multi-dimensional arrays
and array functions.
Now finally, here you
can see at the end of all
of this-- What have we learned?
Nothing.
When do we want it?
Never.