[SINGING] What's the
shooting across the sky?
A rocket, a meteor,
or a data type?
With PHP, we'll make it through
with variables, arrays, and loops.
As you track meteors
around the world,
your coding knowledge
will unfurl.
Shall we play a game?
Yes, indeed.
Let's join forces and Try PHP.
Welcome back to Try PHP level 3.
Sometimes we need to be more
selective with our data.
We'll do this using two
new concepts-- conditionals
and operators.
There are many different
types of operators in PHP.
Thus far, we have
seen one operator,
which is the concatenation
operator or the dot.
These operators you see
here are very common.
They're considered
arithmetic operators.
Some of these
arithmetic operators
are addition, multiplication,
subtraction, division,
and exponents.
Some operators in PHP are
used for direct comparison
of two items.
These are considered
comparison operators.
We can also compare array
values, array keys, even
entire arrays as a whole.
Some of these operators
you've seen before.
Most commonly,
they're in the form
of equals, greater
than or equal to,
not equal to, greater than,
less than, and than identical.
The identical operator
is a bit unique
in that it allows us to compare
both the value of the object,
as well as the type.
In this case, our
values are equal.
The string 5 and the
integer 5 are both 5.
However, a string and an integer
are not of the same data type.
So this identical
test would fail.
The most common use
of our operators
are in comparison statements.
We use comparison
statements when
we want to ask questions
about our variables
and then do something
based off of that result.
The most common of these
comparison statements
is the if statement.
For this example, we want to
check a variable-- a year--
to see if it's greater
than or equal to 2001.
If it is greater
than 2001, we will
want to echo some
information to the screen.
To start with,
you're going to type
that if keyword followed
by a space and a pair
of open and closed
parentheses, then an open curly
brace, a new line, and
finally a closed curly brace.
Since the year variable
is set to 2016,
then this statement
will evaluate to true.
Inside the curly
braces is where we
want to define the
action that will
happen if this statement
evaluated to true.
What happens if our
conditional evaluated to false?
Well, nothing at this point.
Our process would just
enter our if statement,
evaluate to false,
and then just move
onto the next block
of code to evaluate.
What if we want to have an action
happen if our first conditional
evaluates to false?
For that, we're going to use
another common conditional
called else.
To use an else statement,
we'll add the else keyword
just after the
closing curly brace
from our if statement, followed
by another set of curly braces.
This way, if we have another
year that is less than 2001,
we can do another action,
simply by placing it
inside of our curly braces
within the else statement.
We may want to compare
two different statements
to see if they evaluate to
true or false independently
or combined.
For this, we're going to
use a logical operator.
Here are a few examples
of logical operators.
Here we have two variables--
a, which is set to true,
and b, which is set to false.
Using our logical operators,
let's compare these two values.
For the first example,
we're testing to see if
a and b are both true.
In this case they're not,
so that evaluates to false.
In the or statement, we're
testing to see whether a or b
are true.
And since a is true, then
this evaluates to true.
And in the not example,
we're checking to make sure
that b is not equal to true.
And since it's false,
this equates to true.
Using our new
logical operator and,
we can test to see if a date
is between 1994 and 2000.
Now let's look at
another conditional
to round out our if
and else statements.
If we want to add
a middle condition
to check after the
first condition did not
evaluate to true, we can
use an else if statement.
The else if statement
is identical to the if
statement in function, except
we're using the keyword else
if, instead of our if keyword.
In this case, we want
to test if a year is
greater than or equal to 2001.
If that evaluates
to false, then we
want to check if the year is
greater than or equal to 1984.
If that doesn't pass,
then we'll move down
to our else statement.
Let's take a quick
look back at what
we've learned in this level.
We've taken a look at
comparison operators, arithmetic
operators, if, else if, and else
statements, logical operators,
and comparing ranges.
Let's jump in and do some
challenges regarding operators
and conditional statements.
Just using our-- did
that I mumble that?
I think I did it.
And if-- ooh.
Sorry.
[LAUGHING] Terrible,
I get that on screen.