Welcome back.
In this section,
we're going to talk
about combining strings,
or string concatenations,
and different PHP data types.
So far, our name variable
only has a small amount
of data, which is the
name of our meteorite.
What if we want to
add more information
to our echo statement
of that variable,
but not into the
variable itself?
For that, we're going
to use something
called string concatenation,
or combining strings.
To join or
concatenate, a string,
we're going to need to use a
PHP operator, the dot or period
character.
We're going to get more into
operators later in the lesson,
but for now we're just
going to work with this one.
Continuing to use single
quotes with the echo statement,
placing them in front
of our variable,
we can add some new string data.
Then, to join the new
string with our variable,
we're going to add
our dot operator.
Make sure to notice the
space between the colon
and the single quote character.
If we don't use this
space, our string
will just bump right up against
the value of our variable.
Now you can see in our output
we have meteor name, colon,
and then the value
of our variable,
or the meteorite name itself.
Another way to concatenate
a variable into a string
is to use string evaluation.
Instead of using single quotes,
we can use double quotes.
When the interpreter sees double
quotes, and a variable within,
it will evaluate the
content of that variable,
in this case, the string "Hoba".
We will no longer need
the dot character.
So far, we've looked at strings
as our only data type in PHP.
But there are many
more data types
in which we can use to help
create great programs.
A string, simply put, is
a series of characters.
To define a string, we'll want
to surround our information
in single quotes
during the assignment.
An integer is basically
just a number.
It can be negative or
it can be positive,
but it has to be a whole number.
It can also be zero.
Integers can be represented
as base 10, octal, binary,
or hexadecimal.
Mostly, we're going to
be sticking with base 10.
Floating point
numbers, also known
as "floats", "doubles",
or "real numbers",
will be any number that a
decimal point can float.
That is, placed
anywhere relative
to the significant
digits of the number.
An example of a float
would be like width,
which is set equal to 8.9.
Booleans are a data type that
can contain one of two values,
either true or false.
It can also be looked at as
one or zero, or on or off.
If we echo our strings,
integers, and floats,
everything looks as
we would expect it to.
But if we echo our
Booleans, you'll
see that the trues equate
to a 1, but if it's a false,
nothing shows up.
We don't normally echo
Booleans, but mostly
use them for conditionals.
Let's review what we've
gone over in this section.
We've done string
concatenation, and we've
looked over the data types
of strings, integers,
floating points, and Booleans.
Now it's time for you
to play with these data
types in our challenges.
Of good-- [LAUGHTER] Here's
some examples of good and bad.
I wrote this, too.
Now if we do-- [LAUGHTER] I
wasn't looking at the camera.
Like "nerr".