[SINGING] What's that
shooting across the sky?
A rocket, a meteor,
or a data type?
With PHP, we'll make it through
with variables, arrays, and loops.
As you track meteors
around the world,
your coding knowledge
will unfurl.
Shall we play a game?
Yes, indeed.
Let's join forces and Try PHP.
Welcome back to Try PHP.
In this level, we're going
to talk about arrays.
What happens if
we have more data
to work with than just
one variable can hold?
We could keep going with
variables, like meteor 1, 2, 3,
so on, and so forth, but
clearly, this will not scale.
So what we need is
called an array.
An array in PHP is a map.
A map is a language type that
associates keys to values.
Inside of each
array, you'll have
a value with its associated
key for addressing.
It will start with 0 and
then ascend from there.
As you can see, each key has its
own separate and unique value
associated to it.
To create an array, you
have a couple of choices.
We can either use a
built in function, called
array, or two square
brackets, which is a shorthand
version of the same function.
You can use either
of these examples,
but our first choice will
always be the array function
just for the readability.
The two examples
above will create
the exact same empty array.
We can also create an array
with one or more values
by adding them inside of
the parentheses of our array
function.
If we want to add
more than one value,
we just separate each of
the values with a comma.
If we try to echo
an array, we're
not going to get the
results we desire.
Now we're going to need to
use another built-in function
inside of PHP, called print r.
Print r will echo human
readable output of a variable,
in this case, our
array variable.
Let's take a look at the output.
Here you can see it defines
array and then the key, which
is 0, and then the associated
value, which is hoba.
And for key 1, you'll
see it shows Cape
York as its associated value.
What if we want to add two more
values to our already existing
array called meteors?
We're going to
append our new values
by placing the square brackets
just after the array variable,
then use our assignment
operator or the equal sign,
followed by the new value that
we want to assign to our array.
If we now call print r
on our meteor's variable,
you'll see our output has
been updated to include
two new keys.
How do we access the
data inside of our array?
Let's say we want to take
a look at the first key,
or the first item, in our array.
We're going to access
this by using its key,
or in this case,
its numeric index.
The indices of an
array are 0 based.
This means that our first item
as it positions 0 in our array.
We can grab that data by
using the array variable,
followed by the square
brackets, and then our index
contained inside.
If we echo meteor's
with the key of 0,
we'll notice that our
output is the string hoba.
Continuing on what
we just did, we
can also grab the other
items-- in this case,
what's at key 1 and at key 3.
What if we want to
modify an existing value?
How do we do that?
We can do that by
assigning it a value that
overrides the previous, just
like we would a variable.
The only difference is that we
use the same address that we
used for recalling that value.
In this case, we're taking
meteors, the key of 0,
and then setting it equal
to Los Angeles, which
used to be set to hoba.
If we do a print r on
our array variable,
you'll now see that hoba
has been replaced at key 0
with Los Angeles.
Arrays can be very powerful.
A meteorite is clearly
more than just a name.
There's information
like weight, year
discovered or
found, its location.
Let's store more information
about the meteorite
using the name as our
key, instead of a number.
To do this, we're
going to use something
called an associative array.
An associative array is a little
different from the simple array
that we've learned so far.
Indexed arrays use
integers as their keys,
where associative arrays can
use strings-- strings that
will help us find the data
that we're looking for.
To define an associative
array, instead of just writing
values inside the
array function,
we have to create
key value pairs.
We do that by first defining the
key, which is a string of hoba,
followed by an equal sign, and
then a greater than symbol.
This is also known as
the association operator.
After this, we'll create a
value that is paired with hoba.
In this case, it's the
integer value of 600 million,
which is the weight of
grams in the meteorite hoba.
Now if we do a print r of
our array variable meteors,
you'll see a key value
pair association,
where the key is hoba
and then our value
is our weight in grams.
Now if we want to access an
item in our associative array,
we no longer use
the numeric index,
we'll use our string
index, or our string key.
Here when we are echoing
our meteor's array
with the key of hoba, we now
get it's contained value,
which is 600 million grams.
If you want to append
a new key value
pair to our already
existing associative array,
we would do the same as we've
done before, but instead
of a numerical index, we'll
add a new key, a string value,
and its associated value.
Now if we print r
our array, you'll
see we get the new value,
as well as our old values.
Before we jump right into
the challenges, let's
review what we've
learned in this section.
We've talked about
numerically indexed arrays,
associative arrays, creation
of arrays with values,
and modification
of values inside
of already existing arrays.
Now it's time for you to have
some fun in the challenges.