[SINGING] What's that
shooting across the sky?
A rocket, a meteor, or a data type?
With PHP, we'll make it
through with variables, arrays,
and loops.
As you track meteors
around the world,
your coding
knowledge will unfurl.
Shall we play again?
Yes, indeed.
Let's join forces and Try PHP.
Welcome back to Try PHP.
In this final level, we're
going to focus on loops.
Let's say we want to perform
an action that repeats itself
over and over again, but yet
changes a little bit each time.
For instance, we might want to
list out the multiples of 12 up
to 12 times 12.
We could do this long form,
but yet, eventually, you're
going to notice some code bloat.
This is where we're
going to use something
called the D R Y
method of programming
or don't repeat yourself.
We could solve this particular
problem by using a loop.
The first loop we're going to
look at is called a while loop.
And a while loop
works like this.
We set an integer, i,
to the start value of 1.
Then we use the while function
to run a test, of sorts.
We're going to check each time
at the beginning of the loop
that our condition
evaluates to true.
If it does, we're going
to run the code within.
In this case, we're going to
multiply the i variable by 12
and then echo the result.
Once this result is echoed,
we're going to need to
increment our variable by 1.
Here we're using
a shorthand $i++.
This is the same as saying
$i is equal to $i plus 1.
Here you can see
our result-- 1 times
12 is 12, 2 times 12 is 24,
and so on all the way up
to 12 times 12,
which equals 144.
Another way to cycle
through integers
would be using a for loop, and
a for loop works like this.
We'll start by
using the key word
for followed by the familiar
syntax of a set of parentheses
and a pair of curly braces.
Inside of our
parentheses, we will
have three separate
statements where
the first two are
terminated by a semi-colon
to provide separation.
In the first
statement, we're going
to define our counting
variable and set it equal to 1.
This will always run once
when you first enter the loop.
Our next statement is our
evaluation, or a test,
that determines whether
our integer, x, is
less than or equal to 12.
And as long as the variable i
is less than or equal to 12,
then our loop will continue.
The final statement will
be evaluated or executed
at the end of each successful
pass through the loop,
not before.
Again, we're going to use the
built-in PHP operator ++ which
will increment our integer by 1.
Now that we have the
constraints of our loop set up,
now it's time to do something
inside of the curly braces.
The first thing
we're going to do
is create a value by multiplying
our counting integer, i,
times 12.
The next line, we're going
to do the same thing we
did in the while loop which is
to echo the string, i times 12
is equal to our value
that we created.
And as you can see,
here is our result
which looks exactly the
same as our while loop,
except now, we've done
it with a for loop.
Let's take a look at the data
inside of our first array
example.
Other than direct access
and array functions,
how else can we extract
data from the array?
We could just use a
while or a for loop
to cycle through each
index of our array,
but when we're looping
through an array,
there's a special way to do it
in PHP using a foreach loop.
A foreach loop allows us to go
through each item in the array
and assign it to
a local variable.
Now we just replace our
for key word with foreach.
Keeping the same
outer structure,
we can now look at
each item in the array
by using the as keyword.
Here we're saying for each
meteors, which is our array,
we're going to create a
temporary local variable that
represents each
item in our array.
Now this loop will
run as many times
as there are items
in our meteor array,
changing the value of
meteor each pass through.
Next, we're just going to
add an echo statement to echo
our new local variable meteor.
In this case, it's the
name of our meteorite.
If we take a look at
our output, now you
can see that it cycles
through each one of the items
and echos the name.
What if we swapped
our existing array
with an associative
array, the one that
uses the meteorite
name as our key
and the weight as our value?
When we run this code,
it works the same.
We still get the value,
but now our value
is the weight, not the name.
Where before, we
use the as keyword
followed by a local variable
meteor, which just gave us
our value.
We can use the object
operator, which
we've seen before as
the equal sign followed
by the greater than symbol.
Looks like a little arrow.
We can now have a key and
value local variable to cycle
through each time we loop
through the foreach loop.
Using string evaluation, we'll
concatenate both the name
and weight value
into a nice sentence
that makes sense when printed.
This will now
output the following
which is a much more
complete picture of the items
inside of our array.
Let's take everything we've
learned over the last four
levels and combine them together
to get a more complete picture
of some PHP code.
To start with, we're going to
look at a couple of variables.
The first one, we're
going to call epic.
We're going to set it equal
to an integer of 600 million
or 600 million grams.
Then another variable
called huge which
is set to 50 million grams.
We'll do a foreach
loop where we're
going to loop through our
existing meteors array,
giving ourselves
a key value pair
for the name and the weight.
Inside of our
foreach loop, we'll
use a conditional statement.
In this case, we'll
start with an if.
We're going to check
to see if the weight is
greater than and equal to the
value of our variable epic.
If it is, we'll print
the following strings.
If our previous
statement does not pass,
we'll want to follow it up
with an elseif statement.
Here we're going to test
to see if the weight is
greater than or equal to huge.
If that happens
to be true, we'll
print the following information.
If neither one of these
conditionals pass,
we want to follow it up with
a default condition, that
would be our else statement.
And here, we simply echo,
you found a meteorite.
That's awesome.
Before we jump into
our final challenges,
let's look back at level four
and see what we've learned.
We've gone over while loops,
for loops, foreach loops,
foreach loops with a
key and value pair,
as well as combining foreach
loops with conditionals.
Now it's time to take the
last set of challenges
and I'll see you in
the wrap-up video.
Welcome back to Try--
[BEEP]
This lesson alone-- low--
For we've experienced issues
relating to Massaman curry
combined with extra hot sauce.
[BEEP]