Hi.
I'm Dan Denney.
And I worked on creating the
content for Unmasking HTML
emails.
And I also build all of the
emails here at Code School.
Before you started
the course, I wanted
to let you know about some
big changes to Gmail that
change the accuracy
of the course,
but don't yet affect how
we're creating emails.
Spoiler alert —
in Level 1, you're
going to learn that Gmail
is the reason that we
have to use inline CSS.
And that's because
up until now, they
were removing both
linked style sheets
and any CSS in a style element.
They've now made
some changes that
don't remove CSS and
the style element
for most of their users.
At this time non-US
Gmail accounts,
any Google Apps that are
the G Suite, the Google
App for Gmail on iOS, and
any third-party account
in any Gmail app will still
have the style element removed.
And of these, there is
no indication at all
that third-party Gmail apps
will be updated at all.
Since the goal of
this course is to have
you create emails that work
for the most clients possible,
we're not planning
on updating it
to have you remove inline styles
until we're sure that it works
well in these popular clients.
I've added a link to the
Resources section that
will explain how it would
affect the email that you
create in the course and
then emails in general.
So for now, I hope you
enjoy Unmasking HTML Emails.
[SINGING] Designing emails
can be really tough.
Client preprocessors
can be pretty rough.
Coding email for
all their devices
Cut the design into
the slices
Plug it up in tables of inline style,
or DB your queries into one
file to win your train
and learn the details,
Unmasking HTML Emails
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Unmasking
HTML emails.
I'm your instructor Dan Denney.
And I'll be in
your corner as you
learn how to write HTML and CSS
specifically for email clients.
The best way to
learn is by doing.
So in this course, we're going
to take a pre-designed email
set up for a large screen
version and a small screen
version and write the HTML
and CSS necessary for that
to display in email clients.
In this particular
level, we're going
to focus on creating the
header for the large screen
version of the email.
The skills that you're going
to need to complete this course
are a working knowledge of HTML
and CSS, CSS media queries,
and we're going to have to
use some external resources
in order to complete the code
necessary to create this email.
At its core, an HTML
email is an HTML file.
If any of this code
looks unfamiliar,
we may want to have you first
get started by taking Front-end
Foundations to
learn HTML and CSS
or Journey into Mobile to
learn CSS media queries.
The code that we write is
viewed in email clients.
These can be web-based
clients in which you
would visit an URL,
like gmail.com to access
your email in Gmail or
yahoo.com in order to access
your email in Yahoo mail.
The other type of client
are native applications.
One popular version of this
for Microsoft operating systems
is Microsoft Outlook.
And one popular
version for iOS clients
is the Mailbox application.
Each of these would be used to
access mail for many accounts.
In modern front-end
development, we're
used to writing code that
is viewed in browsers.
Those browsers use
rendering engines
in order to interpret the
HTML and CSS that we write.
Email clients have
this same process,
but they have an
additional step too.
They use a preprocessor that
will actually change your HTML.
Let's take a look
at how preprocessors
affect the code that we write.
Their original intention was
to protect the operating system
from code that could
be execute in application
and have harmful effects on
the operating system itself.
Since then, they've added
additional responsibilities
in that they remove
or change our HTML
and CSS, override our
styles with their own CSS,
change the entire
document structure
for web-based clients, and
remove any and all JavaScript.
So you're not going to
be writing any JavaScript
for an HTML email anytime soon.
Gmail has the most aggressive
preprocessor of all.
And this is unfortunate
because it's
one of the most popular
email clients out there.
The combination
of its popularity
and its pre-processing
affect how we
have to write our HTML and CSS.
Let's take a look
at specifically
what Gmail's preprocessor does.
First off, it removes
any link tags.
This means that any external
style sheets in which we
have code would be removed.
It also overwrites our styles
with its own version of CSS.
And then it changes the
entire document structure.
Finally, and this is the
most harmful to our code,
it removes style tags.
This means that we can't write
CSS in an external style sheet.
We also can't lump together
CSS properties in a style tag
to apply to our HTML elements.
So now let's go back
to our base HTML
and start adding some content.
First off, we're going to
add the image for the stars.
One thing to note
is that we're using
an absolute URL for the image.
Anytime that we're adding
an image to an HTML email,
we need to use an absolute URL.
This image needs to be stored
on the server and accessible.
And we will reference it
using an absolute path.
This is one big difference
between email HTML and website
HTML.
All of the images
that we're going
to use in our example email
will have an absolute URL.
This is a lot of
code to look at.
So we're going to abbreviate
these URLs using a dot dot dot,
like this.
Continuing on with
our initial markup,
we're going to add an H1 and
a paragraph tag to our email.
Throughout this
course, we are going
to be writing a lot of code.
And it's all going to
be in one single file.
In order to keep
focus on the part
that we're working
on at the moment,
we're going to collapse the
code surrounding the areas
that we're working on.
You can see here, that
we've collapsed the opening
HTML and the closing HTML so
that we can focus on the body.
If we take our code
and view it in Chrome,
we get expected results.
This is unstyled HTML.
So we're going to
default to Times New
Roman for the font family.
And then we'll have some
browser specific spacing added.
However, if we
view this in Gmail,
we see some slight differences.
Gmail is applying
a different font
family and different spacing.
This is because Gmail's
preprocessor has actually
changed the code
that we've written.
Let's use the browser
developer tools
to compare how our code is
different from the Chrome
version and the Gmail version.
First off, looking at
the Chrome version,
we can see that our
code is as expected.
The only difference is
that Chrome is adding
some of its own default styles.
Continuing on into Gmail,
we see that our code
is in a very different
place than it was before.
If you look way down
the line of divs,
we'll find our code
towards the bottom.
So what is actually going
on with our code here?
If we look at that code
that was towards the bottom,
we can see that it resembles
the code that we wrote.
Our inline styles are there,
but they're now applied
to a div tag instead of a body.
Our image is there,
but it's being
served from a different
location because Gmail wants
to use its own caching service.
Our h1 and paragraph
tags are left alone.
But Gmail is applying CSS to
them via its own style sheet.
In fact, if we look at the
body tag of the Gmail web
application, we
see a lot of code
that is no way related to ours.
Knowing what preprocessors
are capable of,
we need to write our styles in
a way that they won't be removed
and that they can counter
any styles created
by the preprocessors themselves.
In order to do this, we're
going to write our styles inline
to create our email.
To write inline
styles, the first thing
that we're going to do
is add a style attribute
to our image tag.
We'll then add CSS properties
to give it the look that we want
and finally add
a width attribute
to set it to 600 pixels.
Here, you can see that our
star graphic is taking shape.
Next, we'll follow that
same process for our h1 tag.
We'll add our style attribute
and add properties to it.
But the one interesting
thing to note
is that because we can't
reference an area of CSS,
we have to include any reset
styles on every element
that we want to reset.
We're going to put
margin 0 on this
to counter any browser
behavior that would
add spacing to our h1 tag.
Our paragraph tag
is a combination
of both of our prior tags.
And that first we need to
apply container styles,
then font styles, and
also our reset styles.
If we view the results of our
inline CSS, we find a problem.
We want all three of these
elements to be aligned
and to have equal widths.
We can fix this by
adding a div around all
of our current content, applying
margin zero auto to center it
and applying a max
width of 600 pixels
so that it never gets
bigger than that.
As you can see now, the
content is contained
and the container is centered.
To clean this up
a little more, we
can apply text align
center to our div
and allow that to
cascade down to all
of the text inside of it.
To complete our header, we
need to add a background.
We want this background
to run the full width
of the available space.
In order to do that,
we're going to wrap
a div around our current
content container
and apply a background color and
background image to that div.
So far we've seen what happens
if we take our code and view it
after it has been through
Gmail's preprocessor
and Chrome's rendering engine.
Here's an example of
viewing our email after it's
been processed by Gmail's
preprocessor and Firefox's
rendering engine.
As we can see,
everything looks great.
Now it's your turn to
start building an HTML
email in the challenges.
[BEEP]
That be —
[LAUGHS]
[BEEP]
[SIGHS]
[LAUGHTER]
[BEEP]