[SINGING] These creaky
doors and dusty halls
may hide villains
lurking in the walls.
In the walls!
But don't fear old CSS
wearing sheets as coats,
for it's time to stop
making layouts with floats.
Gather Flexbox clues
and before you know,
you'll use it to make
things shrink and grow.
These new ways might
knock off your socks,
'cause we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox.
Yes, we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox!
Welcome back.
This is Level 4, Section
1, Suspect Sizes,
where we're going to be
talking about new properties
for space-based size.
Up until this point,
our flex items
have been their default size.
But there are times
where you're going
to want to control the size.
In this example,
our form, we may
want that to grow and use up
all of the available space
as the screen size grows.
Also, to achieve a two-column
layout with spacing,
we're going to want to
set some defined widths.
In our first example,
we're dealing
with mostly default behavior.
I just wanted to
share one point.
That, in order to
have all the items fit
on that very small screen, I
had to override Chrome's default
behavior and set the min
width of the input to 0.
Aside from that, we can
see that our items are only
filling up their content space.
The flex-grow property
is used to specify
the ratio of the space an item
should fill in the main axis.
It accepts numbers,
and its default is 0.
0 meaning don't grow.
Here, if we set flex-grow
to 0 on all of our inputs,
we get our default
behavior, in that they
are their default content size.
We can change this
default behavior
by setting flex-grow to 1.
Here, if we put it
on just our input,
the input is going
to grow to take up
all of the available space.
In this case, the
available space
is all of the space
of the container,
minus the space necessary
for the other flex items.
We can also set flex-grow
on multiple properties.
If we set flex-grow to
1 on all three elements,
each one is going to try to
fill up all the available space
that it can.
In this case, it
means that all three
are going to be sharing
the space on the flex line.
Now we'll look at how
things get a little tricky.
Since grow is a
ratio-based property,
we can use numbers to
set the ratio of space
that items are supposed to take.
Here, we have three divs.
We're setting a flex-grow
of 1 on two of them,
and a flex-grow
of 2 on the third.
That gives us four units of
space for the divs to divide.
In a perfect world, in a
1,000-pixel container,
our element set to 2 is
going to take up 500 pixels,
and each of the
elements set to 1
are going to take up 250 pixels.
As we change content,
things continue
to change more drastically.
By just changing the number
of characters in each div,
now our one-unit ratio elements
are no longer the same size.
They're 279 pixels
and 288 pixels.
This is something to
know going forward
if you're trying
to create layouts
using ratio-based flex-grow.
If you want defined
widths for items,
you're going to want a
different solution, which
we'll get to later.
In this example, we'll look
at a different problem,
in that we don't want an item
to get smaller than it is.
As the screen size
changes here, you
can see that our image is
getting continuously smaller,
almost to the point of not
being able to see it anymore.
The flex-shrink property
is used to specify
the shrink factor of an item.
It accepts numbers,
and its default
is 1, which means do shrink.
So here, if we change
our value to 0,
the item containing the
image won't change size,
even if it ends up bigger
than the other item sharing
the space.
Here's our flex-shrink
0 in action.
As the screen size gets smaller,
the image stays the same size,
and the other flex item adjusts
to fill the remaining space.
Now it's your turn to have
items grow and shrink using
Flexbox in the challenges.