Welcome back.
This is Level 4, Section
2, Withholding Widths,
where we're going to be
talking about the new property
for setting width values.
So far we've learned
how to have items wrap,
and grow, and shrink.
But in order to create a
two-column layout like this,
we need to be able to
set consistent widths.
The flex-basis property is used
to specify the initial size
of a flex item.
It defaults to auto and
currently supports CSS units
like percentage, pixels,
ems, rems, and more.
We've seen flex-basis in action
so far as elements adjust
to the size of their content.
Here, we're going to override
that with flex-basis.
On our containing
element, we're going
to set a flex-basis of 47.5%.
That's going to
have two containers
right next to each other.
We're using justify-content
to add the space in between.
For our images, we're using
a flex-basis of 140 pixels.
That's going to get a
consistent image container
size on all of our clues.
Here, we can see how
flex-basis works
when we have a
specific pixel value
and allow the other item
to adjust to the space.
As the screen size
shrinks, the text area
is going to
continually get smaller
until we have all
of the items wrap.
We can use absolute
units in flex-basis.
So here, with four divs
in a flex container,
we're setting each
div to 250 pixels.
By default, they won't grow any
larger than the 250 pixels.
So even though our flex
container has more space,
those four divs are only going
to take up the 250 pixels each.
Alternatively, we can use
percentages as a relative unit,
or combine a pixel width
with a flex-grow of 1,
so that the items will grow
beyond their 250 pixels
when the container grows
larger than that as well.
We may be getting more
content-based values
in the future, so you'll want
to keep an eye on the spec.
Now it's your turn to use
flex-basis to control widths
in the challenges.