[SINGING] These creaky
doors and dusty halls
may hide villains
lurking in the walls.
In the walls!
But don't fear old CSS
wearing sheets as coats,
for it's time to stop making
layouts with floats.
Gather Flexbox clues
and before you know,
you'll use it to make
things shrink and grow.
These new ways might
knock off your socks
'cause we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox.
Yes, we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox!
Welcome back.
This is Level 3,
Aligning Alibis,
where we're going to be talking
about distributing space
on the cross axis.
Here, we're going to be looking
at how to distribute space
for our nav items and for all
of the items in our full-screen
layout.
Flex items are also
aligned on a cross axis,
and the cross axis is
perpendicular to the main axis.
So in a column direction,
the cross axis is horizontal.
In a row direction, the
cross axis is vertical.
While justify-content is
used to distribute space
on the main axis, align-items
is used to distribute space
on the cross axis.
Its default is stretch and it
accepts stretch, flex-start,
flex-end, center, and baseline.
In this example, where
we have the value set
to stretch for
align-items, you
can now see why our nav
links have been taking up
the full available height.
They stretch to fill
all of the available space
on the cross axis, from the
flex-start to the flex-end.
To distribute the space
along these lines,
if we set the value
to flex-start,
our items will align to
the flex-start or the top.
Setting it to end will
align items to the bottom.
There's also a
baseline value, which
works better for large and
small text or a small image.
Our solution that we
were using is the value
of center, which aligns the
vertical center of the items
with the vertical center
of the cross axis.
Again, this works in the
same way for column layouts,
except for the difference
that the cross axis is now
running horizontally.
Here, if we set the value
of center to align-items,
all of our items are
centered horizontally
in our full-screen layout.
Now it's your turn to use
align-items to distribute space
in the challenges.