[MUSIC PLAYING]
[SINGING] These creaky
doors and dusty halls
may hide villains
lurking in the walls.
In the walls!
But don't fear old CSS
wearing sheets as coats,
for it's time to stop
making layouts with floats.
Gather Flexbox clues
and before you know,
you'll use it to make
things shrink and grow.
These new ways might
knock off your socks
'cause we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox.
Yes, we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox!
You're watching Cracking
the Case With Flexbox.
I'm Dan Denney, and this is
Level 1, Foreshadowing Flexbox,
where we're going to be
talking about a new display
type for common patterns.
Technically, Flexbox is the
CSS Flexible Box Layout Module
Level 1.
However, in reality, it's a
collection of CSS properties
that are used to align
content and distribute space.
We're going to learn about
two new display values and 11
new properties in this course.
And you can look up all of
this information in the Flexbox
spec.
And since Flexbox has been
around for a few years,
implementation is
continuing to grow.
You can see the latest
browser support on can I use.
To learn these new
properties, we're
going to take a look at them
through various UI patterns
that Flexbox makes easier.
We're going to look at
equal heights, vertically
centered content, media objects,
sticky footers, and column
layouts.
Flexbox is a new display type.
Previously, we've used
block, inline, table,
and positioning layout.
If you're unfamiliar
with any of those,
you may want to check out
Front-end Foundations and/or
Front-end Formations
before continuing on.
In this course, we're
to focus on flex layout
and the various things
it brings along--
like flex containers, flex
items, and flex lines.
First off, we want to
look at the default
behavior of elements.
Here, we have an
article containing
an image and a paragraph.
By default, the article in the
paragraph are display: block
and the images display: inline.
This gets us our grouping
as it is right now.
Our paragraph is going
to be below the image,
and the two items are going
to be within their container--
the article.
We can change the default
behavior of elements using CSS.
Here, if we change
the display property
to have a value of inline,
our article changes.
It's no longer wrapping the
image and the paragraph--
it's now a collapsed element.
And that's because there
isn't a direct relationship
between a parent container
and child elements
in typical layout.
Flexbox handles this differently,
in that flex containers control
the layout of child items.
So here, if we change the
value of our display property
to flex, we not only change
how the flex container works
but how the items
within it align.
Now, our image and our text
are aligned horizontally.
This is a really important thing
to understand for Flexbox
because the bulk of alignment
for items in Flexbox
are handled by changing values
of the properties of the parent
element.
Let's look at some of
the defaults of our flex
properties.
If you set the value of the
display property to flex,
it creates a
block-level container.
So our container here
is going to take up
all of the available space.
There's also the option to
create an inline-flex element.
Here, you can see that
the container adjusts
to the size of the content.
Another key item to
understand for Flexbox
is that flex items are
aligned along flex lines.
Flex items are any direct
children of a flex container.
That means that they can
be text or HTML elements.
Here, we can see that our
flex container is adjusting
the default behavior
of a group of text,
as well as an image,
aligning them horizontally
along the flex line.
But what if we added another
element in our flex line?
Here, we add an h3, and
now all three items
are sharing the space
along that line.
Flexbox uses its own algorithm
to determine how much space
each item is going to get.
There will be times where
you won't want Flexbox
to distribute the
space amongst all
of the items in the container.
While Flexbox does change
the default behavior
of direct child
elements, it doesn't
change the behavior of
grandchild elements--
so children of children.
Here, we can see, if we
group elements together,
we can reduce the
number of flex items.
We're putting our h3 and
our paragraph in a div,
so now the div and the image
are the two items in this flex
container, and they share all
of the space in the flex line.
Now it's your turn to
write your first Flexbox
CSS in the challenges.