[MUSIC PLAYING]
[SINGING] These creaky
doors and dusty halls
may hide villains
lurking in the walls.
In the walls!
But don't fear old CSS
wearing sheets as coats,
for it's time to stop making
layouts with floats.
Gather Flexbox clues
and before you know,
you'll use it to make
things shrink and grow.
These new ways might
knock off your socks
'cause we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox.
Yes, we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox!
Welcome back.
This is Level 2, Section
1, Justice in Justifying,
where we're going to be talking
about distributing space
along flex lines.
In the previous
level, we learned
how to align items
horizontally and vertically.
Now we're going to learn how to
distribute space along the flex
lines horizontally
and vertically.
Flex items are
distributed along axes,
and the first is the main
axis, which is determined
by the flex-direction.
Here, with a flex-direction of
row, the start of our main axis
is at the left of the container,
the end of our main axis
is at the right
of the container,
and it's important
to know that there
is a center point as well.
The justify-content property
is used to distribute space
on the main axis.
Its default is flex-start and
it accepts flex-start, flex-end,
center, space-between,
and space-around.
What we've seen up to this
point is the default behavior,
so our items are
aligned to the left--
the flex-start of our container.
If we change the value of
justify-content to flex-end,
our items will align to
the end-- or the right--
of our container.
There are also values
for distributing space
in between the items.
The space-between value
will align an item
to the flex-start
and the flex-end
and distribute any space
in between amongst all
of the items.
The space-around value will
take all of the available space
on a flex line and
apply it to each side
of each individual flex item.
Going back to our
example from earlier,
we're using the
center value, which
takes the center of the
content and aligns it
with the center of
the flex container.
The one thing that
Flexbox doesn't have
is the ability to say,
"I want this much space
in between items."
For that, we're going to
use some non-Flexbox CSS.
You can use margin and
padding on flex items.
Here, we're assigning
a margin of 20 pixels
to the right and left of each
item with a class of nav-link.
Justifying content in a
column works in the same way,
except that the main axis
is now running vertically.
So the flex-start is at
the top of the container,
the flex-end is at the
bottom of the container,
and it contains a
center point as well.
Here, if we set
justify-content to center,
all of the items
in our container
are aligned in the
vertical center.
Now it's your turn to
jump into the challenges
and distribute space
with justify-content.