[SINGING] These creaky
doors and dusty halls
may hide villains
lurking in the walls.
In the walls!
But don't fear old CSS
wearing sheets as coats,
for it's time to stop
making layouts with floats.
Gather Flexbox clues
and before you know,
you'll use it to make
things shrink and grow.
These new ways might
knock off your socks
'cause we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox.
Yes, we're Cracking
the Case With Flexbox!
Welcome back.
This is Level 5, Section
1, Property Plotting.
And we'll be talking about
aligning content in edge cases.
In looking at the UIs
that we've built so far,
there's a couple
opportunities to make things
look a little bit better.
Could we have the heights
match between the input
and the button, and could
we get all of the content
to center in our
full-screen layout?
The align-self property is used
to align individual flex items
by overriding their
parent's align-items value.
Its default value
is also stretch,
and it accepts the same
values as align items.
In this example, we're
adding align-self of stretch
to the input to have it take
up the same vertical height
as the container.
In this example, the three items
are set to align-item stretch
by default, and we're
using align-self center
to have the main element adjust
to the size of the content
and center horizontally.
There's an alternative way to
handle layout with Flexbox.
Here, if we set our body
to our flex container
and have each item
wrap, we can use
flex-basis to force wrapping
by putting the header
and footer at 100%.
Each item is going to
default to stretch.
It's going to fill
up all of the space
on the vertical--
the cross-axis.
If we try to use our
align-items property
and set it to space-between,
we don't get any change.
That's because align-items
doesn't control wrapped items.
The align-content
property is used
to align wrapped flex items.
Its default value
is also stretch,
and it accepts the same
values as align-items.
If we set space-between
to align-content,
that is going to align
those wrapped items
and give us space between
our header, our main,
and our footer.
Now it's your turn
to handle some edge
cases with align-self
and align-content
in the challenges.