Welcome back to Level 1,
Section 2, Wily Wrapping,
where we learn that items can
wrap, and lines can rotate.
Again, we're going to use some
UI examples to try and learn
these new properties.
So we're going to display flex
items across multiple lines.
We're going to change the
direction of flex lines.
And we're going to
distribute space vertically.
We're going to start
off with a problem.
We learned in the
first section that we
could group elements
together to make sure
that they weren't sharing all
of the space on a flex line.
However, there may be
times where we want
the items to stack regardless.
Here's an example where
it might be better
to have the text display
underneath the image.
There's a property
called flex-wrap
which defaults to nowrap,
which is what we've
seen so far, where
elements are sharing
the space on a single line.
If we change that
value to wrap, items
that can't fit on the same line
will wrap down to a new line.
Here, we can see that
because there's not
enough space for all of the
text to fit next to the image,
it's going to drop
down below it.
Here, you can see that our
flex items are now displayed
across two flex lines.
An interesting
addition to Flexbox
is the ability to have
items display in reverse.
Here, if we set our
value to wrap-reverse,
our items that won't fit
will wrap into a second line,
but display in
the reverse order.
So now our div with
our text is actually
stacked above our image.
There may not always be a
practical use for these,
but they're there
if you need them.
Now we're going to look
at another problem.
We understood that we can
set our items to wrap,
so when there's not
enough space, items
will wrap down into a new line.
However, if there is enough
space, our items won't wrap,
and they'll share the
space on the flex line.
There are times
where you'll want
all items to wrap regardless.
Here, the goal of
this layout is to have
all of the items stacked on
top of each other vertically.
The solution for this is
the flex-direction property.
Its default value is row, and
it accepts row, row-reverse,
column, and column-reverse.
We've seen row in action
so far, but now you
can see if we change the value
to column, all of our items
stack vertically.
What we've just
done is told Flexbox
to align all of our items on a
vertical flex line in a column
layout.
To look a little
further into this,
it's possible to control page
layout with flex-direction.
By making our body
our flex container,
our header, main,
and footer would
try to share all of the
space on a flex line.
By changing the
value to column,
those three elements are going
to stack on top of each other.
The default behavior
of a flex container
in the column
direction is to adjust
to the height of the content.
If we wanted to create
a full-screen experience
for our layout, we would
use some non-Flexbox CSS
and apply a height of 100% to
our HTML, body, and main tags.
Now our flex
container will adjust
the full height of the space.
Now it's your turn to
practice wrapping flex items
and changing the direction of
flex lines in the challenges.