Welcome back.
This is Level 2, Section
2, Order in the Flexbox,
where we're talking
about changing
the order of items with CSS.
There are times in
layout where you
want items to display
in a different order
than their source order.
This can be done with
standard layout techniques,
but it's a little
hacky-- you might
use negative margins
or absolute positioning
to achieve something
like you see here.
However, Flexbox
makes it super simple.
The order property is used to
determine the order of flex
items along the main axis.
It defaults to 0, and it accepts
positive and negative numbers.
Here, by default, each
flex item in our container
has an order of 0, so they
display in their source order.
Here, we're taking an element
with the class of nav-clues
and assigning a negative 1
value to its order property.
That makes it display
before all of the items
with their default order, 0.
In column direction,
this works the same way,
except that the order is going
to adjust things vertically.
Here, if we take the paragraph
with a class of slogan,
change the order
to a positive 1,
that's going to make it
display after all of the items
with the order of 0.
Now you can use Flexbox to
change the order of elements
in the challenges.