Welcome back.
This is Level 5, Section
2, Scary Shorthand.
And we're going to be
talking about grouping
multiple properties
into a single property.
The flex shorthand property
is used to set values for
flex-grow, flex-shrink,
and flex-basis.
It defaults to 0 1 auto based
on the defaults of the grow,
shrink, and basis properties.
Before we go any further with
these, the one thing I will say
is if you have to
support older IE,
you may want to avoid shorthand.
It's where you'll see
the most inconsistencies
among the browsers.
In using shorthand,
you're not always
going to want to set
all three values.
If you see flex with a
single numerical value,
that's declaring the
flex-grow property
and leaving the defaults for
flex-shrink and flex-basis.
If you see flex with
two numerical values,
that's setting the flex-grow
and flex-shrink properties
and leaving flex-basis
to its default.
If you see flex with a
single numerical value
and a measurement-- like
pixels or percentages--
that is assigning the
flex-grow and the flex-basis
and leaving shrink
to its default.
And finally, if you
see a flex with none,
that's going to set
the flex-shrink to 0
and leave the others as default,
thereby treating the item
like it's not a
flex item at all.
The flex-flow
shorthand property is
used to set values for
flex-direction and flex-wrap.
The default is row nowrap
based on the direction and wrap
properties.
Much like the flex
shorthand, you
will see these
with single values.
And if you see flex-flow
with just column,
that's setting the direction
and leaving wrap to its default.
If you see it with
just a value of wrap,
that setting the flex-wrap value
and leaving the flex-direction
to its default.
Congratulations on reaching
the end of the course.
To wrap things up, you're
going to use shorthand
in the challenges, and then I'll
see you in the wrap-up video.
[BEEP]
Be happy for them.
Oh, gotcha.
[LAUGHTER]
Just go do it.
[BEEP]
Everything's new.
That's why we're here.
[LAUGHTER]
On the cross actious-- actious.
Actious Jackson.
Welcome back-- nope.
[LAUGHTER]
But in order to--