Gather all the elements to learn Elixir with our guidance.  Functional programs you will code,
turning the knowledge into gold.  Become a master mixer as you stir it all up with Elixir.
Welcome to Try Elixir.  I'm Carlos Souza, and in this course we'll learn about this dynamic,
functional, and pretty awesome programming language.  In this first level, we'll start learning Elixir
through modules and functions.  But not only that, we'll also learn about the functional programming paradigm.
Let's start with the basics.  What is Elixir?  Elixir is a programming language created in 2012 and designed
for building scalable and maintainable applications.  Here are some of its main features.
First, it's a functional language.  We build our programs with operations insides functions and modules.
There are no such things as objects and classes.  It's also a dynamic language.
This means that when we are writing code we don't need to declare data types for values and operations.
These are checked at runtime when we run the program.  Before we can run our programs, we must compile the
source code into an intermediate form of code called bytecode.  This reduces runtime overhead and allows for
nifty optimizations by the Elixir compiler.  Without much effort, Elixir programs are able to run distributed
and concurrent meaning multiple tasks can run independently and fast.
Lastly, programs written in Elixir run on the Erlang virtual machine called BEAM.
This VM has been around for 30 years, and it's reached an incomparable level of stability and maturity.
Now that we know a little bit about the language, let's talk about what it's used for.
Elixir is a general-purpose programming language meaning it can be used for many different types of
applications, but it's especially suited for the following problem domains:
Data processing where lots of user data is consumed, computed, and transformed into useful information for users.
Networking applications, programs that communicate across the network, like web servers.
And generally speaking, Elixir is suited for high availability systems, which are those that must be always
available despite crashes.  Think telecommunications, flight reservations, banking, etc.
In this course, we'll look at three of the most widely used features of Elixir.
They are functions, the pipe operator, and pattern matching.  But before we dive into code, let's talk about
the functional programming paradigm.
Functional programming is all about functions that operate on and transform data.
Let's look at the following examples.  Here we have a function f that operates on data x given as argument.
In essence, this sums up every Elixir program in the world.  The more complex our programs become,
the more functions like this they'll need to perform.  In the second example, we use the return value of
function f on x as the first argument to the g function, which also takes data y as its second argument and
performs an operation with both these values.
Okay, now it's time to jump into some code and write our first function in Elixir.
All named functions in Elixir must be part of an enclosing module.
We use defmodule to define a new module called Account and a do end block to define the body of the module.
Then we use def to declare a new function called balance.  This function takes two arguments, initial and spending.
Remember, Elixir is a dynamic language, so there's no need to declare the data types for the arguments or for
the return value of the balance function.  Now, from the function body, we subtract spending from initial and
then return the result.  Notice there's no return statement in Elixir.
The last expression evaluated inside of a function becomes its return value.
And that's all there is for defining a function.  Now let's see how we can call it.
Named functions are invoked using the dot notation preceded by the module that they belong to.
Here on the first line we use the name of the module, Account, which acts as the namespace holding the function balance.
We invoke this function using parentheses and passing the values for the arguments separated by a comma, 1000 and 200.
The result of calling this function is stored in a variable called current_balance.
Again, because of the dynamic nature of Elixir, we don't have to declare the data type for the current_balance variable.
The language infers the data type during runtime.  We can use the puts function from the IO module to output
a string to the console.  Inside the string Current balance: US $, we use the current_balance variable
enclosed by the pound sign and curly braces.  This is how we do string interpolation in Elixir.
To run this program, we can use the Elixir command available on the console or command line when Elixir is
installed in our system.  Running this program prints the following:  Current balance: US $800.
There's no need to worry about the installation process for now, we'll provide you with all the tools you
need for this course, but you can check out more information about installing Elixir on this URL.
One very important detail about the type of functions that we write in Elixir is the fact that they are pure functions.
This is a key part in functional programming.  Now in order to determine whether a function is pure,
we'll look for these two things:  First, its return value must rely entirely on the arguments it receives.
It should not depend on any external factor and should always yield the same result when given the same
values as arguments.  Second, it must not cause any side effects.
The result of the computation performed on the function body must be represented by the return value from the
function, which can then be used to perform operations in other functions.
In this example, the balance function from the Account module meets both of these requirements and therefore
can be considered a pure function.
The use of pure functions in functional programming makes programs easier to reason about.
Let's use an analogy and compare object state commonly found in object-oriented programming versus logic with pure functions.
Suppose we're asked the following question:  What is my account balance?
Without knowing how much money they had initially and how much was spent, it's nearly impossible to tell how
much is left.  We must rely on previous state, which in OO is represented as an account object in order to
answer this question with the currentBalance method.  Now suppose we're asked this same question, but in a
different way with more information.  Starting the month with $1000, when I spend $200, what is my account balance?
With this information, we can run a balance function that performs the logic on the initial $1000 and on the
$200 of spending, and that's all the data this function needs to come up with the answer, $800.
This is an example of the types of functions that we should expect to work with when writing Elixir programs.
And that's it for this first level.  Now it's your turn to practice some Elixir in the challenges.