Gather all the elements to learn Elixir with our guidance.  Functional programs you will code,
turning the knowledge into gold.  Become a master mixer as you stir it all up with Elixir.
Welcome back.  In this level, we'll learn about the pipe operator.
To understand how and, most importantly, why they fit in, let's look at the following scenario.
When thinking purely in terms of functions, a common pitfall is to write too many nested function calls,
and this can lead to code that's hard to understand, the complete opposite of what functional programming
aims to do.  Let's look at the following example.  We have already seen these first two before.
In this first one, function f operating on data x is simple and shouldn't be hard to grasp.
In the second example, things start looking not so simple.  Function g is invoked receiving the return value
of function f operating on data x and data y.  It's getting a little hard to read, but not too bad yet.
However, on this third example, we can see how things might start to look confusing.
Function f returns, and then function g, I think, is called, and then function h is called with some
arguments over there to the right, then function i, and finally function j, which looks like it's receiving a single argument.
While this might be valid code, you might have noticed the struggle to read it.
It's hard to understand compared with the other two examples.  And should there be a bug on this line,
trust me, no developer would want to touch this with a 10-foot pole.
This is just silly.  Now, let's see how we might find this code smell in an Elixir codebase.
Back to our Account module and balance function.  This time, calculating the balance is a bit more complex,
and it involves calls to two other function, discount and interest.
Notice, because these two functions are part of the same module, Account, we don't need to repeat the module
name in order to invoke them from inside the balance function.  The issue with this code is that it must be
read starting from the inner function, discount, out.  So here's how we read this code.
It all starts on the discount function, which takes the initial variable and the number 10 as arguments.
Then the return value from discount is used as the first argument to the interest function, which also takes
0.1 as argument.  As you can see, this code is not super clear and requires some extra brainpower in order
to be understood.
Developers with experience in other languages might be tempted to rewrite this using temporary variables, like this.
First, we invoke the discount function and store the result into the discount_amount variable.
Then we use the variable as the argument to the interest function and store its return value into interest_amount.
Then lastly, we return interest_amount.  Now we have two versions, the original version and the new one
using temporary variables.  However, none of them are really satisfactory.
How can we solve this issue?  The answer is using Elixir's pipe operator.
The pipe operator takes the output of the expression on the left and passes it as the first argument to the
function call on the right.  So our previous balance function implementation, which looked like this here at
the top, can now read more fluent using the pipe operator.  Instead of reading from the inside out,
we can now read it from left to right.  We start with a call to the discount function passing it the value
from initial and the number 10.  Then we use the pipe operator to take the return value from the call to
discount and pass it as the first argument to the interest function, which takes 0.1 as its second argument.
Elixir's pipe operator works just like UNIX pipes, which might look familiar to developers with experience
working on the command line.
A lot of times when writing Elixir code we'll find ourselves piping data through a handful of functions,
like we see over here when calling the discount function, then piping to the interest function,
and then piping again to the format function.  Lines that are too long can become hard to read and hard to maintain.
A good practice when piping through multiple functions like this is to break each function call into a new line.
So after the call to our first function, discount, we break it into a new line, use the pipe operator,
and invoke the next function, interest.  Then we break into a new line again, use the pipe operator once
more, and invoke the format function.  Code like this is easier to read and easier to extend should we choose
to add another function call in the future.
Elixir ships with a solid set of modules and functions available on the standard library, and it's common to
use the pipe operator with these functions.  Here's an example.  Inside the new print_sum function from the
Account module we start by creating a range using these two dots.
A range is a sequence of numbers, which in this example starts with 1 and goes all the way up to 10.
Then we use the pipe operator to pass this range as the argument to the sum function from the Enum module
from the standard library.  This function will add all the numbers from the range.
Next, we take the return value from calling Enum.sum and pipe it to IO.puts, which prints it to the console.
When we run this code, we see the number 55, which is the sum of all numbers from 1 to 10.
That's it for this level.  Now it's time for you to practice the pipe operator in the challenges.