Gather all the elements to learn Elixir with our guidance.  Functional programs you will code,
turning the knowledge into gold.  Become a master mixer as you stir it all up with Elixir.
In this level, we'll learn how pattern matching works and how we can use it to remove if statement from our programs.
The equal symbol in Elixir is called the match operator.  Although it might look like it behaves just like
the equal symbol in other languages, it actually works a little different.
Understanding the difference is key to understanding pattern matching.
In Elixir, the equal symbol matches values on one side against corresponding structures on the other side.
Code that might look like a simple assignment, like in this example where language = Elixir,
is actually asking Elixir to try and match these two.  What ends up happening is the string on the right,
Elixir, matches the empty variable, language, on the left, so the value is bound to the variable.
When we print the variable using IO.puts, we can see it prints Elixir.
Here's a more advanced example of pattern matching using strings.
In this example, we use pattern matching together with the operator for string concatenation to extract just
a portion of a string.  On the left of the equal symbol we start with a string, Jose, followed by a whitespace.
Then we use the string concatenation operator, which is this less than and greater than symbol,
followed by an empty variable, last_name.  On the right of the equal symbol, we have this string, Jose Valim,
with a whitespace in the middle.  What Elixir tries to do is match one side of the equal symbol with the other side.
The only thing Elixir needs to do to make the left side equal to the right side is to populate last_name with
a value, Valim, and that's exactly what it does.  When we run this code and print the last_name variable,
we can see it stores the string Valim.  Now, let's look at an unsuccessful match.
In this second code block, we have the same string, Jose, followed by whitespace on the left-hand side of the equal sign.
However, on the right-hand side, we have just the string Valim.  When we run this code, Elixir will not be
able to match the right side with the left side.  When that happens, a MatchError is raised,
which looks something like this.  The compiler provides a friendly error message saying what went wrong.
In this case, it's saying it wasn't able to find a match for the right-hand side value, Valim.
Pattern matching is also used when working with lists of values, and Elixir uses square brackets to specify a
list and allows us to use pattern matching to read elements from it.
In this example, we have a list with two strings, Elixir and Valim, and we store this list in the data variable.
If we print data, we can see ElixirValim printed to the console.
Now we use the data variable again, but this time on the right-hand side of the equal symbol.
On the left-hand side, we specify list with two elements, two empty variables, lang and author.
Again, Elixir will try to make the two sides match by assigning the first element of data to the lang
variable and the second element of data to the author variable.
Here the elements from the list on the right are a perfect match against the two empty variables from the
list on the left.  We can reference the variables on the next slide and print them to the console using
string interpolation, and the result is Elixir, Valim.  Now, let's look at a more practical use of pattern matching.
In functional languages like Elixir, the use of if statements is less common than in other languages.
In this example, we have the run_transaction function from the Account module.
This function takes three arguments, balance, amount, and type.  Here are two ways we can call this function,
with the values 1000, 50, and :deposit, or 1050, 30, and :withdrawal.
Notice :deposit and :withdrawal are atoms, which is a datatype similar to strings, but more memory efficient.
From now on, every time that we see a word that starts with a colon, remember it's an atom.
One way we could implement run_transaction is by creating a conditional using an if statement that checks
the type variable.  If it's equal to :deposit, then we add balance to amount.
Otherwise, we subtract amount from balance.  Notice that a function argument, type, is being used on the if statement.
Using a function argument like this on an if statement is a good opportunity for refactoring.
Elixir supports pattern matching in function arguments, and this allows us to replace our if statement with
two function clauses.  When defining a function with the same name, in this case run_transaction,
multiple times, each definition is called a clause.  The first clause of run_transaction will match calls
that use the :deposit atom as the last argument.  The second clause of run_transaction will match calls that
use the :withdrawal atom as the last argument.  From the caller's perspective, these two calls still produce
the same output.
Pattern matching, which we just learned, and the pipe operator, which you learned on the previous level,
are widely used in Elixir, and it's common to use them together, like this.
In this example, we start with the number 1000 and pipe it to the first call to run_transaction for a :deposit.
Then we use the result of that as the input for the second call to run_transaction for a :withdrawal.
The output is the same as before, but now using idiomatic Elixir.
And that's it for this level.  Now it's your turn to practice pattern matching in the challenges,
and I'll see you in the wrap-up video.