[CAR STARTING] [SINGING]
Put your pedal to the metal
and burn up the road.
Start the race and load
Angular 2 code.
A class decorator can
help you in this moment.
Tune your engine with the
template and component.
Use data binding to
drift through the turns.
With import and export separate your concerns
Inject a service
with your racing crew,
while Accelerating
Through Angular 2.
You're watching Accelerating
I'm Gregg Pollack
and this is level five,
where we will be talking
about services and HTTP.
Let's take a second look at how
we're importing our mock data.
Now, we're loading our car parts
by importing our mock file.
But this actually isn't the best
solution for working with data.
This isn't the best because
we need to import mocks
in every file that
needs this data,
and if the way we access
this data changes,
we'd have to change
it everywhere.
Also it's not easy to switch
between real and mock data.
And this sort of data
loading is actually
best left to service classes.
Services are used to organize
and share code across our app
and they're usually where we
create our data access methods.
So in car parts
component, we're going
to ask our service for data.
We'll create a service called
racing-data.service.ts.
And that file will be
in charge of fetching
the appropriate data,
which in this case
will come from our mocks file.
Let's start out by creating
the simplest service.
And then we'll learn
something called
dependency injection that will
make it even more powerful.
So here's a new
racing data service.
Inside there, we we'll import
our car parts from our mocks,
we'll create the class
RacingDataService,
and inside of it, it'll
have one method called
getCarParts that will
simply return the car parts.
Then to use this
service, we'll import it.
And inside our ngOnInit,
we'll create a new variable
called RacingDataService
that has a new instance
of RacingDataService.
And we'll set this.carParts
equal to the return
value of getCarParts.
So this is great, we've
decoupled our data layer.
But there's still
some stuff that sucks
about this implementation.
Classes using this
service must know
how to create a
RacingDataService
and if that ever changes, we
have to change it everywhere.
And we'll be creating
a new RacingDataService
every time we need to
fetch car parts, which
is going to use up more memory.
And it'll be harder to
switch between a mock service
and a real one later on.
This is where dependency
injection comes in.
When you run an
Angular application
it creates a
dependency injector.
An injector is in
charge of knowing
how to create and send things.
So here's an example
of how it works.
If the car.parts.components
needs that RacingDataService,
it's going to ask the
dependency injector, hey,
could I have RacingDataService?
The dependency injector
might say, oh yeah,
I know how to do that.
So it goes and creates
a new RacingDataService
and delivers that to car parts.
The injector knows
how to inject —
which means create — and
send our dependencies
or the classes
that we depend on.
One benefit of this is that
if the injector already
created a service, you can have
it resend the same service.
So let's say we have
a car.cart.component
and it also wants the
RacingDataService.
It could ask the
dependency injector
and the injector knows,
hey, I already created one,
here it is.
But how does a
dependency injector
know what it can inject?
Well, we have to tell it by
registering providers with it.
So, here, our
dependency injector
has three things it
can provide that it
knows how to create and send.
In order to make this work
with our RacingDataService,
there's three steps
we need to follow.
First, we need to add
the injectable decorator
to RacingDataService.
Then we need to let our
injector know about the service
by naming it as a provider.
And then third,
inject the dependency
into our car.parts.component.
Step one, we need
to turn our service
into something that
can be safely used
by our dependency injector.
We do this by first importing
the injectable decorator
from Angular.
And then we simply
use it @ injectable —
and don't forget
the parentheses.
Next we need to let our
injector know about the service.
So since we want all
of our sub components
to have access to
RacingDataService,
we need to register
it at the top level,
in this case, our app module.
So here, in our
main.ts, we're going
to import our RacingDataService.
And then we're going to add
a new piece of metadata,
specifically
providers, and specify
RacingDataService
inside of that array.
So we could have multiple
providers if we wanted to.
Next we need to
inject the dependency.
So in our car.parts.component
we'll import RacingDataService.
And then we're going to
declare a constructor
for this component.
It's going to have a private
RacingDataService of type
RacingDataService.
That private keyword
will cause TypeScript
to automatically define a
component property based
on that parameter.
So under the hood, the
generated JavaScript
looks something like this, where
it declares this.racingService
equals RacingService.
Setting the parameter
type is what
identifies that the Racing
Data Service is what will be
injected into this component.
Now we just need
to use the service.
So back inside our
ngOnInit, we can
set this.carParts equal to
this.racingService.getCarParts.
Now our app is more
scalable and testable.
It's scalable because
our dependencies aren't
strongly tied to our classes.
And it's testable because
it'd be easy to mock services
out when we want to
test the component.
Now if we jump
back into our app,
it still works but this
time it's using a service.
And our code feels cleaner.
So what did we
learn in this level?
We learned that services are
used to organize and share code
across our app, they're usually
where we create our data access
methods.
We use dependency injection
to create and send services
to classes that need them.
We give our dependency
injector providers,
so it knows what classes it
can create and send to us.
And we ask for dependencies
by specifying them
in our class constructor.
Dependency injection is not
an easy concept to grasp,
but hopefully this
gives you a small basis
to start from and maybe
practice in the challenges.
I'll see you in
the next section.