[SINGING] Put your pedal to
the metal and burn up the road.
Start the race and
load Angular 2 code.
A class decorator can
help you in this moment
tune your engine with the
template and component.
Use data binding to
drift through the turns.
With import and export
separate your concerns.
Inject your service with your
racing crew while Accelerating
Through Angular 2.
You're watching Accelerating
Through Angular.
I'm Greg Pollack, and
in our first section,
we're going to be creating
our first component.
In case you're not
familiar, Angular
is a framework for
dynamic web applications.
It's a way to organize your
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript
so you can ship it over
into somebody's browser.
So it's sent over
from your server,
but you're still going to
need some sort of server
application.
That might be Rails
or Django or PHP,
which loads not
just your Angular
app, but any other data that
you need to load into it later.
Angular was released in
2011, and it's mainly
maintained by Google with
the help of the open source
community.
By the end of the course,
we'll be building together
this Ultra Racing
app that shows us
all of the car parts
we have in stock
and allows us to select
how many we want.
In the challenges, you're going
to be building the Ultra Racing
Schedule, which allows you to
enter races and cancel races
based on how much
money you have.
Just to give you a quick
overview of what we're
covering in this
course, in Level 1,
we'll be creating
our first component.
Level 2, structural
directives, pipes and methods.
Level 3, we'll organize
our code and create
a model and mock our data.
Level 4, we'll do some really
fun data binding, and Level 5,
we'll build our own
service, figure out
dependency injection,
and then use
HTTP to call over the internet
to fetch some data from an API.
And of course,
between all of these,
you'll be doing
challenges and building
that app I just showed you.
You don't need any prior
experience with Angular
to take this course.
However, you do need basic
JavaScript experience,
and if you don't, go check
out our JavaScript road trip
courses.
You'll also need
basic HTML and CSS.
We have courses for that.
And optionally, I recommend
you take our ES2015 Shape
of JavaScript to Come
course, because we're
going to be using some cutting
edge features of JavaScript
in this course with ES2015.
What is the difference between
AngularJS and Angular?
Well, first and
foremost, Angular
is a lot speedier in a
bunch of different ways.
Also, with Angular
, we use components,
which are much simpler
than controllers and scope
from AngularJS.
Also, directives are simpler.
It's easier to create
custom directives.
There's also this great
intuitive data binding,
which we'll get into in Level 4,
where we, you know, link data into our web
page and vice versa.
Also, services are
now just a class,
and there's a bunch
of other things
I'm not going to get into.
A lot of improvements.
I really want to show
you some Angular code,
but before we get there, we need
to decide what language we're
going to be coding in.
We could use plain
old JavaScript,
but browsers aren't up to the
latest version of JavaScript.
And there's a couple
of different ways
we can get access to
these newest features.
One is by using
Babel, which allows
you to code in the newest
versions of JavaScript,
and then it does
something called
transpiling into JavaScript
that is compatible with all
of our browsers.
However, we could
also use TypeScript.
TypeScript is a
superset of JavaScript,
which means it has all those
new cutting edge features,
plus a bunch of
additional features.
TypeScript also
transpiles into JavaScript
to be compatible with
all of our browsers.
In this course, we'll be
programming TypeScript.
Don't freak out.
It's actually really cool.
TypeScript is Microsoft's
extension of JavaScript,
which allows use of all
ES2015 features and adds
powerful type checking and
object oriented features.
And in fact, the
Angular source code
itself is programmed
in TypeScript.
So in this course, instead
of seeing JavaScript files
like main.js, you
see here, we'll
be using TypeScript files,
which end in .ts.
If you want to learn
more about TypeScript,
definitely check out
TypeScriptLang.org.
Since our browsers don't know
how to read TypeScript out
of the box, we need to
translate it or transpile it
into JavaScript, and there's
two ways we can do this.
The first way is we can send
our TypeScript into the browser
and leave it to the browser to
transpile it into JavaScript.
The second way is
we can take care
of transpiling to JavaScript
before we ship to the browser.
This usually happens when
we build or deploy our code.
So I just made a commit,
I build the code,
it transpiles my
TypeScript into JavaScript,
sends that up to the
server, which then
gets served into the browser.
This method is going to
load your website faster,
so it will be what you
want to do in production.
Time to start coding,
and we're going
to start with our index.html
with just some basic HTML code.
Now, inside the
header tag here is
where you're going to load all
of your Angular libraries,
but, I'm not going to
show you how to do it.
There's actually a
few ways to do it.
When you're ready
to start developing,
we suggest you go over and
follow the 5 minute quick start
guide on the official
Angular home page.
Inside the body of our HTML,
we're going to put a body tag
and use our first custom
element called my app.
This is where our Angular
2 application will load,
and it's worth noting that
this my app custom tag could
be anything, even racing app.
Until our app gets loaded in
the browser, if we load this up,
we're just going
to see loading app.
If you followed that
5 minute tutorial,
you probably are using
SystemJS to load Angular.
And inside this
script tag, you have
something that looks like this.
This bit of code
is going to look
for a main.ts file, which
is where we're going
to put our applications code.
This bit of code also makes sure
that error messages are printed
out to the browser console.
Let's jump in and write
our first TypeScript file.
It's going to be main.ts.
Inside here, we're going to
import an Angular library.
That import keyword
is an ES2015 feature
used to import functions,
objects, or primitives.
Here you can see we're
importing component.
It's a function that will
allow us to create components,
which are the basic
building blocks of Angular
applications.
A component controls a portion
of our screen or web page.
So as you can
imagine, we're going
to be creating a bunch of these.
This symbol you see
here, whenever you
see this symbol in this course.
It means we're working
with a component.
I mentioned that
component is a function.
It's actually a
decorator function.
A decorator function
adds additional behavior
to our class from
outside our class.
It's a bit of code we declare
immediately before the class.
So here's our class
app component,
and right before that
is where we're going
to write our decorator code.
And it's that decorator that
turns our plain old JavaScript
class into a component.
You'll notice here, we're
using our component symbol
in two pieces.
The bottom piece for our
class, and the top piece
for our decorator.
Let's code out our component.
It looks something like this.
We write add component.
Inside there, there's an
object with selector, my app,
template, and some HTML.
The at component syntax is
used to apply our component
decorator to our class.
You might not have seen
this before because it's
a TypeScript feature.
Then, we specify the selector.
This is the CSS selector
for the HTML element
where we want the
component to load.
And if we look back
on our index HTML,
we can see this corresponds
to the custom tag we created.
Then, the template
is where we put
the content we want to
load inside our selector.
The configuration lines
inside the decorator
are sometimes referred
to as metadata.
Next, we need to declare
our root Angular module.
Modules are how we organize
our application in Angular.
One app might have
multiple modules,
but we need to declare
a root module, which
we'll need to launch the app.
So here you can
see in our main.ts,
the first thing we need to do
is import the NgModule library.
Then, we'll write @NgModule.
This is a decorator
function, and like before, it
takes some metadata.
Here, we're going to send in
a list of all the components
inside of this module,
all of the declarations
inside that array.
Then, we need to
declare a class,
because every decorator
function decorates a class.
Now, we need to include
some dependencies
to render our application,
specifically, browser module.
That's the module we need
to render Angular websites.
And platform browser dynamic.
This is an Angular library
which will render the website.
This will allow us to bootstrap,
or launch the application.
To use those dependencies,
we'll put them
into the NgModule metadata.
First, in the imports, we'll
load in browser module.
This is the required
dependencies
to launch your app
in the browser.
Then we need to indicate the
root component, the component
that should get loaded
first when the Angular
application gets bootstrapped.
Then, we need to use
the platform browser
dynamic function and
bootstrap our app module.
So now when our application gets
loaded, it gets bootstrapped,
calls app module.
App module realizes, oh,
it's that app component
that should get loaded.
It loads the app
component, which
then goes looking for
the my app selector
back in our index.html.
Components are the building
blocks of our Angular
application, and they nest
very well inside of each other.
An app might look
something like this,
where you have one big
component, and the header
component, maybe a sidebar
component, and little list
components, and each component
can have its own class file,
HTML file, and CSS file.
So we have our first component,
but it's not dynamic at all.
Let's start thinking about
how to send data around.
So if we have a property
inside of our component,
let's create a title
property, which
has the value Ultra Racing.
Notice here, inside a TypeScript
class, we don't use the var
or let key words to
declare class properties.
Though, in TypeScript,
you still use var or let,
but, you know, in methods.
So the question
we're asking now is
how do we put this
class property
inside of our template?
To print properties, we use
something called interpolation.
See those curly braces?
Inside there, we can
specify a component property
we want to print to the screen.
So now, if we load
up the browser,
we can see that it
prints out Ultra Racing.
But what if we have
an object that we
want to print to the screen?
Here, you can see
our car part object
with different keys and values.
To do this, we simply use more
interpolation and access car
part.name, car part
description, car part in stock,
like you see here.
Now, you'll notice, our
single quotes disappear.
This is because this time
we need to use back ticks.
Using back ticks allows us to
have template strings, which
allow us to be multi-line.
This is another ES2015
feature enabled by TypeScript.
So now, if we load
up our page, we
can see it prints
out our object.
Almost time to create your first
component, but first, let's
review what we learned.
Angular is a framework for
dynamic web applications.
We're coding Angular using
TypeScript, a language that
transpiles into JavaScript.
NgModules group Angular code
into blocks of functionality.
Components are the
basic building blocks
of any Angular application.
We use a custom
HTML tag or selector
to show where we
want our component
to load inside our HTML.
Decorators are what turn
our plain TypeScript classes
into components or
Angular modules.
Now, it's time for you to
start coding some Angular.
And I'll see you
in the next level.
So what-- though so.
It gets bigger every time.
FYI, this has nothing
to do-- FY-- FY?
This is how it gets done.