Welcome back.
And now it's time
to use the internet,
what could possibly go wrong?
So up until now we've
been using mock data.
How might we reach out to the
internet for our car parts?
Well, our car parts currently
asked our service for data.
So it's really
inside the service
that we want to fetch
the appropriate data
from the internet and return
that back onto our template.
Before we get into
it, it's important
that you understand how Angular
loads first in our browser
and then loads data.
So when our browser first
tries to access our website,
it sends back each HTML
CSS, it loads up Angular,
and then when it's
done loading, it'll
go back and fetch API
data like car parts,
and then our server
sends back JSON,
which then loads into our page.
Let's go through the steps
needed to make this happen.
First, we need to create a
JSON file with car parts data,
we'll call it car-parts.JSON.
Then we'll ensure our
application includes
the libraries it needs
to do HTTP calls.
Then we'll tell our injector
about the HTTP provider.
Then we'll inject the HTTP
dependency into our service
and make the get request.
And lastly, we'll
listen for data
returned by this request
inside our car parts component.
The first step is easy, we
just brought over our mock data
into our car-parts.JSON file.
But I've wrapped our
array in an object
to make it feel a little more
realistic in that data object.
So we'll have to keep that in
mind, that to get to the data
we need to go through
that data keyword.
Next we need to make sure we're
including the right libraries.
The HTTP library
provides the get
method will need to call
out to the internet.
And the RxJS library
stands for Reactive X
and provides an advanced
tooling for our HTTP calls.
If you use that five
minute quick start,
well, it's already
including these libraries,
you don't need to
worry about it.
Step three is we need to tell
our dependency injector that it
can inject the HTTP service.
To do this, we're going to
go inside our main.ts file.
And inside here, we will
import the HTTP module.
Then we'll include the
library by simply adding it
to our list of imports.
Do we need to also add
it to our providers list?
Well, it turns out we
don't because it's already
getting added as a provider
inside of the HTTP module.
Let's take a look.
If we dive under the
covers of the HTTP module,
we'll see in there, there is
another ngModule decorator.
And inside, it declares a list
of providers, one of which
is Http.
Now, we'll be able to inject the
Http library where we need it.
Time to inject it and use it
to call out to the internet.
So first, we need to import
our Http library as well
as a part of the
Reactive X library,
we just need map in this case.
Then we'll create a
constructor so we can
inject HTTP as a dependency.
We can do this because our
service class is injectable.
If we weren't using the
injectable decorator,
then our service class couldn't
have additional dependencies.
Now, inside the
car-parts method,
we'll write a bunch of code.
And there's a lot going on here.
So I'm going to split it
out into multiple pieces
and we'll go through
it step by step.
First, calling the get method
and fetching our JSON file.
You might expect this
to return a promise.
But it actually
returns an observable.
Observables give us
additional functionality
on our HTTP calls.
One of which is to treat the
return value like an array.
Which leads us to
the map method.
We call the map method.
And then we're saying
for the data returned,
do this to the response.
And we're using the fat arrow.
We call JSON on the response
to parse the string into JSON.
And the array we want, remember,
is under that data keyword,
so we call dot data.
Lastly, we tell our
TypeScript compiler
to treat what gets returned
like an array of CarParts.
Back in our CarParts
component file,
we need to change some code
because our service now
returns an observable object.
And we need to
subscribe to that stream
and tell our component what
to do when that data arrives.
So we'll write subscribe, and
when our car parts arrive,
we'll set this.CarParts,
our local car parts
array, equal to the
data that we receive.
If we called this up in our
browser, we would see nothing.
It would break.
And it would give us this error,
cannot read property 'length'
of undefined.
And it comes down to
this line of code.
this.CarParts —
well, is undefined.
And underneath the covers it's
trying to call.length on it.
Hmm.
Well, remember that
graph I showed you
at the beginning of the section?
Angular loads and then
it evaluates the code,
but we haven't called
out to get our data yet.
So it's calling
this.CarParts.length,
but this.CarParts is
currently undefined.
So we need to make
sure that this.CarParts
is an array before we
try to use this for-loop.
One way to solve this problem
is to use the arrays isArray
function to make
sure this.CarParts
is an array before we
try to loop over it.
Now, if we jump back
into our browser,
we can see that we can now
increment and decrement
our different car parts all
loaded across the internet.
Before we move on to challenges,
I've got a few last thoughts.
First of all, we didn't put any
error handling in this code.
And if you're actually
calling across the internet
to a data API,
you're going to want
to code in error handling to
make sure you fail gracefully
when that API doesn't work.
Also since we isolated our
network calls as a service,
we could easily write a
RacingDataService mock
and inject it when we're
testing or developing offline.
Lastly, observables
are really cool.
And they're worth learning about
if you do lots of http calls.
So what did we learn
in this section?
Well, Angular apps
usually load data
using service classes after
the application is initialized
and running.
We can use the HTTP library
through dependency injection
to make internet calls.
And our HTTP calls return an
observable, not a promise,
which behaves more
like an array.
So why don't you get your
hands dirty in the challenges,
and I will see you
in the outro video.
[BEEP BEEP] --still
kind of sucks.
No.
So this great-- [BEEP BEEP]
And wow, if I read that,
I wouldn't understand.
I'm just trying to put
it in my own words.
Cool.
These are your own words.
Oh. [LAUGHING] That's
one way to do it.
[LAUGHING] That's hilarious.
Is this easy to you?
All right.
I like it.
I like it. [BEEP]