[SINGING] Put your pedal to
the metal and burn up the road.
Start the race and load
Angular 2 code.
A class decorator can help you in this moment.
Tune your engine
with a template and component.
Use data binding to
drift through the turns.
With import and export
separate your concerns
Inject a service with your
racing crew while
Accelerating Through Angular 2.
You're watching Accelerating
through Angular 2.
I'm Gregg Pollack,
and in this section,
we'll be splitting out our
code into multiple files
to get things more organized.
We've been developing Angular
2 all in one file: main.ts,
and obviously, it's
not going to scale.
So we're going to split this
into three different files.
First, our main.ts
is going to be
just for bootstrapping
our app and loading
our first component.
Then, our app.component.ts
file is where
we'll have our page header.
And then finally, we'll have
a car-parts.component.ts
that will have our
list of car parts.
After this, we will have
two separate components.
So let's jump back
into our main.ts,
and you'll notice
around here, I'm
using a lot of dot
dot dots, which
means that code is still there.
It's just hiding because
I couldn't fit it
all on one slide.
So just know that
it's still there.
So we'll take some of this
code out and into a new file
called app.component.ts.
Does this work?
No, it doesn't work.
It's actually broken.
We're bootstrapping
our app component,
but inside our main.ts
it doesn't have access
to our app component.
So how do we get
access to a class
from another file in Angular?
First step is to
export the class
that we want to import, in
this case, our app component.
Then, inside main.ts,
we'll import app component
from the file AppComponent.
Notice here, we use
dot slash to specify
it's in the same directory.
And we don't have to
write dot ts at the end.
Also worth noting, the names
here have to be the same.
We're exporting AppComponent,
so that's
what we write inside of
our import statement —
AppComponent.
All right, we're halfway there.
If we look in our browser, we
see that everything is still
working just fine,
but we need to create
that second component.
Let's jump into that.
So here we are in
our app component,
and we need to take the
car parts specific code
and move that into a new file
called car-parts.component.
And in here, we're going to
import the component decorator
function, and then we'll declare
a component, and inside of it,
we'll have a selector
we'll call car parts.
Then, we already have the
template, and our class,
in this case, we're going to
write export class car parts
component, and that's it.
But now, how do we
tell our application
about this component
so we can use it?
First, if we go back
inside our main.ts file,
we need to import this new
component, like you see here.
Secondly, we need to
add this component
to our module
declarations array.
So it can be used in the
rest of our application.
We can use this new
component by going back
into our app.component.ts and
specify right after the title
our car parts selector.
And if we jump into our browser,
we can see that it still works.
So now, we've separated our
concerns into three files,
and our application
feels more scalable.
We've also created our
first reusable component.
And components are meant
to be reused, if we can,
in different parts
of our application.
Remember, Angular
2 applications use
a component-based architecture.
Components make up the
different parts of our app.
This isn't the app
that we're building,
but it could look like this.
Our app looks a little
bit more like this,
where we have our app component
and our car part component.
So what'd we learn?
Well, in our main.ts,
that's usually
where we just import our first
component and bootstrap it.
In order to import a
class, we must make
sure to use the export keyword.
We use the directives metadata
to list the directives
that our component uses.
And components are the building
blocks of our application.
Here is what our
architecture currently
looks like with our index file,
and we have our three files,
main, app, and car parts.
Why don't you do some
challenges, and I'll
see you in the next section.