So in section one, we
covered property binding
and class binding, and then
we covered event binding.
Both of these are
one way binding —
one in that direction,
one in that direction.
But how might we bind
in both the directions,
like when we have
a form field and we
want to keep it in
sync between the data
we have over the JavaScript
and the value and the HTML?
First off, let's add an
input field in-between
the plus and the minus.
And we should be able
to adjust the quantity
either by typing
a number in here
or by pushing plus or minus.
How do we make that work?
Well, given what
we know so far, we
could start by using
property binding.
So we could bind to
the value and bind
that to the carPart.quantity.
What would happen in this case?
Let's see.
So we increment using
plus and decrement,
but now when we set the
value by typing in 10 ...
well, it didn't remember the 10.
That's not good.
So we've only bound
in one direction.
We can then use event binding
to listen for input on our event
box.
So here, we could listen
for the input event.
And when it happens,
we're just going
to write some code
here inline, we'll
set carPart.quantity equal
to dollar sign event.target.value.
Now, let's see what happens.
We can change the quantity
using the input field
and it remembers.
Sweet.
Information is flowing two ways.
But there's another
way to do this.
First, back in our main.ts, we
need to import the forms module
into our app.
Then to make it accessible,
inside of our ng module,
we need to add it to
the imports array.
Now we can use the
ng model directive
inside of our app,
which allows us
to have one command to
express two-way data binding.
You can see this ng
model command uses
both square brackets
and parentheses
to signify that we
have two way binding
and we just specify
the component property
that we want to bind on.
And as you can see,
it works just like it
did on the previous slide.
This syntax has a
funny name, sometimes
it's called banana in a box.
Can you see why,
with the parentheses
and the square brackets?
It's important to note that
when we use the ngModel syntax,
we can only set it equal
to a data bound property.
So because of that, we'll use
it mostly for form fields.
Here are two different
components properties
like user age and first
name, those would be great.
But if we try to set
this equal to a component
method, for example,
it's going to error out,
it won't work at all.
In this level, we learn
that the ngModel syntax
allows us to specify a
component property, which
will use two-way binding.
We also learned
that two way binding
means that if the component
property is modified
inside the component
or inside our web page,
it will stay in sync.
Have some fun with
the challenges
with that banana in a box.
Box-- bocked-- bock-- binding.
Where as where-- where as
where-- where is where--
id-- blah-- we'll do it again.
I don't always like banana, but
when I do, I put it in a box.