[SINGING] Your online
application's starting to fail,
and it's crawling on the
network just as fast as a snail.
We need advanced programming
starting from the top.
Better write some code so
the world doesn't stop.
With the non-blocking
model, we will be just fine.
Build some Google
Chromes, right on time.
And if all you need to do is
write some JavaScript code,
and use the real-time
web with Node.
You're watching Real
Time Web with Node.
I'm Carlos Souza.
And in this level, we're going
to be talking about streams.
When we're writing
applications that
depend a lot on network
access and accessing
files on the disk, one thing
that we have to keep an eye out
for is how the data is being
transferred back and forth.
Lucky for us, this is where
Node.js really shines.
For ultimate efficiency,
and especially when
we're dealing with
large sized data that's
being sent across
the wire, we need
to be able to access
that data piece by piece,
or chunk by chunk.
When that happens, we can
start manipulating that data
as soon as it arrives
in the server,
and keep it from being held
into memory all at once.
Streams are like channels, where
data can simply flow through.
They can be of different types.
We're going to be
looking at the two
most common, readable
and writable streams.
And the streams API
that we've covered here,
is for Node version 0.10,
also known as streams2 API.
Some of the code that
we've seen in the course
has already involved
working with streams.
The request object for
example, is a readable stream.
And the response object
is a writable stream.
We read data from the
request and we write data
to the response.
When we run this code, an issue
or request from the browser,
our server responds with
the 200 status code,
and writes Dog is
running to the stream.
The browser automatically
receives that response.
Then, we fire a set
timeout for five seconds.
But the stream is
still kept open.
The channel between the
server and the client
is still good to receive data.
So five seconds
later, we write again
to this stream, this
time, dog is done.
And finally, we close it.
We've seen how to
write to the response,
but how might we read
from the request?
As we've mentioned
before, the request object
is a readable stream.
And it also inherits
from EventEmitter.
This is a great combination,
because the request object
can then communicate with other
objects through firing events.
The events fired
are readable, which
is fired when data is
ready to be consumed,
and end which is
fired the client
is done sending all the data.
Now, let's write some code
where we print to the console
the data that we received
from the request.
So inside of our
request handler,
we start by responding
with a 200 status code,
then we'll listen to the
readable event on the request
object.
Inside of that, we
declare a chunk variable.
Inside of the while loop,
we're going to read out
a chunk from the request.
And if it's not new, we'll
print it to the console.
We have to call the
toString function,
because the chunks we
get, they are buffers.
So we might be dealing
with binary data here.
Finally, we'll listen
to the end event.
And when that event is fired,
we just finish the response.
With this code, we're printing
to the console the data
that we get from the client.
How might we change this
so that we echo back
to the client, the data
that we get on the request?
All we have to do
is change one line.
In this case, instead
of console.log,
we call response.write, here.
Notice that we don't have to
call the toString function.
response.write does that
behind the scenes for us.
When all we need to do is
write to a writable stream
as soon as we read from
a readable stream, which
is exactly what
we're doing here,
Node actually offers
a helper method
that we can use to pipe these
two operations together.
This method is called pipe.
pipe handles all of the
events listening and chunk
reading behind the scenes.
So we can replace all of
this code with this one line.
Now, when you were
uncurl from the terminal
and send in the
string, 'hello', we
can see that string
being sent back.
In case you're used
to the Unix syntax,
then you might remember pipe
from the command line, which
streams the output
of one operation
to the input of the next one.
Whenever you can,
prefer using pipe
over listening to
the readable event
and manually reading the chunks.
This can help protect
your application
from future breaking changes
to the stream's API, which
is still not stable.
Remember that Node itself
hasn't reached 1.0 yet.
So it's always good to check
whether a specific API that we
want to use is stable or not.
And we can do that
looking at the docs.
Each core module has a
stability score next to it.
We can see that the file system
module is considered stable
with a score of three.
This means that no major changes
are expected anytime soon.
On the other hand,
the streams module
is still unstable
with a score of 2.
This means that changes to
the API are still possible.
So next time a new
version of Node comes out,
it's important to check
for any changes on streams
or any other unstable API
your Node application might
be using.
Let's go over another
example of using streams.
This time, we're going
to read the contents
from a file in the file system
and stream it to another file.
So first, we require
the file system module,
then we create a read stream
from the original file,
readme.md, and store that
to the file variable.
Then, we create a write stream
to the destination file,
readme_copy.md, and store
that on the new file variable.
All we have to do
is call file.pipe
passing in the new file.
Stream is so powerful,
and yet, so simple
to use with a pipe
function, that there's
third party libraries
that heavily depend on it.
One example is the
Gulp build system.
gulp exposes the pipe
function as its public API
so you can do all
sorts of manipulation
on assets with very
few lines of code.
I suggest you check
out gulp's website
to look at some examples of
using streams in the wild.
We can pipe any read stream
into any write stream.
So let's combine
the two examples
so we can read from the
request and pipe it to a file.
So we'll keep our
write stream as is.
But instead of
reading from a file,
we're going to read
from their requests,
calling request.pipe,
and pipe being
the content to the new file.
Lastly, we'll listen
to the end event
and close the
response, responding
with an uploaded stream.
Now, when we run
this from our client,
we call curl with a dash dash
upload-file option passing
in a file as an argument.
And then we can see
the response back.
So let's take a moment to
visualize what's going on here,
because it's pretty amazing
that Node supports this.
So we're streaming
pieces of the file
from the client to the server.
And the server is streaming
those pieces to disk
as they are being
read from the request.
At no point in
time is the server
holding the entire
file in memory at once.
It's all just
flowing continuously.
And due to Node's nature,
it's all nonblocking.
So if we try to upload two files
at the same time to the server,
we can see that our node server
can handle them simultaneously.
One of the reasons that
Ryan Dahl created Node.js
was to deal with file uploads.
If you've done enough
web development,
then you're probably
familiar with the whole drama
that goes around implementing
file uploads correctly.
What a lot of web
apps will try to do
is to load the entire file
into memory before writing it
to disk, which can cause all
sorts of issues on the server
side and affect all the other
users of the same web app.
And it's also tricky to be
able to provide the file
progress to the clients as
the file is being uploaded.
In Node.js, we can actually
do this quite simple.
So let's look at how we
can implement our own file
upload with progress.
So this is what our
uploader will look like.
We need to be able to issue
a request passing in a file,
either from the command
line using curl,
or from the browser.
And then, receive the progress
as the file is being uploaded.
To implement this, all we need
is the HTTP module and the File
System module,
which you've already
been using from our
previous examples.
So we'll start with our upload
code, which we already created.
Then, we need to know what the
entire size of the file is.
And we'll do that by
reading the content length
header from the request.
We're going to store it
on the filebytes variable.
We'll create the
upload bytes variable
to keep track of how
many bytes were uploaded,
and we'll initialize it to zero.
Then, listening to
the readable event,
we'll loop through and read each
of the chunks from the request.
Inside of the while loop, we'll
increment the uploaded bytes
variable with the
length of each chunk.
Then, we calculate progress by
dividing uploaded bytes by file
bytes, and multiply it by 100.
Then, we send the progress
back to the client
using the
response.write function.
We use parseInt to round
the progress to an integer.
Down at the bottom,
Pipe is still
taking care of the
actual upload for us.
And the only reason why are
we using the readable event
is so that we can keep track
of the current progress.
Now, when we run our
code and upload our file,
we can see the progress.
Nice.
So that's it for this level.
Have fun with the challenges.