You're watching jQuery,
the return flight.
And in this level, we're going
to be going over promises.
Now, this is pretty advanced
jQuery stuff.
So don't be too afraid if you
don't quite get it the first
time, but hang in there.
This is some really
powerful code.
In this first example, we have
one of our favorite cities,
the name of the city, and a
button that allows us to get
the weather.
And, of course, when we click
this button it goes out and
does an AJAX request, and
displays the weather right
there on the page.
So, how do we write the jQuery
to make this work?
Here you see the HTML for the
page, where we have our image,
our location, and the
Show Weather button.
Then our jQuery is going to
listen for click on that
button, get our current location
by getting the text
inside of the paragraph
for our location.
We'll set a location in our AJAX
request by specifying the
data option, like you see
here, with the key of q.
And our location, that we just
grabbed out of the HTML.
Then in our success call back
the JSON result that we get back
will look something like this,
with the weather code and the
weather description.
And we'll just grab the weather
paragraph and insert
that text right into the DOM.
What if we wanted to extract
this Ajax call and use it on
multiple pages on the website?
Well, one way we could do this
is by using promises.
We're going to encapsulate our
first promise inside of a
JavaScript object
called Weather.
Inside of there we're going to
have a key called today, which
will have a function.
Inside that function we're going
to pass in one argument
called location, which will be
the location from which we
want to get the current
weather.
Then inside there, we're going
to have a variable called
promise, which will be set to
what gets returned from the
AJAX request that we do.
You see all AJAX requests
return an
object of type promise.
And that object, that promise,
we're going to be able to call
some methods on promises later
on, that will give us some
interesting behavior.
At the end of the today
function, we're simply going
to return the promise.
Now, let's move the promise over
onto the right hand side
of the page, and refactor
our old code to use it.
First thing we want
to do is create a
today promise variable.
This will contain the promise
that gets returned, when we
call the today method with
our current location.
You might have noticed that our
AJAX call is missing the
success call back that
it had originally.
That's because we wanted to find
what happens on success
in our main bit of code,
that we're writing now.
Remember this small bit of code,
where we get the weather
paragraph and we populate
it with the weather.
We want to define what happens
when the AJAX return
successful over here.
This will allow us to
reuse our Weather
object in other places.
So how do we do this?
Well, we need to call something
on the promise.
Luckily, promises have this
function called done.
It's kind of like the AJAX
success call back, when Ajax
comes back successful.
By default it's going to call
the done method on that
promise, if it's defined.
So let's go ahead
and define it.
Here you can see we call the
done method, and we tell it
what to do when the
promise is done.
This method gets called when
the AJAX request returns
successful.
Let's make sure this
code still works.
If we jump into our browser and
we get the weather, sure
enough it returns the weather
from our favorite city.
Now, the code as we've written
it, is a little bit brittle.
And that's because, inside that
done method, that result
parameter we need to know that
we can call result.weather to
get the weather.
But wouldn't it be better if
that done method only had to
now about result, instead of
having to know that it needed
to call the weather function
on result?
So, back in our today method,
we need some way of
intercepting the success call
back and then only returning
the weather string to
the done method.
How do we do that?
Well, there's two steps
to do that.
First, we need to create our
own promise from scratch.
Up until now, we've been getting
the promise from our
AJAX request,
because it happens to return
an object of type promise.
But let's create one
from scratch now.
To get a promise object
we can use the
deferred jQuery method.
So, we'll set our promise equal
to this deferred method.
Next, inside of our AJAX
request we'll create a
success call back.
And in here it's going to get the
results from the server.
And somehow, we need to
tell it to only return
result.weather for that
done call back
inside our main code.
It turns out promise has a
method called resolve, which
triggers the done method that
we defined earlier.
So, inside of our success method
all we need to do is
call promise.resolve and pass
any arguments we want to send
to the done method.
Like so.
So now the weather gets passed
into the done method.
And we don't have to call
result.weather anymore.
And the code should
work great.
So the Weather object is now
responsible for parsing the
JSON response.
That way when we invoke this
promise in other functions
throughout our code, we
don't have to worry
about parsing it.
We don't have to remember
to call result.weather.
Just to review, to create a new
promise we call the jQuery
deferred method, like
you see here.
We can then call the resolve
method on the promise, which
we'll call the done call back on
the promise, if it exists.
In the same way, if we need to
create a method that gets
called when a promise fails, we
can call promise.reject if
we want the promise to fail.
And that will call
the call back
promise.fail, as you see here.
In the next slide, you'll
see this in action.
We need to define what
happens when our AJAX
method errors out.
So, here's our AJAX call back.
Inside there we're going to
define a little error message, which
is just invalid location.
And then we'll call the
promise.reject method with
that error.
Then in our main code
we'll just define
the fail call back.
In this case, we'll take that
error and we'll just print it
out to the log.
Here, we could have also just
called today promise.fail, but
we decided to chain this
onto the done method.
So let's jump back
into the browser.
And here you can see when the
promise fails, it prints out
the error to the console.
Let's jump into another example
and show you where
promises start getting
really useful.
And if you're not following,
bear us because there's some
cool stuff coming up.
So here we have the same old
weather promise that we saw
before, over here
on the right.
And then on the left we're
going to create a new
JavaScript object called City,
which has a find method, which
creates a promise for us
doing an AJAX request.
This is going to get information
about a particular city.
Here's what these promises
are going to do for us.
When we go back into our browser
and we click on the
More Info button next to one of
these cities, it's going to
go fetch some information about
that city, as well as
the weather and display
them both on the page.
Let's take a look at the
rest of the code
to make this happen.
Here's our HTML.
You can see we have our buttons
and our results divs.
Then in our JavaScript we're
going to create a click
handler for that button.
We'll go ahead and
get the location
out of the data element.
Then we'll get the results div
and empty it out, just in case
we clicked the button before.
Then we'll call this today
method on the weather object,
sending in the location.
And specify that when it's done,
it should run this call
back, which will update
the result div
with the current weather.
Then we'll call the find method
on the City object,
sending in the location.
And when it's done, it should
run our call back which
updates our results with some
HTML, which displays the title
and image of the city.
Now, there's something
that's a little
fishy about this code.
See, these two AJAX
calls are going to
get fired off together.
And sometimes the weather call
is going to get back first,
and sometimes the city
information call is going to
get back first.
Allow me to illustrate.
So here we have the two
different calls.
The first time weather
came back first and
appended to the screen.
And the second time we call it,
looks like the city ended
up going first.
So the image is now
above the weather.
So, how might we fix this?
Well, it turns out that when
you're working with promises
there's two additional jQuery
functions which you can use to
give you the behavior we need, called
when and then.
The when function takes in
any number of promises.
The then function contains the
call back data in the same
order that you called in
the when function.
So this is the solution
we needed.
So, now when we call each of
these promises, our code is
going to wait until both of
the promises are done.
And afterwards it will call the
then callback, displaying
the information on the screen
at the same time.
So, let's go ahead and use when
and then in our current
code to make this work.
Here, you can see we're calling
when and sending in
each of the promises.
And we'll chain that with the
then message which has two
parameters, weather result and
city result, which it gets
back from the done functions
of each of the promises,
and then we can append both of
these results to our div.
And now it doesn't matter if the
weather finishes first or
the city finishes first.
As you can see here, the city
result will always be appended
to the page first.
Let's jump back into
the browser.
And as you can see here, when
we click on More Info on any
of these favorite cities, it
will always display the
information in the
correct order.
Whoa, that was a tough level.
Good luck with the challenges.
I believe in you.
You can do it.
I promise you can.