You're watching jQuery,
The Return Flight.
And in this level, we're going
to be going over advanced
events and jQuery plugins.
OK.
New scenario.
We've got two functions.
One's called picture.
One's called status.
And they both just logout
to the console.
We also have this button.
That's a plane, Boeing 777.
And when we click on this
button, we want to call both
of these functions.
So what we might do is have a
click handler that listens for
the button click and calls the
picture function, and have
another handler which listens
for the click
event and calls status.
Up above we have sort of a good
reference for each of our
click handlers.
They are just there for
your reference.
And when we click on that
button, of course, both of
these functions get called.
But what if, at some point in
time, we wanted to turn off
these event handlers, so when
we click the button they
didn't happen anymore?
Well, we can do this by
using the off method.
Just like jQuery has
an on method, it
also has an off method.
And we simply specify
the event name we
want to turn off.
So here, if we run button off
click, it's going to remove
all of the click call backs.
So when we click the button,
neither of those functions
gets called.
But what if we only wanted
to turn off one
of these event handlers.
How could we do that?
Well, this is where
event namespacing
starts to come in handy.
So here you can see, we're
adding the namespace of image
when we call our picture
function, and the namespace of
details when we call our
status function.
Now, if we want to remove the
click handler that calls the
picture function, all we have to
do is call off click image.
Namespacing is just what
it sounds like.
It's just about adding names,
or labels, on these click
handlers, so if we need to pull
one out or turn one off, we
can easily.
We could also simply
write off.image,
and that would remove all types
of event handlers that
end in .image.
So now, if I added a new
function, we'll call it zoom,
which is going to zoom in on
a picture, and we call this
function when we mouse
over the button
for whatever reason.
Now, if we ever want to turn
off the event handlers that
have the image namespace all
at once, we can simply call
off.image, and it's going to
turn off the click Image and
mouse over image event handlers
on the button.
Another useful jQuery
event function
is the trigger function.
This allows us to trigger an
event using JavaScript, rather
than by interacting with the
web page and, perhaps,
clicking on the button itself.
To use this in our code, we
can simply run button,
trigger, click.
And this is going to do the
same thing as if the user
actually clicked on the button,
in our case, call the
picture and the status
function.
We can also trigger individual
namespace events If we want to
be more specific.
For example, we could trigger
the click.details event, which
in this case would call
the status function.
Let's jump into a new example
and use some of these
techniques.
Here you can see, we have three
different vacations.
And we can show the price for
each of them, which shows us
how much it's going to
cost for three days.
If we take a look at the HTML,
we can see that each of them
is a list item with a
classification.
It has the price stored right
there in the HTML for us and
then, of course, an
h3 and the button.
Here's another vacation.
And then finally, we have this
show all prices button, which
we'll implement in
a little bit.
Each of these needs its own
event handlers, obviously.
First, let's define
the handler on
the show price button.
So we're going to look
inside vacation
for clicks that happen.
And notice we're using a
namespace on the click event,
since it's part of the
price responsibility.
It calls the show price
method, which
we'll define in a minute.
Also notice we're
using the proper
delegation syntax for this.
So now that we have this event
handler, let's define the show
price function.
Show price is going to find the
closest vacation div to
the button we just clicked.
Then it's going to
grab the price
out of the data attribute.
Then it's going to create a new
DOM element, which is a
paragraph, which specifies how
much it's going to cost to
book three days of this trip.
And then finally, it's going to
append the new DOM element
into the vacation list item.
To finish the functionality on
the page, we need to implement
the show all prices button.
So when we click this, it calls
show price on each of
the different vacations and
shows the proper price.
Well, we want to implement this
in a way that allows us
to use that same show
price function.
How would we do that?
Well, our typical event
handler syntax looks
something like this.
Right?
This is the generic layout,
where we have the DOM element,
followed by the event, followed
by, optionally, the
namespace, and then the
method to call.
Well, the interesting thing
about event handlers is that
they can also be custom.
So we can come up with
a name for the event.
In this case, we're creating
a custom event called show,
which gets triggered on the
vacation list item.
And it calls the show
price function.
Well, interesting.
So how do we trigger that event
to happen if it's not
hooked on to some click or hover
event on our web page?
Well, we recently learned
about trigger.
So if we want to trigger this
event on all of the vacations, we
call trigger show.price,
as we see here.
And it will call the show price
function for each of the
different vacations.
If we wanted to trigger this
event on a single vacation, we
could simply grab one vacation
list item and call trigger
show price.
Same thing.
So to bring it all
together, we have
our show price function.
We already created our vacation
event handler, for
when people click an
individual button.
We have our show price
custom event.
And then all we have to do is listen
for the click event on
the show prices link.
When it's clicked, we need to
prevent default, you know, prevent that
link from being followed.
And then, all we have to do is
trigger show price on all of
the vacations.
Now, if we go back into the
browser and click on show all
prices, we can see that it
properly calls the show price
method on each of
our vacations.
Time for you to play with some
events in the challenges,
and I'll see you in
the next section.