You're watching Try jQuery,
The Return Flight.
I'm Gregg Pollack.
And in order to do this course,
you need to have
already played through Try
jQuery, our previous course.
So if you haven't, go do that,
and then we'll get started in
this level with some Ajax.
Let's take a look at a typical
web request without Ajax.
So our web browser requests
a URL from our server.
Our server then sends a response
which contains an
HTML file and maybe some
JavaScript files.
Then our browser takes the
HTML, loads that into our
document object model, which
we learned about in the
previous course.
Then our JavaScript gets
executed, which may interact
with the DOM.
Now let's figure out how
communication works with Ajax,
which, by the way, stands
for Asynchronous
JavaScript and XML.
And it's basically a way for
communicating with the web
server without doing a
full-page refresh.
So we already have
our page loaded.
And without refreshing the page,
we can go and fetch more
data from the server, and if
we want, load that into the
page dynamically.
Here's our server and
our browser again,
and notice the browser has
already loaded our web page
into the DOM.
But we want to get additional
data from the server.
So inside of our JavaScript,
we do an Ajax
request to the server.
Our web server then returns an
Ajax response, which could be
HTML or another data format.
Then our JavaScript can act
on that response, perhaps
interacting with the DOM and
updating our web page.
Now let's jump into an example
where we can use some Ajax.
This should look familiar.
It's from Try jQuery.
You can see here when we click
on Flight Details, it gives us
some details from the flight.
And then when we click on View
Boarding Pass, it gives us
this image.
Now in our previous course, we
loaded all this data into the
page and just revealed it
as we clicked on things.
However, this time let's wait
to load those flight details
until someone clicks
that button.
And then we'll go and fetch that
from the server and load
it into the page.
Here's some of the code from
that Try jQuery example.
You can see we have a title,
Hawaiian Vacation, a button,
Flight Details, and then a DIV
where we can click to view the
boarding pass,
but none of the data we need
is loaded in there yet.
Then we have some
event handlers.
So if someone clicks the button
inside the confirmation
class DIV, it will find the
ticket and reveal it.
Then we have another click
handler that looks for the
View Boarding Pass link.
And if that gets clicked, it
will show the boarding pass.
So how would we load the ticket
information inside that
ticket DIV from the server when
our button gets clipped?
To do this, we're going to use
the jQuery Ajax function,
which requires a URL and has
optionally a bunch of other
settings which we'll get to.
Here's our Ajax call, and here's
the URL which we want
to call, confirmation.html.
Our second argument is a
JavaScript object which
contains one option
called success.
This is where we tell our
browser what to do if a
response gets successfully
returned to this call.
The response we're going to get
back from the server in
this case is going to be some
HTML which looks like this.
Notice this is not
a full web page.
This is just the HTML which
you want to load into our
ticket DIV.
Now inside of our success call
back, we're going to find the
ticket, load the HTML that we
got back from the server into
it, and then reveal
it by calling
the slide down function.
Before we see this Ajax call an
action, let's simplify the
URL we're calling.
See here we can specify
a relative URL.
That's because by default this
Ajax call will use the same
domain that your browser
has loaded.
It's the same thing as
doing this Ajax call
you see down here.
So if we jump into the browser
and we click the Flight
Details button, we can see that
they get loaded using
Ajax from the server and then
displayed on the screen.
You also might notice that on
the bottom here we're using
Chrome DevTools to actually see
the Ajax request happen.
This is really convenient.
If you're not familiar with
Chrome DevTools, Code School
has a great course called
Discover DevTools which will
teach you everything you
need to know about it.
There's another method for doing
simple Ajax calls in
jQuery using the GET method
which only takes two
parameters, the URL and what
to do when it gets back a
successful response.
So if we were to rewrite this
request using the GET
function, it would look
something like this.
You might have noticed that
every time we do this Ajax
request, we're hitting the same
URL, that same static
confirmation.html file.
But we like to create
dynamic websites.
How might we do a request that
sends along the confirmation
number, something that looks
like this that appends the
confirmation number
to the URL?
Well, of course the easy
solution here is simply to put
that inside of the Ajax request
and we'd be fine.
However, there's a better
way to do that in Ajax.
This is where the Ajax
data option comes in.
This simply takes a JavaScript
object of keys and values and
adds that to the URL.
So these two pieces of
code are equivalent.
Another way we can get the
confirmation number is if we
stored it inside of the HTML.
So here you can see
the ticket DIV.
And we have an attribute called
data-confNum that will
store our confirmation number.
And then inside of our Ajax
call, we can use that data
option and specify to pull the
confirmation number out of
that attribute.
This of course still results in
the same URL request from
the previous slide.
Now it's time for you to try
some Ajax calls, and I'll see
you the next section.