You're watching jQuery, The
Return Flight, and in this
level, we're going
to be taking a
look at utility methods.
Here's a new example.
It's simply a Show
Favorite button.
When we click that, it's going
to go to the server using Ajax
and populate the data and show
our city, like you see here.
So what does a code
for this look like?
Here's the HTML for the page.
You can see we have our favorite
div and our Show
Favorites button there at the
bottom, which populates our
image and our paragraph.
Here's the jQuery code that
we would write to
make this page work.
First, we need a Click Handler
for the button.
The Callback function is going
to do an Ajax call with the
URL cities/favorite/1.
On success, it's going to return
some JSON, which looks
like this with the image
and the name.
From there, we're going to grab
the favorite div, find
the paragraph, populate that
with the name of the city from
the result.
Then we'll find the image in
our div and populate the
source attribute with our image
that was returned from
our server.
This works fine, but what if
we have multiple favorites?
We don't want to have
to do a call to the
server for each favorite.
We want to do one call
and get back all of
our favorite cities.
The JSON that we might get back
in this scenario might
look something like this.
As you can see, we have
an array of objects.
Now, if this gets returned, our
success callback no longer
is going to work as
we want it to.
We need a way of populating the
data from this JSON that
got returned into all
of the different
favorite divs on our website.
Here you can see three favorite
divs that we already
have on the page.
We just need to populate
it with this new
data that comes back.
But how do we iterate over each
of the different items in
our JSON array?
This is where we can use
the each jQuery method.
The each function takes
two parameters.
The first is a collection that
we want to iterate through,
and the second is a function
that is going to get called on
each item in our collection.
This gives us two parameters.
The first is the index.
So when we first go through
the array, it's going to
populate index with zero
for the first item.
And then it's going to set
object equal to that first
item in the array.
And then it's going to go
through again and set index to
one and then do the next item
and so on and so on.
So let's use this inside of
our success callback.
So here's the each method.
And our first argument is the
result that we got back from
the server.
Our second argument is a
function with two parameters.
The first is, of course, the
index that we're currently at
in the array.
And the second is our current
city as we're iterating
through the results.
Then we simply need to grab the
appropriate favorite div.
Here we're using the index to
find the appropriate div.
And then simply populate the
paragraph and the image, like
we did before.
So here you can see when we
hit Display Favorites, it
fetches our JSON array
and populates all of
our favorite cities.
So in the previous level,
we booked our flights.
And now we need a way to view
all of our flight statuses.
But this could change from
moment to moment.
As you can see, when we go to
the page, it shows us a couple
flight statuses.
But there's also this Update
Flight Status button.
And when we click that, we want
to be able to do an Ajax
request, which will return an
array of all the different
flight statuses and rebuild this
list on this page in case
any have changed.
Here you can see the JSON
response that we're going to
get back from the server once
we do our AJAX request.
It's an array of flight
statuses.
Our JavaScript might look
something like this, where
we're listening for the
click event on the
Update Status button.
When it's clicked, we'll
do an AJAX request
to the status URL.
We set the content type to
JSON, we set the data type to
JSON, and then we just need to
specify what to do we get back
the result.
Alternatively, we could have
written out this request using
the jQuery get JSON function,
like you see here.
It's doing basically
the same thing.
Let's go ahead and use this
alternative syntax.
So now inside this callback, we
need to take the results,
which are JSON, and translate
them into some HTML which we'll
store in the status
elements variable.
And then we'll update our status
list element with the
HTML that was generated.
We want our status elements to
each be a list item, an LI.
So the HTML might look
something like this.
There's a few different
ways we could do this.
Sure, we could use each, and we
could iterate through each
of them and build up a string
and append to the string.
But this time, let's
try using the
jQuery map utility function.
Map takes a collection that's
going to be our array.
Then our second parameter is a
function which gets called on
each item inside our collection,
each setting the
first parameter as the item
we're currently iterating
through and the second parameter
as the index.
Notice that between the each and
the map jQuery functions,
the parameters are switched.
With map, it's item and index.
And with each, it's
index then item.
It's a little tricky.
The difference between the two
is mainly that map returns an
array modified by what is
returned in the function
passed as an argument.
Now, I know that sounds
really confusing.
An example is worth 1,000
explanations.
Here, let me show you.
So here we have an array of
numbers called it myNumbers.
And our goal is to create a new
string which adds one to
each of these numbers.
So here's our variable,
newNumbers.
Inside there, we're going to
call the map function.
Send in is our collection,
the myNumbers array.
Then we're going to go through
each item in the myNumbers
collection, adding plus one to
each of them and returning it.
So the value of myNumbers
at the end of this
is still the same.
It wasn't changed.
It's still one, two,
three, four.
And newNumbers is equal to
two, three, four, five,
because that's the
array that got
returned by the map function.
If that didn't make sense,
here's another example.
Up here at the top, you can see
the JSON array that got
returned from our get
JSON request.
Inside there, you can see
all of our different
names and our statuses.
Now, we're going to send
each of these into map.
So here we have map, result,
function, status, i.
And we're going to go through
each of these, create a new
list item, which is populated
to just our LI tags.
And then we're going to
return list item.
Now, each of these goes into the
map, and it returns an LI
so that what gets returned
from the map function is
simply an array of
different LIs.
Obviously, we want our list
items to have some more data
inside of them, so let's build
out our map function so that
this time we create a new
H3 Dom element and
append it to the list.
Then we create a new
paragraph and also
append that to the list.
Now, here's the array
that gets returned
from the map function.
Now, let's take this map
function and move it back into
our get JSON function.
So inside of here, we need
to create a new variable.
So we can store what
gets returned
from the map function.
We'll call it status elements.
Then the only thing we need to
do is grab our current status
list and set the HTML equal
to the status elements.
Even though status elements is
an array of jQuery objects,
when we populate it onto the
page, it's going to take each
of those jQuery objects and
create a bunch of list items
in our unordered list.
So now when we go and click
Update Flight Status, you can
see it goes and grabs that
JSON array, uses the map
function to transform that into
HTML, and populates each
list item on the page.
Understanding the difference
between each
and map can be difficult.
So let's go over it one more
time in the Chrome console.
Here you can see we have
a simple array of three
different cities--
Paris, London, and Orlando.
We're going to iterate
through each of them.
And what we're going to do is
we're going to print out to
the console the result of just
appending their city name with
their current index.
Once we run this, we can see
it runs Paris zero, London
one, Orlando two.
It just logs that out
to the screen.
The each method does return an
array, but it simply returns
an array of the cities as they
were when we created them,
exactly the same.
Now, let's use the map function
on our cities array.
We'll create this same result,
log that result to the
console, and then explicitly
return that result.
The console log prints out the
exact same thing that our each
function did.
So this time what gets returned
is a completely new
array which contains
Paris zero, London
one, and Orlando two.
Before you jump into the
challenges, there's one more
optimization that I want
to show you how to do.
You see down here where we're
updating the HTML with all of
our status elements?
Well, we're going to give
the DOM a break.
Optimize this by using
the detach function.
This allows us to remove an
element from the DOM, do
things to it, and then append
it back to the DOM.
So instead of updating all the
HTML elements while they're
displayed, we're going to
remove it from the page,
modify it, and then display
it all at once.
It's a little more efficient.
So here you can see, we detach
the status list from the DOM.
Then we update it with our
new status elements.
And then we re-append it
back to our status div.
And that's all there is to it.
Now, when we go back to our page
and we update our flight
status, we can see that it
properly detaches, updates,
and re-attaches, not that
we can see that.
But now, it's a little
more efficient.
And it's time for you to try
this in the challenges.