You're watching JavaScript,
The Return Flight.
And this is level two, where
we're going to be using some
JavaScript to organize
our jQuery code.
With all the code that we wrote
in level one, things are
starting to get messy in our
application.js file, and a
little disorganized.
So in this level, we're going
to take a look at two
different ways we can organize
this code, starting with
refactoring it to use
JavaScript objects.
Here you can see, we have
a confirmation variable.
Inside of that we have a
JavaScript object, which has
an Init key, which contains
a function.
This is where we're going to put
all of our event handlers.
Then when we want to call this
Init function, we place it
inside of our document
ready and simply call
confirmation Init.
So every piece of functionality
that has to do
with confirmation is going
to get wrapped up in that
JavaScript object.
So as I mentioned, inside of our
Init method we create our
event handlers.
So here we have our click
handler for our button.
Inside of that it does
the Ajax call.
And then here we have the
view-boarding-pass click handler.
And these handlers get invoked
when the document is ready,
and it calls the confirmation
Init method.
There's one more step we can
take to organize our
JavaScript objects.
And that is to pull out the
call backs from our event
handlers, the functions
inside here.
So let's pull this out and
give it its own key.
We're going to call it
load confirmation.
And that's where we're going
to have our Ajax call.
Then above, in our confirmation
click handler,
we're simply going to pass
in that function, calling
this.loadConfirmation.
We need to use this when we call
load confirmation because
we're referencing the current
object that we're inside.
Now, we'll use the same
technique with the other click
handler and pull out that
function call back into its
own key, showBoardingPass.
Then we'll specify
this.showBoardingPass to send
in this function. Now, if we go
back in the web page, yep, it
still works.
And this time our code
is much cleaner.
Now, it's time for you to try
out a JavaScript object in the
challenges.