You may have heard of the
term JSON before.
It stands for JavaScript
Object Notation.
And it's simply a data format,
kind of like XML, if you know
what XML is.
And up until now, when we've
been doing AJAX requests,
we've always been getting HTML
back as the response from the
server, and we simply load
it into the page.
Here was the HTML from
our last example.
So in this case, our server
is deciding how we want to
display that information
in the page.
Because it's already giving us
formatted HTML, and we just
put it in there.
However, what if the
response was JSON?
It might look something
like this.
As you can see, we have keys
and values for all the
important information that we
need to display to the user.
And now, it's up to us, it's up
to our JavaScript code, to
take that data and format it,
maybe into some HTML, and
display it on the page.
If we look back at our previous
code, we're going to
need to make some modifications
if we want to be
using JSON.
First thing we can do is specify
that the response
we're getting back we expect
to be in a JSON format.
Then we can also specify
a content type.
This gets sent, with a request,
to the server and
tells the server, hey,
we want this response
to be in a JSON format.
We also need to change the
success call back.
Because as you see here, we're
simply taking the result we
get back from the server and
displaying it on the page.
But we don't want to
display our JSON.
Instead, we want to create some
HTML out of it and then
display it on the page.
So let's do that now.
Just for reference, here's the
JSON that gets sent as a
response from the server.
Now, our JavaScript will
automatically convert this
from JSON into a JavaScript
object.
So we can use that to construct
our HTML, which
you'll see in a minute.
Here, we declare a variable
called message, which starts
out as just two paragraph
tags.
This little box, here at the
bottom, will show you what our
HTML looks like,
as we build it.
Then we're going to append to
this string the destination,
which will contain
result.location which is from
the JavaScript object
from our JSON.
Then we'll append the price
referencing result.totalPrice,
and then the number of nights, then
our confirmation code.
And then we'll simply
insert this new DOM
node into our HTML.
Put it all together,
and our final code looks
something like this.
But there's one more thing
that we can do
to clean this up.
There's some duplication
going on.
See, we're referencing the
endpoint from our AJAX request
and from inside the
form action.
So how do we eliminate
this duplication?
Well, one way people eliminate
this is by grabbing that
action attribute using
one of these
attribute helper methods.
So inside of our AJAX call,
instead of hard coding our URL
endpoint, we're simply going
to get the form element and
grab the action attribute
out of it.
All right,
so here's what our final event
handler looks like.
And if we jump into the form,
select a destination, the
number of tickets, and book it,
we can see that it works,
this time, using JSON.
Time for you to get familiar
with some JSON, and I'll see
you in the next level.