Here in our AJAX function we
have a success call back,
which tells our code what
to do when a request is
successful.
However, what happens when a
request gets a timeout, an
abort, or server error?
We need to tell our code what
to do in that case.
Which is why we're also going to
specify an error call back.
This call back as a couple
parameters, request, error
type and error message.
And we're just going to print
out error type and error
message to the screen
if an error happens.
So if we trigger our AJAX
request, and our server times
out-- it never returns
any response--
this is what we're
going to get.
This alert will appear
on our browser.
You might be wondering, how
long does our AJAX request
wait before it times out and
calls that error call back?
Well, every browser is
different, which is why we
might want to specify exactly
how long to wait using the
Timeout option.
Here you can see we specified
a timeout of 3,000.
That's 3,000 milliseconds which,
of course, amounts to
three seconds.
So after three seconds
it's going to
call that error callback.
There's two other call backs
you should be aware of.
The first is Before Send.
This runs before the AJAX
request gets fired off.
This might be a good place in
our code to trigger a spinner,
or a loading screen, so the
user knows that an AJAX
request has been fired off
and is waiting to receive
something back from
the server.
Then there's a complete
call back.
This is going to get run after
success or after error.
So it's probably the last thing
that's going to get run
in our AJAX function.
And this might be a good
place to turn off
that loading screen.
In our case, we're going to use
a little plane animation
to tell our user that the AJAX
request has been fired off.
So here we are back in our
browser, and when we click the
flight details button we can
see that little plane
animation pops up, and then
once our data has been
returned from or AJAX request,
it gets loaded into the page
as you see here.
Now let's click on the View
Boarding Pass link.
And it doesn't seem
to be working.
Turns out we've got a
bug in our code and
we need to fix it.
Here is our AJAX response that
came back from the server that
contains our View Boarding
Pass link.
And here is the click
handler which
doesn't seem to be working.
This is the one that looks for
the View Boarding Pass class,
and adds a click handler which
shows the boarding pass.
Well it turns out that this code
only gets run once when
the page is loaded, but when the
page is loaded, our View
Boarding Pass link
didn't exist yet.
It didn't exist until after
we ran our AJAX call.
So we need to change this click
handler so that it's
always looking for this link,
and not just once when the
page is loaded.
To fix this we're going to
use Event Delegation.
So here, you can see, we're
telling the browser now to
listen for click events inside
confirmation, and when they
happen, check to see if the
target was View Boarding Pass.
And if it is, go ahead and
show that boarding pass.
So now if we go back into our
browser, we can view flight
details, and now we can also
view the boarding pass.
You've reached the
end of level one.
It's time for you to do a few
more AJAX challenges, and I'll
see you in the next level.