JavaScript objects are great
for organizing our code.
We start out with an init method
and inside, DOM load this
init method gets called.
However, this is limited to
one confirmation per page.
What if we needed
to have multiple
confirmations on our page?
Then we might want to use
a function instead to
encapsulate our code.
A function might look something
like this, where we
have capital Vacation.
And we can send in parameters
into our function, which
allows us to customize them.
Then we will initialize the
vacation to this destination,
much like we initialized
in our object.
Then inside of our document
ready, we can call this
function by using this syntax,
sending in specific
parameters, if we want to.
In this case, we're going to
have a Paris vacation and a
London vacation.
Let's take a closer look at this
function, add a few more
lines of code, starting
with console.log.
console.log is a function that
we use in JavaScript to do
debugging on our browser
console.
If you're not familiar, you want
to get more familiar with
this, again, check out
the Chrome Dev Tools
course that we have.
Inside of our vacation function,
we're going to
create a details method.
This will contain a function
which prints out the
destination onto the console.
To invoke this function, all
we need to do is call
paris.details
parenthesis.
And we'll call the same method
on our London vacation.
Now if we open up developer
tools and run this code, we'll
see that it prints out, as
we might expect, Paris.
And then it prints out London.
Pretty straightforward.
Could we call paris.destination?
We are sending in that
destination.
Well, it turns out, we can't.
We can't access locally scoped
variables, which is a subtle
difference between JavaScript
objects
and JavaScript functions.
You can see here, it prints
out undefined.
Let's take a look back at our
JavaScript object from the
previous section, and then
we'll move this into a
reusable function.
So here, you can see we started
with init method that
had our event handlers.
Then we have the load
confirmation and show boarding
pass methods.
And these all get fired off when
we call confirmation.init
in our document ready.
To reorganize this JavaScript
object into a reusable
function, we're going to
start by declaring a
confirmation function.
This takes one parameter, which
we're going to call el.
el refers to the element, the
jQuery element, we're going to
be passing in to
this function.
We're going to save a reference
to this passed in
element, so we can use it in
our callbacks, later on.
Then our helper methods go here,
and our event handlers
go here, which we'll
see in a minute.
Then inside of our document
ready function, we can call
our confirmation function,
passing in the Paris element.
And we can call our London
confirmation, passing in the
London element.
Now let's add our methods
and event listeners.
So here, you can see we have our
load confirmation method
which contains a function
callback.
And also, we have our show
boarding pass method.
Then we're going to declare
our click handlers.
The first click handler happens
on the element that
we passed in.
So we can simply call
this.el.on.
In order to make this function
reusable, we need to revise
some of the callbacks.
See, inside some of them, we
have some hard coded elements.
Right, so this, here, will target
all of the tickets.
And in our case, we only want
to target the ticket that is
inside our current vacation.
So we're going to go ahead and
create a new variable called
ticket, which finds
the ticket inside
of our current vacation.
Then inside of our callback,
we can simply say,
this.ticket.
Now if we jump into our browser
and try it, we can see
that it doesn't work still.
Why is that?
Well, it turns out inside of
this code, we're referencing
the wrong this.
This is where jQuery starts
to get confusing.
So if we look back in our code
and we did some debugging, we
would learn that the this inside
of the success callback
isn't referring to the right this.
This is the wrong this.
Right?
I know, it gets confusing.
See, it turns out that sometimes
jQuery changes the
value of this.
And inside AJAX callbacks,
this is
set to the AJAX settings.
So we need some way of
specifying to our AJAX
callback what the value
of this should be.
So to fix this, and to use the
right this, we're going to
declare a variable called
confirmation and
set it equal to this.
Then inside of our AJAX call,
we're going to set a new
option called context and set
that equal to confirmation.
This option allows us to set
the value of this inside of
our callbacks, which
should fix this.
So if we go back into our
browser, we can see now when
we click on the buttons,
everything works as it should.
So we fixed the load
confirmation method.
But the show boarding pass
method still has some hard
coded selectors in it.
You know, this is the link that runs when
that link is clicked, and
we show the boarding pass.
So inside of this method, you
can see we prevent default, we
hide the view boarding pass
link, we show the boarding
pass image.
These are the two lines of
code that we need to fix.
But how do we reference
these elements?
Do we use this or do we
use confirmation?
Well, to figure that out,
let's write two
lines to the console.
We'll write out this
to the console.
And we'll write out confirmation
If you ever get confused, this
is a good way to do a little
debugging, to figure out
which object is what.
So now, if we go on to the
console, we can see that this
represents the link that
was clicked, the view
boarding pass link.
And confirmation refers
to the confirmation
object that we're inside.
So our code can be revised so
that we hide the link that was
clicked, which is referred
to here as this.
And then we want to get the
vacation element out of the
confirmation function, find
the boarding pass
image, and show it.
Then if we jump back into our
browser, we can view the
flight details for each vacation
and also view each
boarding pass.
Time for you to create some
reusable functions.
And I'll see you in level three,
where we're going to go
into even more AJAX.