You're watching jQuery, The
Return Flight, and in level
three, we're going to
be going over Ajax
forms, and using JSON.
In this level, we have a new
example, it's a form where we
can select a destination, the
number of tickets we want, and
then we can book the trip.
When we click that, it submits
the form as a full page
refresh and it comes up
with this response.
Now, how might we do
that using Ajax?
So when that button is clicked,
we need to figure out
how to trigger an
Ajax request.
It would look something
like this.
We listen for the Submit event
on the form, and then inside
of the callback function, we're
going to do an Ajax
request to the book URL, and
inside there, we need to
specify the type of the
request to POST.
So now, when we select a
destination, select the number
of tickets, click to book the
trip, we oh it didn't work.
Something went wrong with
our Ajax request.
So let's take a look
back at our code.
Oh.
I see what's missing.
We forgot
event.preventDefault to
prevent the default behavior
of the form, which is to
submit and refresh
the entire page.
So without it, it was doing the
Ajax request, and it was
also submitting the form and
refreshing the page.
Well, we don't want it to
refresh the page, so we'll
prevent that default behavior
from happening.
All right.
There's something else that's a
little fishy here, and that
is that we're doing the Ajax
request now, but it's not
sending any of that form data
over, any of that form we
filled out.
So how do we add that?
Right.
That's the destination and
the quantity you see
here in this HTML?
We need to attach that
to our Ajax request.
As we saw in level one, we can
use the data option to send
this information to our server,
specifying a key of
destination, grabbing the value
out of the HTML, and
doing the same thing with
quantity, wrapping it up in a
JavaScript object, and sending
that to the server.
This works fine, but there's
a better way.
jQuery comes with a shortcut
method called serialize which
you can use to merge all
of the form fields for
submission.
So to use serialize, we simply
put it right here and call
form.serialize, it pulls all the
data out of the form and
sends it along with
our Ajax request.
If we want to do anything on
the page when our Ajax
response comes back, we're
going to need to define a
success callback,
as you see here.
The result coming back from the
server is going to be a
snippet of HTML which
looks like this.
So inside our success callback,
let's simply remove
the form, hide the current
vacation div, populate it with
the HTML from the result was
returned, and then finally
fade it back in.
What else can we do to
improve this code?
Well, remember back in level
two when there were two DOM
look-ups looking us the same
element, we re-factor this
into a variable.
Let's do that again.
So we'll create a form variable
and set it equal to
this, which, because we're
inside an event handler,
happens to be the
form element.
Then inside of our data option,
we can just specify
form.serialize, and then inside
success, form.remove.
And then here we are back
in our browser.
We select the destination, the
number of tickets, and we book
the trip, and it happens.
And this time, using Ajax,
without a page refresh.
Now why don't you try to create
some Ajax forms, and
I'll see you in the
next section.