In this next section, we're
going to be taking a look at
JavaScript plugins, which are a
way to encapsulate behavior
that we might want to
reuse in different
places around our website.
Here's our vacation page again
where we can show prices, just
like you see here.
And we can also specify if
we're not interested in
specific vacations.
We can also show all prices
for all the vacations.
And we want to encapsulate
all of this
functionality into a plugin.
Here's the HTML from
that page.
So when we click that Show Price
button, we're going to
add a "p" for the price.
When we click the Not Interested
link, it's going to
hide that vacation.
And then finally, when we click
the Show All Prices
button, it's going
to show all the
prices for all the vacations.
So let's start setting
up our plugin.
To do that, we write
$.fn.pricify.
Pricify is the name of our
plugin, and using that .fn
makes this method available
to all jQuery objects.
So inside there, we
define a function.
And just to start taking
baby steps, let's
do two console logs.
One to designate that
pricify was called,
and the second log to figure out
the value of this, which
will be the jQuery object the
plugin was called on.
To invoke this method,
we simply need to
grab a jQuery object.
In this case, we're going to
grab all the Vacation objects,
and call .pricify.
If we take a look at the
console, we can say that
pricify called gets
executed once.
And then for this, we can see
it's the value of each of our
different vacation list items.
Let's ditch the console
logs and start
implementing this plugin.
So first thing we're going
to do is set the Vacation
variable equal to this, which
will be of course, vacation--
based on how we call it here.
Then we're going to create a
ClickHandler when the button
gets pushed.
And then, of course, inside of
that, we'll get the price,
just like we did before--
create the details, which are
what it costs to book for
three days.
And then, we'll hide
the button, and
append the price details.
Then lastly, we only want the
Pricify method to get loaded
when the document is ready.
So now, we can jump back
into our browser.
And when we click Show Price--
uh oh, you see what it did?
It showed you the prices for
all of them, all at once.
And it's the same price.
Which is definitely
not what we want.
We need each of these to show
each price, as we click the
different buttons.
So what went wrong?
Well, it turns out that when we
set this equal to vacation,
this is pointing to all of
the vacation elements.
Remember the console
logs from earlier?
It's all the elements it once.
And when we call Append, it'll
append it in multiple
places, which is why
we saw that price
on each of the vacations.
So to fix this, we're going to
use the jQuery object method
called Each, which
is going to go
through each of our vacations.
This is similar to our previous
Each that we saw in
previous levels, except that was
a jQuery utility method.
And this is just an Each method
that we can call on any
jQuery object.
To use it, we're going to
call this .each
and send in a function.
This of course is going
to be an array of
our vacation items.
And then as it goes into the
function, running it one time
for each item, it's going to set
the value of that vacation
equal to the Vacation variable,
set the proper
ClickHandler for each of them,
and then it should work.
So now if we go back into our
browser, we can see that Show
Price works properly for
each of our vacations.
Now, what if we wanted to allow
our plugin to accept
different arguments?
For example, if we wanted to
change the number of days that
it displays in the price.
Well, we could simply send
in a JavaScript object,
like you see here.
Then in our plugin, we
simply update it to
take the Options parameter.
Then we have the normal
Price variable.
And then in our Details
variable, we simply build a
string using the Options
JavaScript object.
So we just call options.days to
get out the number of days
that we want to calculate
the price for.
But what if we wanted our plugin
to take in optional
parameters?
For example, if we want it to
default to showing the price
for three days, if we
don't specify it.
So we can either call it with
five days, as you see here, or
with no parameters at all,
and it will default to three.
To do this properly, we're going
to learn a new utility
method called Extend, which
can take in two or more
JavaScript objects
and combine them.
So for example, if we called
Extend with two JavaScript
objects, one having days three,
the other having price
five, it would combine them into
one JavaScript object,
which has days three,
price five.
If we called Extend with days
three and then an empty
JavaScript object, we would
simply get back days three.
Then if we called days three
and then days five, this
second JavaScript object would
overwrite the first one.
And we get days five.
So as you can see, this is how
we can specify a default value
of days three.
And then if we pass in a second
JavaScript object that
simply has days five in
it, it's going to
override the default.
So here we are, back in
our Pricify plugin.
We're going to use the Extend
Utility method, set the
default number of days to three,
and then the second
parameter is going to the
Options object, which we pass
in to the function.
These two objects will be
combined into a settings
variable, which we can
then use later on.
Now we have other settings
inside of this plugin, which
we have defined as
variables here.
But why not define them
inside of our
Settings JavaScript object?
Let's do that.
Let's move them inside
of our settings.
So now we have our Settings
object with all the different
settings that our plugin uses.
So now, we need to go back
into our EventHandler and
update that to use
our new settings.
And to access each of these
values inside of our settings,
we'll do like settings
vacation.
We'll do settings.days
and settings.price.
OK.
Let's use these.
So let's move them
into our code.
So first, we use
settings.vacation.on, to get
our current vacation.
Then we'll create the details
DOM object, then hide the Show
Price button, and lastly, append
our DOM object to our
current vacation.
So now if we go back into our
browser, we can see that, yep,
it still works.
And now our code is
a lot cleaner
and even more flexible.
But we still need to implement
this Show All Prices button.
Let's do that now.
Now here's the HTML for our Show
All Prices link, which
has a class of Show Prices.
And we could make this trigger
all of the Click Pricify
events on all of the buttons.
But there's a cleaner
way to do this.
We're going to create a custom
event which will call the same
function that Click
Pricify uses.
So the first step down
this road is to
factor out this function.
Let's split this out into
its own function,
and we're going to call it
"Show." This encapsulates all
the behavior we want
when we click on
the Show Price button.
So now our Click Pricify
EventHandler simply calls this
Show function.
Let's shrink that down.
And now we're going to create
a custom event called Show--
it's show.pricify--
which calls the same
Show function.
Now all we have to do to make
the Show All Prices button
work is create a ClickHandler
like you see here--
prevent the default behavior
from happening; we don't want
it to follow the Show
All Prices link--
and then trigger the custom
event show.pricify on all of
our vacations.
Now when we call the Show All
Prices button, that custom
event gets called.
And they all work.
Next up though, let's go ahead
and implement that Not
Interested link, so it makes the
vacation disappear when we
click on it.
Inside each of the vacations,
they have a link at the
bottom, which has
Not Interested.
So to make this work,
first we're going to
create a Remove function.
This is going to grab our
current vacation, fade it off
the page, and then turn off
all of the EventHandlers.
Lastly, we need to create a
ClickHandler, so that when
somebody clicks the Not
Interested link, it calls the
Remove function that
we just declared.
Now when we jump back into our
browser, we can click the Not
Interested link, and
it will properly
fade off each vacation.
Plugins can be really helpful
when you need to encapsulate a
piece of behavior that you may
want to use in different parts
of your application, or even
package up and use in
different applications.
Now it's time for you to
create you own plugins.
And I'll see you in
the final level.