[Initial 27 seconds not captioned.  An update is planned!]
[SINGING] The
Flatlanders need to store
to sell their gems and more -
and they need it really quick.
Angular will do the trick.
Directives set the
stage in your HTML page.
Controllers give your wrap
the behavior that it lacks.
Write expressions so that
you can add your data
to the view. And modules
make connections
with dependency injections.
You're a scripting
connoisseur when
shaping up with Angular JS.
Welcome to Shaping
Up With AngularJS.
I'm Gregg Pollack,
and in Level One
we'll be giving
you an introduction
to what is AngularJS. We'll
show you the application we'll
be building together
in this course,
and then introducing you to the
core elements of any AngularJS
application.
In order to learn
AngularJS, it's important
that you're very familiar
with HTML and CSS,
as well as JavaScript.
If you're not familiar
with JavaScript,
Code School's got a great
course JavaScript Road
Trip, which you
should go check out.
It's also nice if you
know some testing tools.
Behavior Driven Development,
Test-Driven Development,
because AngularJS is
really easy to test.
And you should be doing that
in a professional application.
Not so important, you
don't need to know jQuery,
Ruby on Rails, Python, PHP,
or any of those back end
frameworks.
AngularJS is just a
front end framework,
so all you need to
know is JavaScript.
You may want to use AngularJS
when you're using JavaScript
to build any sort
of dynamic website.
AngularJS is going to help you
organize your JavaScript code.
It's going to help you
create responsive websites,
meaning they're fast, they
respond quickly to user input.
Also, if you're
familiar with jQuery,
AngularJS plays really
well with jQuery.
And it's also, as
I mentioned before,
really easy to test,
which means you
can create
maintainable software.
Let's dive a little
deeper into this word
"responsive" and see what I mean.
So here's the Code
School website.
And you'll see that when I click
on a link like, screencasts,
the page goes blank for second,
and then reloads that page.
And then I click
on something else,
and it goes, and it processes,
and brings up something,
and I get to see that page.
This is a traditional page
refresh response cycle,
but what's going on
behind the curtains?
So here we have our
browser and our web server.
And our browser's going
to initiate a request
to our server.
The server responds with the
web pages and assets, the HTML
and JavaScript, and our browser
loads of the entire web page.
But when the user
clicks on a link,
initiates a new
request, and the server
responds with a new
web page and assets,
the browser to load up
the entire web page again.
Obviously, laid out like this,
it's not quite efficient.
So now here's an
example of a web page
I would call responsive.
This is our recent
Discover Drive course.
You'll see when I
click around this page,
the page refresh is
almost unnoticeable.
The pages so responsive
and quick every time
we click on a link.
So what's going on here?
Well, behind the curtains when
a request is first fired off,
the server responds back with
all the web page and assets,
as you might expect,
and the browser
loads up the entire webpage.
This time, when a
user clicks a link,
something different
is going to happen.
It's only going to
request the information
it needs to update the page.
In this case, just
some JSON data.
Once our browser
has this data, it's
going to load it into
the existing page,
and update what we
see on our browser.
An increasing number
of applications
these days are building
their own APIs.
They might do this to interface
with a mobile application,
say on iOS.
They might also build an API so
that other developers can build
applications that communicate
with their application.
They might also built APIs
to communicate with front-end
applications, like
the application we're
building in this
course using AngularJS.
So in this course, we'll
be building a front-end
application using AngularJS,
which will communicate
with a back-end application.
But we're not going to
be building that back-end
application, we're just going
to focus on the front-end.
A simple definition of AngularJS
is a client-side JavaScript
framework for adding
interactivity to HTML.
We need to figure out
how to tell our HTML when
to trigger our JavaScript.
So here we have some
HTML, how might we
tell it to call this function,
which triggers an alert?
In AngularJS we add behavior to
our HTML through directives.
A directive as a marker
on an HTML tag that tells
AngularJS to run or reference
some JavaScript code.
So the answer here is to add
the attribute ng-controller
to our body tag, setting
it equal to "StoreController"
which is the name
of our function.
And if we loaded this up,
we might get this alert.
Obviously, this is a
really contrived example,
and you would never actually
write this AngularJS code,
but you get the gist of it.
Directives, it's how
we bind the behavior.
The application
we'll be building
in the rest of this course
is our Flatlander's store.
In it you can see we
have several thumbnails
of different products.
We can tab through different
information about each of them
and we have reviews.
You'll see a list of
reviews and we'll even
be able to submit our own
review using this form here.
The first step, if you want
to start playing with AngularJS,
is to download the library
from the official website.
In the application we'll
be building in this course,
we're going to be using Twitter
Bootstrap, which you also
might want to download, and
feel free to follow along.
Let's start coding up our HTML.
You can see here we've included
the CSS for Twitter Bootstrap
and we've included the
AngularJS library, which
we downloaded as well.
The next component of
our AngularJS application
that we need to learn
about is modules.
Modules are where
we write pieces
of our AngularJS application.
It's how we keep our
code encapsulated.
Because of this, it makes
our code more maintainable,
more readable,
and more testable.
Also, it's where we define
all of the dependencies
for our application.
Because we might run one
module and we can tell our code
this module depends
on these two modules.
So it shouldn't surprise you
that the very piece of code
that you write in
AngularJS is a module line.
So we're going to right var
app - that's our application -
equals angular - that's the
AngularJS library - dot module -
because we're
creating a new module.
We give it a name -
In this case, "store."
And then, in that little arrays
syntax, we define dependencies.
We don't have any
dependencies yet,
but we still have to
send in an empty array.
Because that's how we roll.
This piece of code is going
to live inside an app.js file.
So we're going to need to
include that in our HTML,
as you can see right here.
Then we'll need to add an
attribute to our HTML tag.
In this case, ng-app equals "store."
ng-app, remember, is
another directive.
This directive creates
an AngularJS application
by running this module
when the document loads.
The modules isn't doing anything
yet, but just by including it,
it's going to treat the
HTML inside of this element
as part of the AngularJS app.
And this means we can
start writing expressions.
Expressions are how we insert
dynamic values into our HTML.
Here's some basic ones just
using numerical operations.
So if we say "I am 4 + 6," that's
going to render out on the page
as "I am 10."
We can also do
string operations.
Saying "hello" +
"you" and that's
going to evaluate to "hello
you," as you might expect.
We'll be using lots
of expressions inside
of our AngularJS application,
but for more examples
check out this URL.
So if I move "hello you" into
our AngularJS application,
and I load it up
locally in my browser,
I'm going to get "hello you,"
just as you might expect.
So we learned about directives,
modules, and expressions.
Why don't you try
putting them all together
in the challenges and I'll
see you in the next section.