[MUSIC PLAYING]
[SINGING] Starting back in
the machine age,
the telephone had
just taken the stage.
No one had predicted
its acceleration,
evolving all of
our communication.
Today we build with storyboards
Use Xcode projects
where they're stored.
Controllers with scroll,navigate, and tables
Outlets,
and actions, buttons and labels.
To code a phone is a learned
gift with the App Evolution
with Swift.
Welcome back to App
Evolution with Swift.
In this level, we'll
look at how to display
lists of data in tables.
Dropping labels and image views
directly under the main view,
makes sense to
display our content,
until we have something that
would naturally appear better
in a list, like
this list of phones.
In this case, it
makes more sense
to use a Table View,
instead of a normal view,
and we'll hook that up to
a Table View Controller,
instead of a normal
view controller.
A Table View Controller is
just a special view controller
object that has
support for working
with Table Views built in.
The main view of a
Table View Controller
is a special object
called, Table View,
and Table Views have subviews,
just like view controllers do.
But those subviews
are called table cells,
any normal subviews like
labels and image views,
then go inside of
those table cells.
Let's jump back into Xcode to
create our first Table View
controller.
To start, we'll turn
off the assistant editor
and go back in the
standard editor mode,
and we'll scroll over so we
have some more room to work.
Then, we'll create a brand
new scene, using a Table View
controller, instead of a
regular view controller,
and line it up a bit next
to the first view controller.
We'll also make sure it's
the initial view controller,
so that we'll see it when
we build and run the app.
Now, let's click on the
Good As Old Phones folder.
Right click and choose
New File, and again, we'll
use the Cocoa Touch class
in the iOS source section.
Hit Next, but this time
instead of subclassing UI view
controller, we'll subclass
UI Table View Controller,
and we'll name this class
products Table View Controller.
We don't need to create a zip
file because we've already
got that in our
storyboard and we'll
keep the language as Swift.
Then we'll hit Next, save
it in our project folder.
And you'll notice, there's a
ton of boilerplate code in table
view controllers,
we're not going
to need most of this
for this course,
so let's just delete all of
it so we can start fresh.
Don't forget to leave that
last curly brace, because it
closes out the class.
Back in the main
storyboard, we'll
click on the table
view controller scene
and go into the class
inspector, and set our class
to products Table View
controller, and hit Return.
And now the storyboard
Table View Controller
is associated with our products
Table View Controller Swift
file.
We need to do one
more thing now,
though, you can see that
there is already a prototype
cell in this Table View.
If we click it to select it and
look at the Attributes panel
you'll see there's a
field labeled Identifier.
We want to set that Identifier
to product cell and that's
going to let us access this
prototype cell in our Swift
file.
Let's jump back in the slides
to talk about reuse identifiers
and how dynamic cells work.
Table cells are recycled,
as they scroll off screen,
and the only new cells
that ever get created,
are the very first ones, as
the Table View first loads.
Every other cell that's
created after that,
is just pulled out of
that recycling queue.
Let's take a look
at how this works.
On load, three new
cells are created,
we label them A, B, and C.
As the Table View scrolls a bit,
now four unique
cells are visible,
the original A, B,
and C, but also,
cell D. So in our
applications memory,
there's four cells loaded,
then after some more scrolling,
cell A is no longer visible.
But, rather than completely
removing it from memory,
it gets placed in
this recycling queue.
On screen only, cells
B, C, and D are visible.
After even more scrolling, a new
cell is ready to be displayed,
but there's no need to create
a brand new cell object
because the recycled cell
A can just be re-used.
At the end here, there are
still only four cells in memory,
even though our Table View has
displayed a total of five cells,
with different content.
This is a simple
example, but think
of a Table View in
something like the music
app, where you might have
300 or 400 rows of albums.
It wouldn't be memory efficient
to load all 300 of those cells
into memory, so this
recycling approach,
make's sure that there's only
a few cells that are ever
created, and just recycled
with new content and new data,
as the table scrolls.
It's really memory efficient.
Because these
cells get recycled,
unlike normal view controllers,
the content for a table cell
needs to be set in code.
UI Table View Controller
is like a view controller,
with table specific
functions and two
of those that we'll use, and
are automatically run for us,
are the functions TableView
NumberOfRowsInSection,
and TableView
CellForRowAtIndexPath.
The first sets the number
of rows in the Table View,
and the second is
responsible for creating
one cell for each row.
This function looks really
long, so let's break apart
what it means.
First, is the name of
the function Table View,
and there's
parentheses after it,
inside of those parentheses,
are two parameters as variables,
which are then available inside
of the body of the function,
so we can use them,
if we need them.
The variables table
view and section,
the arrow end at the end
means that the function
should return a number.
Now you might have
noticed something strange
about these two functions—
they both have the same name,
TableView.
But, they're actually
different functions,
because they have different
parameter names inside
of the function declaration.
The first one has the
parameter names TableView
and NumberOfRowsInSection,
and the second
has the parameters TableView
and CellForRowAtIndexPath.
Because of that they're
different functions
and they perform
different operations.
Back in the TableView
NumberOfRowsInSection version
of the function, we
need to return an Int.
So, if we start simple
and do just that,
we can write return five in
the body of this function
and that means this TableView
view will have five rows.
Now on to our second
Table View function,
the CellForRowAtIndexPath one.
This function runs one
time for each number of rows
that we set in the function
above, which was five.
Based on the arrow at the end
of the function, we can see
this one should return a
UI Table View cell object.
We can create the cell by
writing this line of code,
which looks at the storyboard
for any prototype cells
with a re-use identifier
of product cell
and then creates a cell
object when it finds one.
Remember, that we set that
re-use identifier back
in Xcode. Then we
can just return
our new cell from the function.
Now we got our code, in
the Table View Controller,
to create five rows and five
cells to go in those rows.
But if we build
and run right now,
our Table View is
a bit confusing,
it looks like it's showing
way more than five rows,
but that's not accurate.
It's a little bit easier
to see what's going on,
by stopping the app,
clicking on the Table View,
and in the Attributes inspector,
changing the style from plain
to grouped.
When we do that
we can even see
that the prototype cell
looks a bit different.
It looks like the row
is isolated, with gray
above and below it.
Now when we build and
run the app again.
We can clearly see that the
Table View has five cells.
They don't look like
much yet, but before we
go any further, why don't you
practice creating some cells
and take some
challenges? And I'll
see you in the next section.