(SINGING) Starting back
in the machine age,
the telephone had
just taken the stage.
No one predicted
its acceleration,
evolving all of
our communication.
Today, we build
with storyboards,
use Xcode projects
where they're stored.
Controllers with scroll,
navigating tables, outlets,
actions, buttons, and labels.
To code a phone
is a learned gift,
with the App
Evolution with Swift.
Welcome back to App
In this level,
we're going to look
at how we can link views
and buttons up to code.
We've already got a
label displaying text
and an image of you displaying
an image in our storyboard.
But we want to be able to
set those values in code.
We also want to make the
button respond to being tapped.
The place we're going
to write that code
is in a View Controller.
You might have noticed
in the storyboard
that the Main View is embedded
inside of a View Controller.
The reason for having
a controller object
separate from a view object is
that you can separate program
logic from the display of data.
This is commonly referred to
as MVC, model View Controller.
Separating these two
out makes code easier
to understand than just having
all of it in one big file.
View Controllers can tell
a view what to display.
And then views can
tell controllers
when the user is
interacting with them.
We've got to do a
little bit of setup
in the storyboard to connect a
View Controller to Swift code.
So let's jump back into
Xcode and get that set up.
Let's create our
first Swift file
so we can write code
to change the label
text, the image
displayed, and that we
can use to respond to
taps on the button.
To start, click on the folder
name in the Project Navigator.
Right click on it
and choose New File.
In this list of file
templates that come up,
we want to make sure we're
looking at the iOS Source
section.
And you might think we want
the Swift file template,
but we actually want
Cocoa Touch Class.
Then we hit Next.
And we're asked what name
we want for this class.
We'll will delete what's
there and type Product View
Controller.
And for the subclass, we'll
type UIViewController.
We don't need to
create a XIB file,
but we do want to make sure
the language for the project
is set to Swift.
Then when we hit Next,
we're asked where
we want to save this file.
And our default save location
is the project folder, which
is a good place to save it.
When we hit Create, we'll get
our productviewcontroller.swift
file.
You'll notice there
is some starter code.
We won't need all of that.
We don't need the Did
Receive Memory Warning
function or the whole navigation
section at the bottom.
Notice that we are leaving one
curly bracket after the stuff
we're deleting.
This is the closing curly
bracket for that class
that's open on line 11.
So that one needs to stay.
So we'll highlight both
of those and hit Delete.
When we delete that code,
we've got a really nice start
to this Swift file.
There's one more step, though.
We need to associate
this View Controller
Swift file with the View
Controller object that's
in the storyboard.
So we'll go back into
the storyboard file,
click on the View Controller
in the seen navigator,
and click on the third page
of the Inspector panel.
In that panel, we'll click
into the class setting
at the top for the Custom
Class section and type
ProductViewController
and hit Enter.
We can check that it worked,
because the scene navigator now
updates to show that the name
changed from View Controller
to Product View Controller.
Now our storyboard
product View Controller
is linked up with our
productviewcontroller.swift
file.
To be able to change a subview
in a storyboard with code,
we need to create an outlet.
Outlets are a way
to make a connection
between a storyboard object
and a variable in a Swift file.
Although the main
view is automatically
connected when we linked
our Swift file to the View
Controller in the storyboard,
all of the subviews
still need to be
manually connected.
These connections
are called outlets.
And we need to create one
between our View Controller
and label subview so that
the controller can tell
the label what text to show.
Then in the Swift file,
you can create a variable
and mark it as an
outlet there, too.
Remember, the controller Swift
file and the storyboard view
controller are
already connected.
But that outlet makes a
connection with the subviews
as well.
Let's jump back into Xcode to
see how to create an outlet.
To create an outlet
between the Swift file
and storyboard, the
easiest thing to do
is open up the Assistant Editor.
The icon looks like two
interlocking circles up
in the toolbar.
When we click that
icon, it's kind of
hard to read what's
on the screen.
The default layout is
to have the storyboard
on the left and the associated
Swift file on the right.
We're going to
change that, though,
by clicking on the
tiny dropdown arrow
and sending the Assistant
Editor to appear on the bottom.
Now it's easier to see the
storyboard scene navigator
and editor and the
Swift file down below.
Next, we'll click on the
label in the scene navigator
and control click from that
label down to the Swift file,
right in between the class line
and the viewDidLoad function.
When we let go of
the mouse button,
another little helper pops up.
We want to create an outlet so
the first default is correct.
It's happening on the Product
View Controller object.
And we need a name that will
become a variable in the Swift
file that we can use to access
the label in the storyboard.
This name can be anything,
but it's a good idea
to name it something obvious.
So here, we'll use the
name Product Name Label.
The type is a UIlabel.
That just has to match
the type of the object
in the storyboard.
And the storage should
be left as weak.
Then when you hit
Connect, the outlet code
gets automatically
generated for you.
And you see a darkened
in circle to the left
of the line numbers.
That means the
outlet is connected.
We're going to make one
more change here, though.
Instead of putting
the name of this phone
inside of the label
in the storyboard,
we're going to go back
into the Attributes panel.
And we're going to change
the text to Phone Name.
That way, we'll know for sure if
setting the name and the phone
in code works, because if
the text when we're done
is different from Phone
Name, we know we successfully
changed the text from code.
Here's what
productviewcontroller.swift
looks like after we
create that outlet.
Now we can access
our storyboard label
in the controller with the
name Product Name Label.
But where do we write code that
will change the label's text?
To answer that, let's look at
what happens when an app runs.
You might have noticed
a file in your project
that was automatically created
called AppDelegate.swift.
That runs a function
called UIApplicationMain
that actually starts your app.
Once the app starts,
it looks for a file
called Info.plist, which is also
automatically created for you.
And that Info.plist
file is where
the name of the
storyboard file is set.
Next, the storyboard
loads the View Controller
that's set as the
initial View Controller.
Then that View Controller
loads its view.
And loading that
view automatically
runs the viewDidLoad function.
And we'll set the text
for the label inside
of that viewDidLoad function.
We can do it like this, by
writing productNameLabel.text
and setting it equal
to a string, which
is just some characters
or numbers in quotes.
We can do this, because the
type of the label variable
is UILabel.
And UILabels have a
property called text
that we can set to change
the text of the label.
But how did we know that
UILabels had this property?
If you want to check
out what properties you
can set for each
type of object, you
can check out Apple's
official documentation.
Here's one item from the Swift
documentation for UILabel.
Docs show properties and
functions for each class.
The colon string here means that
the text property is expecting
us to assign a string to it.
It's impossible to remember
every property of every class
in UIKit, so you
end up referencing
the documentation a lot
when you're building an app.
When we build and
run our app, we
see that our text
did, in fact, change.
Remember, in our storyboard, we
just set some placeholder text.
But our Swift file
code overwrote that.
Now, let's jump back into
Xcode and do the same thing
with an image.
Still in our
Assistant Editor view
where the storyboard
is at the top
and the code is at the
bottom, let's click
on the Image View in the
seen navigator and control
click and drag
from the image view
object down to the Swift file
in between the first outlet
and the viewDidLoad function.
We get a little helper
like we did before.
This is, again, an outlet on
the Product View Controller.
For the name this time,
we'll use Product Image View.
The type is a UIImageView.
And the storage
will be weak again.
Now we've got another outlet,
this time connecting the image
view to a variable in code.
Like before, when we wanted
the test if this was working,
we deleted the label text.
So we'll go into the Inspector
panel for the image view,
highlight the image name,
delete it, and hit Return.
Now there is no image
set in this view
controller in the storyboard.
So we're going to have to
be able to set it in code.
Let's jump back in the
slides to see how to do that.
Just like before, our
controller Swift file
now has a property for
accessing the image view.
And we can set the image
property of that image view
to a new UIImage object.
And we'll pass in the
string phone-fullscreen3
for the name of that image.
Let's look at how the
UIImage class works.
Writing the name of a class
with parentheses after it,
like we did here, runs
an initializer function.
And that initializer function
returns a UIImage object.
Here in the documentation
for UIImage,
you can see there's
an init function.
That init function
is expecting you
to put a string with
a named parameter
inside the parentheses.
This initializer might
look a little confusing,
because it looks like it has
two parameters, named and name.
But you don't actually
have to worry about that.
You just have to know that the
first word, named, is the one
that you'll use when
you're passing a parameter
into the initializer.
When we were setting a label,
we sent the text property
equal to a string.
But here, we're setting an
image views image property
equal to a UIImage object.
And this initializer
returns a UIImage object
that the image view wants.
As of Swift version
3 in Xcode 8,
you've got another useful option
for setting an image in code
called image literals.
Image literals are
a special identifier
that can look directly
into your asset catalog
and intelligently
complete code based
on an image chosen from a list.
So here, instead of creating
an image with the UIImage
initializer, we can
instead delete that and start
typing the text, image literal.
As we do that, we
can just double
click on the image literal
option that pops up.
And we're greeted
with a pop up that
contains all of the images
in our asset catalog.
We'll select the
phone-fullscreen3 image.
And you can see that
it puts it in line
in your code with
a tiny preview.
Now, that literal represents
an actual UIImage object.
So you can assign it to the
image views image property.
And now, you can see
that the image is still
appearing, even though we
turned it off in the storyboard.
That's because it's
set by our code.
Now you try setting some
text and images in code
and take some
challenges, and I'll
see you in the next section.
.