[SINGING] Starting back
in the machine age,
the telephone had
just taken the stage.
No one predicted
its acceleration,
evolving all of
our communication.
Today we build with storyboards.
Use XCode projects
where they're stored.
Controllers with scroll,
navigating tables, outlets,
actions, buttons, and labels.
To code a phone is a learned
gift with the App Evolution
with Swift.
Welcome back to App
Evolution with Swift.
Our product View Controller
is in a really good place,
so we're going to switch gears
and work on a different screen
for our Contact View.
Now that Contact View is going
to contain more content that
can fit on the device.
So we're going to add
a Scroll View that
allows for stretching beyond
the bottom of the device screen
and scrolling up and down.
Scroll Views look a
lot like a normal view,
except for one thing.
If you have subviews
that are outside
of the visible
screen on the device,
you can scroll up and
down, left and right
or both, to see
all of the content.
Now the Scroll View is still
a subview of the main view,
but all of the rest of
the subviews on the screen
go inside of the Scroll View.
So let's jump into Xcode and
create our Contact screen
in a Scroll View.
To get started creating
our Scroll View,
we're going to create a brand
new View Controller scene
called Contact View Controller.
We'll search for a view
controller in the object panel
and slide our storyboard
to the right a little bit
so we've got some
more empty room.
Then we'll click and drag on
the View Controller Object
and place it on the
storyboard editor.
We've also got the
assistant editor still open,
so let's turn that off by
clicking on the first icon
to turn the standard
editor back on.
Now we've got a full
view of the storyboard.
Let's also go ahead and
create the Swift file
for this View Controller, too.
Click on the project folder.
Then right-click,
and choose New File.
Then Cocoa Touch Class
from the iOS source section
and click Next.
For the name of this
View Controller,
we'll call it the
ContactViewController.
Make sure it's a
UI View Controller
and the language is Swift.
And we'll save it in our
project folder like before.
And also like before, we'll
delete all that boilerplate
code, except for the
viewDidLoad function.
Back in the storyboard, we'll
click on the View Controller,
open up the Class page
of the Inspector panel,
and set the name to
Contact View Controller.
Now let's go back
into the object panel
and search for Scroll
View, and drag it
into the View Controller.
We'll make this view full
screen by grabbing the anchors
and adjusting the
width and height,
so that it takes
up the entire width
and height of the main view.
Now we are ready to
start loading content
into the Scroll View.
First, let's head over
to the Asset Catalog
and add some new images that
we'll use on this screen.
In the Asset Catalog,
we click the plus button
at the bottom of the
panel, choose Import,
and on our desktop in
our Image Files folder,
we've added a few more images.
One for the header
and three icons
we can use in the
Contacts section.
Back in our storyboard,
let's look for an Image View
in the Object Panel.
And we'll drag that
inside of the Scroll View.
Set the image for that image
view in the Attributes panel,
choosing the Image
Header Contact.
Then we click inside
of the Image View
so the image is selected.
And choose Editor,
Size to Fit Content.
Click out of the image.
And click and drag the
Image View into place
at the top of the screen.
Now let's grab a label and
drag it onto the Scroll View
and expand the
width to both edges.
We'll center the text, change
the font from System to Custom.
And, use Damascus again. Setting
the style to Bold and the size
to 24.
We'll also set the text to
About Us in all capital letters.
And then we'll adjust
the height of the label,
so we can see all of the text.
Now let's drag in another label.
But this label, we're not
going to make full width.
We're going to leave
some space on both sides.
And we'll set the alignment
to Justify instead of Center.
Our copywriter has
given us some text
that we can input into our
app for the About Us page.
So let's grab the
first line and copy it
with command-Z,
and back in Xcode,
paste it with command-V into
the Labels Text Attribute.
You can see that
the storyboard is
trying to fit all of
that text onto one line.
Even if we increase the
height of that label box,
it's still going to
fit all on one line.
Strangely enough, the way
you support multiple lines
on the label is to set
the number of lines to 0.
If we flip the number
of lines from 1 to 0,
now all of the text fits
across multiple lines.
We can tighten up the
label's width and height,
so it's not using any
more space than is needed.
For this font, instead
of using the System font,
we'll change it to Custom.
Use Georgia with the
regular style for the family
and will drop it
down to 16 points.
And, readjust the anchors
so the text fits nicely.
Rather than create
a brand new label
for the next block of
text, let's just duplicate
the one we have, since
all of the attributes
will be the same.
We can click on the
label and hit command-d.
And that will create a
duplicate that we can just
move below the first label.
You can see that the
storyboard is even
drawing some of those blue
anchor lines on the screen
to show how
everything is aligned.
We'll go back over to
our copywriter text,
copy the second line with
command-C, go back into Xcode,
select the text in
the Attributes panel.
Hit command-V to paste it
in, and then hit Return.
For the last label,
we'll do the same thing.
Click on the label.
Hit command-D. Line
it up into place.
Go back into the About Us copy.
Select the text.
Hit command-C to copy.
Back into Xcode,
highlight the label text.
Hit command-V to paste.
And hit Return.
Since this text
is only one line,
we can bump the number
of lines back up to one.
We'll also change
the font properties
from Regular to Italic and
drop the size down to 14.
Then, we'll scroll the
storyboard down a bit
and drag the bottom
label anchor up,
so it's not taking
up too much space.
Now, let's duplicate
the About Us header
and drag it down here.
And change the text to
say Contact in full caps.
If we want to add some icons
to this Contact section,
we can start by searching
for an Image View Object,
and drag it onto
the Scroll View.
We'll set the image for that
Image View to icon-about-email.
We'll select the image
like we've done before,
and choose Editor,
Size to Fit Content.
Then, we click out of the
image, so we can pick it up
and drag it into place.
We can drag another
label in, setting it
to a custom font using Georgia.
Drop the text size down to 13.
And for the text, we'll
write, goodasold@example.com.
We can stretch out the email
address label so it all fits.
And now we have a
little bit of a problem.
We want to be able to add two
more images and two more labels
for the phone number and
website for our store,
but we don't have any more
room in our Scroll View.
We've reached the
very bottom of it.
We could try to make
the Scroll View taller,
but the main view isn't
going to get taller,
so we still wouldn't be
able to drag and drop
more stuff in the storyboard.
One way to fix this
is a little weird.
We can take the Scroll View
object, which is currently
a subview of the main view.
And we can click and drag it
out of the View Controller
hierarchy and down
below, so that it's still
part of the Contact
View Controller scene,
but it's not part of the Contact
View Controller main view.
As you can see, the
Contact View Controller
is still in the
storyboard editor.
But up above, there's a new
associated view that looks just
like our Scroll View.
We can't even pick this
up and move it around.
It's sort of locked into
place above the Contact View
Controller.
What that enables us to do,
is click on the Scroll View,
and go into the Inspector
Panel's fifth page, which
is the Size Inspector.
Let's scroll down to the bottom,
so we can see this changing.
As we click on
the Height button,
we can see the height
getting bigger and bigger.
If we hold the button
down, we keep increasing
the height of the Scroll View.
Or, we can just key in
the value that we want.
It seems like 800 is going
to give us enough space
to put all of our content.
Now, we'll go duplicate the
icon in the Contact section
three times.
And, duplicate the
label three times.
And then change the images
for the two new icons
back in the Attributes panel
to icon-about-phone and icon-
about-website.
We'll also change our label
text for both the phone number
and website.
And, we can even
select and move all
of those labels and images
that looks a little more center
than before.
Now, we need to do is, still
with our Scroll View selected,
go back into the Size
Inspector and change it
to what it was before.
The main view height for
an iPhone 6S is 667 points.
So we can enter that, and now it
looks like our content is gone,
but it's not.
It's just sort of
hiding below the scroll.
Next, we can create
a Scroll View Outlet
to the Contact View Controller.
So we'll select our Contact
View Controller object.
Turn the Assistant
Editor back on.
And then control-click and
drag from the Scroll View,
down to the Contact View
Controller code and let go.
We'll call this
outlet scrollView.
It we'll actually change the
storage from Strong to Weak.
Every time we have
a subview that's
going to be attached to
a controller's main view,
we can mark that
subview as weak.
Then we hit Connect.
And now we have an outlet
to our Scroll View,
that's in our Contact
View Controller scene.
One last step.
We'll click on the Contact View
Controller in the storyboard,
and click Is Initial
View Controller,
so that this view is
the one that displays
when we build and run the app.
Now, let's see how we can
connect the Scroll View
to the Contact View Controller
with code back in the slides.
Our Scroll View and subviews
all set up properly.
But we've got another problem.
Our Scroll View isn't showing
up when we build and run
our app, because the
Scroll View is not
a subview of the main view.
Since we have an outlet to the
Scroll View in the storyboard,
we can fix that pretty easily
by typing, view dot add subview
and passing it that
Scroll View variable
between the parentheses.
This attaches the Scroll View
to the main view hierarchy.
And thus the Scroll View, and
everything else that's in it,
can now be seen.
And there it is.
But wait, we're
still not scrolling.
Well, that's because we've
set the Scroll View's frame,
but not the content size.
So the Scroll View doesn't
know how much content
it should try to display.
We need to explicitly tell
the Scroll View how wide
and how high the content
is that's inside of it.
The place to do this is
in another View Controller
function that runs
after viewDidload,
called viewWillLayoutSubviews.
Any time you're changing the
size of a subview with code,
you should do it
in this function.
Inside of that function, we'll
set the Scroll View's content
size equal to the output of
a function called CG size.
CG size takes two values
as parameters, a width
and a height.
And here, we'll use
the values 375 for the width
and 800 for the
height, since those
are the values we used
for the Scroll View
in the storyboarding when we
were originally laying out
content.
And now you can see, we've
got a working Scroll View
that displays all of
our content and allows
us to scroll up and
down to see things that
don't fit on the device screen.
Now it's time for you to create
a Scroll View in your project
and take some challenges.
And I'll see you
in the next level.
.