Now that we've got
a handle on how
to start working
with storyboards,
let's build the first screen
in our application: the product
screen.
This screen is going
to display an image.
It's going to have a label with
the name of the phone on top
of that.
And there's going to be
an Add to Cart button.
Let's jump back into
Xcode to set this up.
Before we try to connect up a
swift file to the storyboard,
let's delete this default
scene that the project gave us
when we selected Single
View Application Template.
We can delete this
view in the storyboard
by clicking the View controller
scene and then hitting Delete.
And we can also delete
the auto generated
view controller dot swift
file by right-clicking on it
and choosing Delete.
And then selecting
Move to Trash.
We can add a new view
controller to our storyboard
by dragging from the Object
panel to the Storyboard Editor.
The Object panel is
at the bottom right
corner of the
screen and contains
a list of all the objects
and views that you
can place in a storyboard.
View Controller is the
very first one in the list.
So we'll click and drag
that View Controller object
onto the Storyboard Editor.
And we can see that it
creates a new scene for us
complete with a view.
There's another
option that we have
to check because we
created this from scratch.
And that's Is Initial
View Controller,
which you can find
in the Attributes
panel of the Inspector.
Checking this makes
this view the one
that opens up whenever
this app runs.
Since the app we're going
to make in this course
will be built for
the iPhone 6s, we'll
also want to make sure
we're viewing as iPhone 6s
in this Trait Selection bar at
the bottom of the Scene Editor.
Ours is already set
to iPhone 6s here,
but you can see the
view change size
based on the device selected.
Now let's jump back
into some slides
to see what we need to do next.
Now that our Product View
Controller is set up,
we need to add a label, image,
and button to the Main view.
Whenever we put views
inside of the Main view,
we refer to them as subviews.
So let's jump back
into Xcode now
and add some of those subviews.
Let's start building
out this Main view
by dragging a label
from the Object panel.
We can either
search by scrolling
or just type in the
Search bar at the bottom,
and it will update the list
to show us only the views that
match our search term.
As we click and drag the
label onto the Main view,
you'll notice some
dotted blue lines appear.
They appear on the very left and
very right edges of the view.
And they also
appear in the center
to help you try to
center objects.
We'll drop this label right
in the middle of the screen.
We can set the text for
this label in the Attributes
Inspector.
And here we'll type "1937
desk phone" and hit Return.
When we do that, you can
see that our label text got
truncated down with three dots.
The reason this is
happening is that the width
of the label in the
storyboard is not big enough
to hold all of the text.
So since we know we want
this button to be centered,
we can just grab these anchors
on the sides of the label
and drag them all the way out
to the left and right edges.
Then back in the
Attributes Inspector,
we can center the label text.
That font doesn't look
too exciting either.
So we can change
the font properties
by clicking on the small T
icon next to the font name.
And instead of
using a system font,
we can choose a custom font.
Here, we'll use Damascus.
Set the style to bold.
And up the size to 24 points.
And then hit Done.
As you can see, the very top
line of the text looks cut off.
So we can drag the
labels height to make
it a little bigger so everything
is able to be displayed.
Now let's add an image
to our Main view.
The object that displays an
image is called an image view.
We can search for image
view in the Object panel.
Then we'll click and drag
it onto our Main view.
Notice that I'm not specifically
placing it anywhere yet.
The reason for that is
we need to actually add
the image file to
our Xcode project
before we can put it
inside of an image view.
Images in Xcode projects
are stored in something
called Asset Catalog.
And every project
by default gets
an assets dot xc assets file.
If we click on that asset
catalog in the Project
Navigator, you can see there's
not much in here right now.
You can add assets
to the catalog
by clicking the plus button that
appears in the second column
and choosing Import from
the menu that pops up.
We've created a folder called
Image files on our desktop that
will contain some of the images
we'll be using in this course.
You can see there's two
images currently in here.
So you can drag and
select both to import them
both at the same time.
Then hit Open, and they'll
be added to the project.
The first is called
button dash add to cart.
And the second is called
phone dash full screen 3.
And that's the image
we'll use right now.
Now, back in the
main.storyboard file,
make sure we've
selected the Image
View from the storyboard
Scene Navigator.
And then in the
Attributes panel,
we can see the first
option for the image
view is a field called Image.
If we click on the
dropdown, we'll
get a list of any images that
are in our asset catalog.
So we'll pick a
phone full screen 3.
When we do that it
doesn't quite look right.
The reason for this is that
the image view container
is one size, but the image we're
trying to display is another.
We can fix this by clicking on
the image in the Image view.
You'll know that it's selected
because everything around it
gets grayed out.
And then going to
the Editor menu
and choosing Size
to Fit Content.
This updates the
image view to be
the exact size of the image
displayed inside of it.
We can click on the
image view object
again so it's selected.
And then we can click
and drag the Image view
so that it fits perfectly
inside of our Main view.
There's one other
little problem though.
Our label just disappeared.
This is because we put the
image of you on top of the label
so it's completely obscuring it.
To fix this, just
rearrange the position
of the label and image view in
the Storyboard Scene Navigator.
Click and hold the image
view, and move it up
one spot so that the label
object is below the image view
object.
And now the label
appears on top.
Finally, let's add a
button to this interface.
Since we already have
the storyboard open,
we can just search for
button in the Object panel.
We want the first button
that comes up in the list.
And we'll click and drag it to
the center of the Main view.
We could just put some
text for this button.
But our designers have created
a custom button image that
fits the theme really well.
Over in the
Attributes Inspector,
we can choose the default
image for the button
and pick button-addtocart
from the list.
When we do this, you can see
that the original default
text for the button is
sitting on the right.
So again, in the
Attribute panel,
we can highlight
that default text,
hit Delete, and hit Enter.
Now we've got a
sharp looking button.
Let's build and run our app
to see what this looks like.
And there you have it our very
first product screen laid out
in a storyboard
that's displaying
great in the simulator.
Now it's your turn to
create some subviews
and take some challenges.
Remember, if you're
following along
in your own copy
of Xcode, you can
download all of the image
assets that we showed you
in this level.
Have fun.