[SINGING] Starting back
in the machine age,
the telephone had
just taken the stage.
No one predicted
its acceleration,
evolving all of
our communication.
Today we build with
storyboards, use
Xcode projects where
they're stored
Controllers with scroll,
navigate, and tables
Outlets, actions,
buttons and labels.
To code a phone is a learned
gift with the App Evolution
with Swift.
Welcome back to App
Evolution with Swift.
In this level, we'll
be looking at how
to connect two view controllers
together and then transition
between them.
We've got a great start
on our Table View.
But now, it's time to connect
that up to our Product View
Controller, so that
when we tap on a cell,
we can show some detailed
information about each product.
On the surface, doing
this is pretty simple
and involves something called
a Navigation Controller.
A navigation controller
manages moving
between any view controllers.
And the way you set it up is
to set one view controller
as the root view controller
for the navigation stack.
And then transition to any other
view controller with something
called a segue.
Yes.
That's how that word's
pronounced, segue.
And it literally
means to transition
from one thing to another.
So let's jump into Xcode
at a navigation controller
and create a segue.
Before we add a
navigation controller,
let's organize our
storyboard a bit.
If we option-click and drag
on the storyboard editor,
it zooms out so we can see
all of our view controllers
at once.
We want to organize
these a bit differently.
We'll take the Contact View
Controller and move it up.
We'll take the Products
Table View Controller
and move it all the
way to the left.
And, take the Product
View Controller
and move it to the right of
the Table View Controller.
Now, we'll click on the
Products Table View Controller
again and choose Editor, Embed
In, Navigation Controller.
Because our table
view controller
is now in this
navigation controller,
if we connect up segues
between other view controllers,
we'll be able to
transition between them.
We'll scroll a bit so we
can see both controllers.
And we'll right-click and
drag from the prototype cell
to the product view controller.
In the Segue Helper
that comes up,
we'll choose Show a
Segue, which means
we're going to show the
product view controller when
the product cell is tapped.
If we click on that segue,
we can give it a name.
In the Attributes
Inspector, we'll
type Show Product and
hit Enter, since that's
what this segue is responsible
for: showing a product.
Now if we build and
run our app and we
tap on one of those cells,
we see that it pushes over
to the product view controller.
Our segue's working great, so
now let's make a plan of attack
for passing data from the first
view controller to the second.
Every view controller, even
table view controllers,
has a function called
Prepare For Segue,
that gets called
whenever a segue happens.
We need to override
that function
and pass the product name to
the product view controller
during the segue.
We'll also need to add a product
name property to the product
view controller that
will store the value when
it gets passed over.
Adding that product
name property
in the ProductViewController
Swift file looks like this.
Note that we made this
variable an optional string,
because any data that we
don't know until the app runs,
has to be marked as optional.
Then we'll update the
product name labels text
to come from the
product name variable,
instead of just hard
coding a string.
Over in
ProductsTableViewController,
we'll add the Prepare
For Segue function.
Remember, this function runs
every time a segue happens.
So whatever we tap a cell in
our app, this function will run.
Since there can be multiple
segues in one controller,
we should first check of
the segue's identifier
is Show Product.
Remember when we set the
segue name in the storyboard?
Here's where that's paying off.
So inside of this
conditional, we
need a way to capture
the view controller
that we're transitioning
to, so that we can
set the product name property.
Looking at the documentation
for UIStoryboardsegue,
we can see that it has a
property called destination.
If we access that
property, we get a copy
of the view controller
we're transitioning to,
which in this case is our
product view controller.
So we can grab a copy of
that product view controller
like this, and assign it to
a variable named product VC.
But that alone is not enough.
Destination View Controller
returns a UI view controller,
but we want Swift to know
that this is specifically
a product view controller.
We can do that by adding
as ProductViewController
to the end of this statement.
As is a way to convert from
one data type to another.
So here we're trying to
let the compiler know
that our destination view
controller is, in fact,
a product view controller.
When we do that though, we run
into another little problem.
An error message that
says UIViewController
is not convertible to
ProductViewController.
Did you mean to use
as to force downcast?
That's a crazy error
message, right?
So what's happening
is the compiler
can't just take our
word for it and be sure
that the destination view
controller is a product view
controller.
And if it's not sure, it won't
compile your code and run.
That's because if
it guesses wrong,
the app's going to crash.
We can fix this by
again using optionals.
Remember, if we can't be
sure that a value will exist,
it should probably be
marked as optional.
Adding the question mark
to the end of the as word
here returns an optional
product view controller
and stores it in the
Product VC variable.
We can use that same
question mark trick
from before by
writing, Product VC?
dot product name and setting
that equal to a string.
Remember, this means
only set the product name
if the product VC exists.
It doesn't exist, the code won't
run, and therefore won't crash.
It's also important to
note that in this scenario,
the segue would still transition
between the view controllers.
We just wouldn't be sending
any extra data along
with the segue.
Now, whenever we
tap on a cell, we're
directed to the Product
View Controller.
And we're shown the text
that we set in the Prepare
For Segue method.
This is pretty powerful stuff.
We were able to get one view
controller to tell another view
controller what data to display.
So now it's your turn to
try passing some data along
with a segue in your app,
and take some challenges.
And I'll see you in
the next section.