Welcome back.
Now that we've got
some cells, we're
going to put some
content inside of them.
UI table view
cells actually come
preloaded with a few
subviews that we don't even
have to wire up
in the storyboard.
They're already wired up for us.
One is called image view.
And it can be used to
display a small image
in the left side of the cell.
Another is called text label.
And it's a UI label that
stretches across the rest
of the length of the cell.
We can create the
cell by writing
this line of code
here, which looks
at the storyboard for
any prototype cells
with a reuse identifier
of product cell
and then creates a cell
object when it finds one.
Now you might have
noticed that we're
creating this variable
with let instead of var.
If you have a
variable where you're
going to change it
after it's been created,
you want to use var.
But if not, you want
to use let, because it
makes the variable immutable.
So let's try setting the
cell's text label text
property to Hello friend.
If we try that, though, we get
an error that looks like this.
What's going on here?
Let's take a look at the docs
for the UI table view cell
to find out.
When we do that, we'll
see something interesting.
The text label property in the
cell isn't just a UI label.
It's a UI label with a
question mark after it.
That question mark means
that this label is optional.
It may or may not exist.
So what would that
mean if the text label
property didn't exist?
That would mean you'd
still have a cell object.
The text label property
wouldn't exist,
which means the text property
of it wouldn't exist.
So trying to set it
would crash the app.
This could actually
happen because it's
possible to create a custom cell
that doesn't have a text label
property.
That's why Swift has a way
to mark types as optional.
It's a way to say the data
could or could not exist.
Because the text
label is optional,
we first have to check if
it exists before we try
to set the text property on it.
And one way we can do that
is with a conditional.
We can check if cell dot
text label is not nil
and then set the text.
But inside of the
conditional, we'll
need to add an exclamation
point after the dot text label.
This is called force unwrapping.
And it's basically
saying, trust me,
I'm absolutely sure this
optional variable has
a value that's not nil.
So just use it like it exists.
There's an even better
way to write this
without using a conditional
using something called
optional chaining.
And that looks like this.
We just write cell dot text
label with a question mark
after it dot text
equals a string.
Adding that question mark
after an optional property
means first check
if this exists.
If it does exist, we'll continue
running this line of code
and setting the text.
And if it doesn't exist, we'll
stop running the line of code
right there, thus
avoiding a crash.
If we put that updated code back
in our cell creation function,
we can see that we've now
got five cells that all
have the text Hello friend.
The cell's image view
property is also optional.
So we can set it the same
way by adding a question mark
after the image view property.
Then we just set
that image property
to a UI image, named
something that matches
an image in our asset catalog.
Here, we're setting
it to image cell1,
because that's something we
just added to our asset catalog.
And you can see the result here.
Now let's jump back
into Xcode really quick
to see how we can customize
cells in the storyboard.
We can actually adjust some
properties of the prototype
cell from the storyboard.
For example, if we
click on the cell,
we can click and drag
the anchor at the bottom
to make the height
of the cell bigger.
We'll set it to 100 points high.
And that should
let the cell image
display its full resolution
if we build and run again.
Now you can see that
the cell height has changed.
And the image fits nicely
in there without resizing.
So why don't you try displaying
some dynamic data in your cells
and take some challenges?
And I'll see you
in the next level.