Welcome to App
Evolution with Swift.
I'm Jon Friskics.
And in this course,
you'll be learning
how to build your first
simple iOS app with Swift.
Swift is a programming language
that Apple introduced in
June 2014 for creating
iOS and OS X apps.
Apple has been updating Swift pretty regularly
with new features and fixes.
And as of the recording
of this course,
Swift is at version 3.0.
You can still make
apps with Objective-C.
But if you're just starting
to learn iOS development right
now, it probably makes sense
to learn with Swift first.
In this course, the simple
app we're going to build
is for the fictional
Good As Old phone
store, an antique
phone shop that sells
nothing but old telephones.
This app will have the ability
to view a list of old phones,
tap into that list to get
details about each phone,
and display a message when the
Add to Cart button is tapped.
We'll also have a
contact screen that
contains more content than
will fit on the device
that you need to
scroll through to read.
As we make the different
parts of this app,
we're going to be showing
you short screencasts of how
to work in Xcode, which is the
program that you write apps in.
So feel free to pause the video
and head over to the Mac App
Store to download Xcode
so you can follow along
on your own computer.
Xcode does only run on the Mac.
So if you're following
along with all of the code
that we're writing, you
will need a Mac in order
to be able to build an app.
If you're using a PC
or other computer,
you can still watch the videos
to see how all of this works.
[SINGING] Starting back
in the machine age,
the telephone had
just taken the stage.
No one predicted
its acceleration,
evolving all of
our communication.
Today we build with
storyboard, use Xcode projects
where they're
stored. Controllers
with scroll, navigating tables,
outlets, actions, buttons,
and labels.
To code a phone is a learned
gift with the App Evolution
with Swift.
Before we start
making an app, there's
a very important
prerequisite that we need:
to understand how
to make a sandwich.
No, really, stay with me.
Making iOS apps is actually
a lot like making a sandwich.
You need a pile of ingredients,
like bread, onions, and cheese,
maybe even some meat.
You also need a place to
prepare those ingredients,
different utensils like
a cutting board, knives,
and forks, maybe
even a plastic bag
to carry it with
you after it's made.
And not every
sandwich is the same.
But unless you can tell the
chef how to make it different,
you won't get the
sandwich you want.
In this analogy, UIKit is like
the parts of the sandwich.
It's a framework that contains
templates for standardized ways
to display data in your app,
like text, images, and buttons.
Xcode is like the
kitchen and utensils.
It contains all of the
tools you need to assemble
the parts of the sandwich.
It's a free program that's
provided by Apple that they
update a few times each year.
And Swift is the instructions
for making the sandwich.
You'll write Swift code in
Xcode that tells parts of UIKit
how to display your data.
And the chef?
Well, that's you.
So let's get started
by seeing how we
can create a project in Xcode.
After you've
downloaded Xcode, you
can open it by double-clicking
on the Xcode app, Alias,
or by finding it in your
applications folder.
In the splash
screen that pops up,
there's an option for
creating a new Xcode project.
The first thing you're asked
is to choose a new template
for your project.
Templates contain some common
starting configurations
for different kinds of apps.
For the app we're
making today, we're
going to choose Single View
Application because that's
the closest one to a bare
bones, default template,
and it will be a good
place for us to start.
Once we click Next,
we're shown a screen
where we can set some
options for our project.
This is where we want to
set the name of our app
for the product name.
Here we'll type GoodAsOldPhones.
You want to set the organization
name, which is usually
just your company name,
and then the organization
identifier, which is usually
in the form of com.companyname.
That automatically generates
a bundle identifier,
which is what identifies your
app as unique in the store.
We'll make sure we've got
Swift selected in the language
dropdown.
And for the device,
we'll choose iPhone.
That's because the
app we're making today
is only going to
be built to be run
on the iPhone, not a universal
app that runs on iPhone
or iPad.
We'll also leave these
three boxes unchecked
because we won't need any of
these features in our app.
Once we click Next,
we're asked where we
want to save this new project.
Here we'll save
it on the desktop.
After hitting Create, we can see
that Xcode opens up like this.
It might look kind
of intimidating.
But the screen we
see here is just
showing some general
options for our application.
We don't even need to
change any of these settings
to get started.
On the left, you'll see a panel
with eight icons on the top.
And that first icon contains
the project navigator.
This is where all of the
files in your project
will be displayed.
And you can open up
any one of those files
by single-clicking
on the filename.
Right now we'll open
up Main.storyboard.
And let's jump back
into some slides
real quick to talk about
what a storyboard is.
A storyboard is a way
to visually lay out
the screens in your
application as scenes
and create templates for
different UI elements
that can later be filled
in with real data.
You can also connect
different scenes together
and model how the user will
flow between them as they
interact with your app.
Each scene contains something
called a view controller that
manages one main view.
And everything else that
you see on the screen
goes inside of that main view.
Let's jump back into Xcode to
play around with the main view
and see if we can change
some of its properties.
To access the main view
for this storyboard,
we need to look in the
Storyboard Scene Editor panel.
If this panel isn't
showing up for you,
you can click on this icon at
the bottom left of the Editor
panel to expand and collapse it.
Then we can just
click on the arrow
to expand the View
Controller scene
and then click on
the View Controller
to expand the View and
Layout Guides inside of it.
The panel on the right is
called the Inspector panel.
If you don't see it
in your copy of Xcode,
you can click on this far
right icon in the toolbar
to make it appear and disappear.
The Inspector panel
contains six different ways
you can inspect the
parts of your storyboard.
Right now we'll click on
the fourth inspector, which
is the Attributes
Inspector, and there's
an attribute for this
view called Background.
If we click on the color
here and pick a new color
from the color
picker that comes up,
we can see that our view
changes color in the storyboard.
We can run this app
right now to see
what it looks like on this
computer using an iPhone
simulator.
You can choose what
device you want
to simulate from this
dropdown in the toolbar.
Here you can see we have
devices ranging from the iPad 2
all the way up to
the iPhone 6s Plus.
We'll choose iPhone
6s because that's
the size we'll be designing for.
Then you can just hit the
Play button in the toolbar,
and it will build and
run the application
and show you the simulator.
And here you can see the result
of setting the main views
background color to
red in the storyboard.
If you haven't been
following along already,
now's a great time
to jump into Xcode
and create your first project.
We've also created
some challenges for you
that help solidify some of the
most important concepts of iOS
development that you'll need
to know to build any iOS app.
So after you
complete those, we'll
see you in the next section.