[MUSIC PLAYING]
[SINGING] Starting back in
the machine age,
the telephone had
just taken the stage.
No one predicted its
acceleration evolving
all of our communication.
Today we build with storyboards
use Xcode projects
where they're stored.
Controllers with scroll,
navigate and tables. Outlets,
actions, buttons, and labels.
To code a phone
is a learned gift
with the App
Evolution with Swift.
Welcome back to App
Right now, we're passing just
product name into the product
view controller.
But that means we can only
pass one piece of data.
What if we wanted to also pass
stuff like the product image
name, or even the cell
image for that cell?
One thing we could do is
create multiple variables
inside of product
view controller
and pass values into them.
But that would quickly
get really messy.
Especially as we
have more and more
values that we wanted to pass.
So instead, we can
create a new class,
to hold all of those
variables as properties
and then just pass one
object over instead of three.
So let's jump into Xcode
to see how we can do that.
The first thing we'll do is
create a brand new Swift file.
And instead of choosing
a Cocoa Touch Class,
we'll just choose
an empty Swift file.
This is because we're
not going to need
to subclass any
of UI Kit classes,
so instead, we'll
just start fresh.
We'll name this file Product,
with a capital P dot Swift
and hit Create.
Since we do want this
to be a class file,
we'll type Class,
Product with a capital P,
and the opening and
closing curly brackets.
And we'll create three
variables in this class.
The first one will
be called Name,
and it will be an
optional string.
The next one will be
called Product image
and it will also be
an optional string.
Then the third
will be Cell Image,
and again it will be
an optional string.
Now we'll be able to create
objects of type product
and then we'll be able to
set each one of those three
variables for those
objects with dot notation
to the info for each
individual product.
We'll do that inside of our
products table view controller,
and we can create those product
objects inside of ViewDidLoad,
like this.
Then, for each one of
these product objects,
we need to set their name,
product image, and cell image.
We should also note that we've
added all of the remaining
necessary images to
our asset catalog,
so we've got all four full
screen images loaded in.
Now, we need to fill in the
rest of the data for each
of these products and
we'll skip ahead here
so you don't have to watch
us type all of this in.
The place we need to put all
this data is in an array.
And we don't even need our
product names array anymore,
so we'll rename it from
product names to products,
and instead of holding
a group of strings,
it will hold the group
of product objects.
We'll adjust the
name of the array
in ViewDidLoad to Products.
Instead of using these
hard-coded strings,
we can use the product one,
two, three, and four objects.
Down in the TableView
NumberOfRowsInSection function,
we can update this code to
unwrap the optional products
array instead of
product names, and also
make these unwrapped variable
names a little shorter.
Down in the TableView
CellForRowAtIndexPath function,
we'll do something similar.
We'll grab just
one product object,
and grab it from the products
array and let p equal
that product,
unwrapping the optional.
Then, we can adjust the
text label dot text,
to come from p dot name,
which is the string
inside of the product object.
We can move the image
setting code up as well.
But if we try to replace the
hard coded image with p dot
cell image, we'll get
an error, and that's
because cell image is optional.
And this UI image
initializer has
to be absolutely sure that the
image we're using to create it
exists.
So we can wrap
that too, by typing
if let i equals
p dot cell image,
and move the cell image
creation code inside of that
if let block.
Then we can use the unwrapped
image name from the variable i
and that will show the right
image view in the cell.
Next, down in the prepare
for segue function,
we can just pass a product
object over, instead
of a product name string,
and pulled the product
from the products array.
But we still get an error,
because the product view
controller still doesn't
have the right variable set.
So, if we go into the
product view controller,
we can change our product name
variable to just Product
and instead of having
a string as the type,
we'll use that product class.
Just like in the cell, we can
unwrap that product object,
pull our label code inside
of that unwrapped block,
and then grab p dot name
as the text for the label.
Then, we can unwrap the image
and copy the image view inside
of that block.
Instead of the hard coded image
name we can just pass
I, which is going to be
the unwrapped product image.
Now, if we build
and run the app,
you can see we've
got dynamic cell
images for each cell,
dynamic cell text,
and when we tap on
each one of the cells,
the correct text and
correct product image
is shown in the product
view controller.
And there you have it.
Now we're passing only one
object from our Products table
view controller, over to
the product view controller,
and we're able to read
from that object, any place
that we need to display data.
So, now it's your turn, to
go try adding a custom class
to hold your data
in your project,
and take some
challenges and I'll
see you in the wrap up video.
Screencasts!
Screencasts.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, screencasts.
I didn't see you there,
have you been here all along?
Screencasts.
I can't even do,
like, fake angry ...
This is what I talk
like when I'm angry.
If I ever talk to
you like this, it
means I'm really angry with you.
[LAUGHING]
Screencasts.
[Surprised Jon] Screencasts!
Oh OOOH.
[Jon á la Steve Jobs] Screencasts.
[LAUGHING]
What were you holding?
Just upholding the screencasts.
UI label
Just in case you need that for an out take.
[LAUGHING]