Welcome back.
In this section,
we'll be looking
at how we can display
dynamic table cell data.
So our table view is
working really well.
But it's always showing the
same label for each line,
because we're hard
coding the labels text.
Let's update our
table view to show
different data in each cell.
There's a few steps to
setting up dynamic data.
First, we need to create
a variable that will
store multiple product names.
And we'll use an array for this.
Next, we need to update all
of our table view controller
functions to use the data
from that array instead
of the hard coded data
that's in there right now.
Let's start by
creating an array.
Arrays can store multiple
values of a single type of data.
In this case, we'll
store strings.
We'll also need to make
this array optional.
We can set the product
names in viewDidLoad.
And we'll just make four
values for each one of our four
phones.
Now that we've got
some data, we need
to update the table view number
of rows in section function
to return the number of
items in the array instead
of a hard coded number.
Then, we'll need to update
the table view cell for row
at index path version
of the function
to display one of the names in
the array for each cell instead
of the hard coded text
that's in there now.
First, in the table view number
of rows in section function,
instead of just returning
a hardcoded number five,
we can instead return
the count property
of the product names' array.
Remember the product
names is an optional,
so we've got to put the
question mark after it when
we're writing it.
The count property returns the
number of items in the array.
So since we've got four array
items, we'll get four rows.
If we try to write
it just like this,
though, we're going
to run into an error.
The problem is that if
product names doesn't exist,
then the count property
won't exist either.
And therefore, this function
is returning an optional int,
instead of a regular int.
To fix this, we can write
if let pNames equals
product names, and inside
of that conditional return,
pNames dot count.
If let is a special way
of working with optionals
called optional binding.
And it combines checking
if the value exists
and assigning it to a new
variable all in one line.
Here, the if part is checking
if product names exists.
And if it does, it
copies everything
that's in product names
into a new variable called
pNames that's only accessible
inside of the if statement.
Since we know anything inside
of the if statement exists,
we can just return pNames.count.
And we can be sure that
we're returning a real int.
After this optional binding,
we also need to return zero.
That's because if the product
names' array doesn't exist,
we still need to return an int.
Next, we need to map
each item in the array
to a corresponding
cell in the table.
We've got an array
with four strings.
And we've got four cells.
So if each cell were
displaying the text of one
of those product names,
that would work out great.
So in the table view cell
for row index path function,
we first need to get a copy
the name from the array
and store it in a variable
called productName.
Just pretend for a minute
that we've got that already.
Then, since that productName
variable will be optional,
we can unwrap it with if let.
And if it does exist, we
set the cell's text label
dot text property to the
productName variable.
So as you may know,
each value in an array
can be accessed by
putting a number
inside of square brackets after
the array of variable name.
So here, the first value can
be accessed with the number zero,
like this.
And the last value can be
accessed with the number three,
like this.
Here we've set the productName
equal to the productNames
array at position zero.
Remember that this function runs
once for each row in the table.
So doing this will
actually set the name
to be the same
for all four rows.
We need that number
to be dynamic
based on the current cell
and not just always zero.
The answer lies in index paths.
Every cell in the table view
has an index path property.
And every index path
property has a row property.
And that row property
is just a number,
starting with zero
for the first cell,
ending at three for the last cell.
This is really convenient
because our array
also starts at zero and ends in three.
So instead of hard
coding a number,
we can use index paths dot row
for the index of the array.
And then we should
be good to go.
As you can see, each cell
now displays the name
from one item in the array.
It's now time for you to add
some dynamic data to your cells
and take some challenges.
And I'll see you in
the next section.