Welcome back.
In this section,
we're going to wire up
a button to trigger a
function in our Swift file.
And the function is going to
print a message to the console
every time that
we tap the button.
To do this, we'll create
a storyboard action,
which sends interaction
information from a view back
to a view controller.
Outlets meant that we can
have a controller change
the data that's
displayed, but Actions
mean that we can
have a user event run
some code in the controller.
Let's jump back into Xcode
to set this action up.
Creating an action is a lot
like creating an outlet.
We'll click on
the object that we
want to receive the
action, and control click
and drag down to the Swift file.
But instead of putting this
new code up top by the Outlets,
we'll go to the very last
line before the closing curly
bracket and let go of our mouse.
In the helper that
pops up, we'll
change the connection
from Outlet to Action.
The name we'll give
is addToCartPressed,
the type will be
AnyObject, and the event
should be Touch Up Inside.
There's a bunch of
different events
you can choose from
depending on what user
action you want to respond to.
For buttons, Touch Up
Inside makes the most sense
because it means that the
user tapped on the button
with their finger
and then let go,
or touched up, inside of
the button's hit area.
We'll leave the
argument as Sender.
When we hit Connect, you can see
that an entirely new function
got added with the @IBAction
keyword in front of it.
Let's jump back into some
slides to see how this works.
Here we can see the
addToCartPressed function
that we created
in our Swift file.
Every time we tap the button,
this function will run.
You might've also
noticed the arrow Void
at the end of this function.
That just means it
doesn't return any values
after it's done running.
It just runs whatever code is
inside of it, and then stops.
View Did Load was
like that, too,
but being explicit
about the return type
can help you quickly
see what a function is
responsible for doing.
If we add the Print function
with the message "Button tapped,"
whenever we tap the
button, that message
will be logged to the console.
If we build and run our app and
tap on the Add to Cart button,
we'll see that the
console pops up and logs
the message "Button tapped"
every time we tap the button.
Now it's your turn to create
an action in your project
and take some challenges, and
I'll see you in the next level.
.